window.quizData = [
  {
    question: "Who is the Comptroller and Auditor General (CAG) of India?",
    options: [
      "K Sanjay Murthy",
      "Girish Chandra Murmu",
      "Rajiv Mehrishi",
      "Vinod Rai",
    ],
    answer: "K Sanjay Murthy",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the current RBI Governor?",
    options: [
      "Sanjay Malhotra",
      "Shaktikanta Das",
      "Urjit Patel",
      "Raghuram Rajan",
    ],
    answer: "Sanjay Malhotra",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Director General of the International Solar Alliance?",
    options: [
      "Ashish Khanna",
      "Ajay Mathur",
      "Upendra Tripathy",
      "Ravi Kapoor",
    ],
    answer: "Ashish Khanna",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the President of the Federation of Indian Chambers of Commerce and Industry (FICCI)?",
    options: [
      "Harsh Vardhan Agarwal",
      "Subhrakant Panda",
      "Uday Shankar",
      "Naina Lal Kidwai",
    ],
    answer: "Harsh Vardhan Agarwal",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief Minister of Jharkhand?",
    options: ["Hemant Soren", "Babulal Marandi", "Raghubar Das", "Arjun Munda"],
    answer: "Hemant Soren",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Chairman of the National Legal Services Authority (NALSA)?",
    options: [
      "Supreme Court Justice Bhushan Ramakrishna Gavai",
      "Justice DY Chandrachud",
      "Justice NV Ramana",
      "Justice UU Lalit",
    ],
    answer: "Supreme Court Justice Bhushan Ramakrishna Gavai",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief Minister of Maharashtra?",
    options: [
      "Devendra Fadnavis",
      "Eknath Shinde",
      "Uddhav Thackeray",
      "Ajit Pawar",
    ],
    answer: "Devendra Fadnavis",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the head of the Airports Authority of India?",
    options: [
      "Vipin Kumar",
      "Sanjeev Kumar",
      "Arvind Singh",
      "Guruprasad Mohapatra",
    ],
    answer: "Vipin Kumar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chairman of Tata Trust?",
    options: [
      "Noel Naval Tata",
      "Ratan Tata",
      "Cyrus Mistry",
      "Natarajan Chandrasekaran",
    ],
    answer: "Noel Naval Tata",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chairperson of the National Commission for Women?",
    options: [
      "Vijaya Kishor Rahatkar",
      "Rekha Sharma",
      "Lalitha Kumaramangalam",
      "Jayanti Patnaik",
    ],
    answer: "Vijaya Kishor Rahatkar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Director General of the Indian Coast Guard?",
    options: [
      "Parmesh Shivamani",
      "Rajendra Singh",
      "Krishnaswamy Natarajan",
      "Virender Pathania",
    ],
    answer: "Parmesh Shivamani",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the 51st Chief Justice of India (till May 13, 2025)?",
    options: [
      "Justice Sanjiv Khanna",
      "Justice DY Chandrachud",
      "Justice NV Ramana",
      "Justice UU Lalit",
    ],
    answer: "Justice Sanjiv Khanna",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief Minister of Haryana?",
    options: [
      "Nayab Singh Saini",
      "Manohar Lal Khattar",
      "Bhupinder Singh Hooda",
      "Om Prakash Chautala",
    ],
    answer: "Nayab Singh Saini",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Chief Minister of Jammu & Kashmir and who is the Deputy CM?",
    options: [
      "Chief Minister: Omar Abdullah, Deputy CM: Surinder Kumar Chaudhary",
      "Chief Minister: Mehbooba Mufti, Deputy CM: Nirmal Singh",
      "Chief Minister: Ghulam Nabi Azad, Deputy CM: Tara Chand",
      "Chief Minister: Farooq Abdullah, Deputy CM: Mushtaq Ahmed Shah",
    ],
    answer:
      "Chief Minister: Omar Abdullah, Deputy CM: Surinder Kumar Chaudhary",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief of Air Staff of the Indian Air Force?",
    options: [
      "Air Marshal Amar Preet Singh",
      "Air Chief Marshal VR Chaudhari",
      "Air Marshal RKS Bhadauria",
      "Air Marshal BS Dhanoa",
    ],
    answer: "Air Marshal Amar Preet Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Vice Chief of Air Staff?",
    options: [
      "Air Marshal SP Dharkar",
      "Air Marshal Vivek Ram Chaudhari",
      "Air Marshal Anil Khosla",
      "Air Marshal Harjit Singh Arora",
    ],
    answer: "Air Marshal SP Dharkar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Director General of the Narcotics Control Bureau?",
    options: [
      "Anurag Garg",
      "Satya Narayan Pradhan",
      "Rakesh Asthana",
      "Rajesh Ranjan",
    ],
    answer: "Anurag Garg",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Chairperson of the National Human Rights Commission (NHRC)?",
    options: [
      "Vijaya Bharathi Sayani",
      "Arun Kumar Mishra",
      "Kailash Satyarthi",
      "Ravi Shankar Prasad",
    ],
    answer: "Vijaya Bharathi Sayani",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chairman and CEO of the Railway Board?",
    options: ["Satish Kumar", "VK Tripathi", "Suneet Sharma", "Ashwani Lohani"],
    answer: "Satish Kumar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the first Indian President of the Olympic Council of Asia?",
    options: [
      "Randhir Singh",
      "Narinder Batra",
      "Rajeev Mehta",
      "IOA President P.T. Usha",
    ],
    answer: "Randhir Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the International Olympic Committee member from India?",
    options: ["Nita Ambani", "Anil Khanna", "Abhinav Bindra", "P.T. Usha"],
    answer: "Nita Ambani",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the first Indian Ambassador of the International Table Tennis Federation?",
    options: ["Sharath Kamal", "Manika Batra", "G Sathiyan", "Achanta Kamal"],
    answer: "Sharath Kamal",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chef de Mission for the Paris Paralympics 2024?",
    options: [
      "Satya Prakash Sangwan",
      "Deepa Malik",
      "Avani Lekhara",
      "Devendra Jhajharia",
    ],
    answer: "Satya Prakash Sangwan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chef de Mission for the Paris Olympics 2024?",
    options: [
      "Gagan Narang",
      "Rajyavardhan Rathore",
      "Abhinav Bindra",
      "Neeraj Chopra",
    ],
    answer: "Gagan Narang",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Director General of the National Security Guard (NSG)?",
    options: [
      "B Srinivasan",
      "Kuldeep Singh",
      "Mohanlal Bhardwaj",
      "Rajesh Kumar",
    ],
    answer: "B Srinivasan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Director of Enforcement Directorate (ED)?",
    options: [
      "Rahul Navin",
      "Sanjay Kumar Mishra",
      "SK Gupta",
      "Rakesh Asthana",
    ],
    answer: "Rahul Navin",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chairperson of NASSCOM?",
    options: [
      "Sindhu Gangadharan",
      "Debjani Ghosh",
      "Rishad Premji",
      "Keshav Murugesh",
    ],
    answer: "Sindhu Gangadharan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the 27th Chairman of the State Bank of India (SBI)?",
    options: [
      "Challa Sreenivasulu Setty",
      "Dinesh Khara",
      "Rajnish Kumar",
      "Arundhati Bhattacharya",
    ],
    answer: "Challa Sreenivasulu Setty",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the new Cabinet Secretary of India?",
    options: ["TV Somnathan", "Rajiv Gauba", "Ajay Seth", "VK Pandian"],
    answer: "TV Somnathan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief of the Intelligence Bureau (IB)?",
    options: [
      "Tapam Kumar Deka",
      "Arvind Kumar",
      "Rajnish Kumar",
      "Anil Dhasmana",
    ],
    answer: "Tapam Kumar Deka",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Director General of the Border Security Force (BSF)?",
    options: [
      "Daljit Singh Chaudhary",
      "Pankaj Kumar Singh",
      "RK Mishra",
      "Anil Kumar Jha",
    ],
    answer: "Daljit Singh Chaudhary",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Director General of the Central Industrial Security Force (CISF)?",
    options: [
      "Rajwinder Singh Bhatti",
      "Subodh Kumar Jaiswal",
      "Maheshwar Dayal",
      "Rajnish Kumar",
    ],
    answer: "Rajwinder Singh Bhatti",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Director General of the Sashastra Seema Bal (SSB)?",
    options: [
      "Amrit Mohan Prasad",
      "Sanjeev Kumar Yadav",
      "Kumar Rajesh Chandra",
      "Rajiv Sharma",
    ],
    answer: "Amrit Mohan Prasad",
  },
  {
    question: "Who are the new Election Commissioners of India?",
    options: [
      "Gyanesh Kumar, Sukhbir Sandhu",
      "Rajiv Kumar, Anup Chandra Pandey",
      "Sunil Arora, Ashok Lavasa",
      "Harish Kumar, Ravi Kumar",
    ],
    answer: "Gyanesh Kumar, Sukhbir Sandhu",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Director General of the Employees' State Insurance Corporation (ESIC)?",
    options: [
      "Ashok Kumar Singh",
      "Rajendra Kumar",
      "Manoj Yadav",
      "Arvind Kumar",
    ],
    answer: "Ashok Kumar Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chairman and Managing Director of SIDBI?",
    options: [
      "Manoj Mittal",
      "Sivasubramanian Ramann",
      "Rajnish Kumar",
      "Challa Sreenivasulu Setty",
    ],
    answer: "Manoj Mittal",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the 2nd woman Chairperson of the Union Public Service Commission (UPSC)?",
    options: [
      "Preeti Sudan",
      "Mrs. RM Bathen",
      "Aruna Sundararajan",
      "Kiran Bedi",
    ],
    answer: "Preeti Sudan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the 1st woman Chairperson of UPSC?",
    options: ["Mrs. RM Bathen", "Preeti Sudan", "Indira Sawhney", "Leela Seth"],
    answer: "Mrs. RM Bathen",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the National Ambassador for UNICEF India?",
    options: [
      "Kareena Kapoor Khan",
      "Priyanka Chopra",
      "Amitabh Bachchan",
      "Sachin Tendulkar",
    ],
    answer: "Kareena Kapoor Khan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Director of the International Film Festival of India (IFFI), Goa?",
    options: ["Shekhar Kapur", "Anurag Kashyap", "Ramesh Sippy", "Zoya Akhtar"],
    answer: "Shekhar Kapur",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Brand Ambassador for the Ports Ministry?",
    options: ["Manu Bhaker", "PV Sindhu", "Neeraj Chopra", "Mary Kom"],
    answer: "Manu Bhaker",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the first woman Chancellor of Aligarh Muslim University (AMU)?",
    options: [
      "Naima Khatoon",
      "Begum Rokeya",
      "Fathima Beevi",
      "Dr. Zakir Naik",
    ],
    answer: "Naima Khatoon",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Chief of the Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR)?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Kalaiselvi",
      "Dr. Renu Swarup",
      "Dr. Vijay Raghavan",
      "Dr. G. Satheesh Reddy",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. Kalaiselvi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chairperson of the National Medical Commission?",
    options: [
      "B.N. Gangadhar",
      "Dr. Randeep Guleria",
      "Dr. Naresh Trehan",
      "Dr. Devi Shetty",
    ],
    answer: "B.N. Gangadhar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Director General of the National Testing Agency (NTA)?",
    options: [
      "Pradeep Singh Kharola",
      "Anil Sahasrabudhe",
      "Prof. Nageshwar Rao",
      "Vinay Kumar Tripathi",
    ],
    answer: "Pradeep Singh Kharola",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the 18th Speaker of the Lok Sabha?",
    options: ["Om Birla", "Sumitra Mahajan", "Meira Kumar", "Balram Jakhar"],
    answer: "Om Birla",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief of Army Staff of India?",
    options: [
      "General Upendra Dwivedi",
      "General Manoj Pande",
      "General Bipin Rawat",
      "General Dalbir Singh Suhag",
    ],
    answer: "General Upendra Dwivedi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Vice Chief of Army Staff of India?",
    options: [
      "General NS Raja Subramani",
      "Lieutenant General Anil Chauhan",
      "Lieutenant General Yogendra Dimri",
      "General VK Singh",
    ],
    answer: "General NS Raja Subramani",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Principal Secretary to the Prime Minister of India?",
    options: [
      "Pramod Kumar Mishra",
      "Nripendra Misra",
      "Ajit Doval",
      "PK Sinha",
    ],
    answer: "Pramod Kumar Mishra",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the National Security Advisor to the Prime Minister of India?",
    options: ["Ajit Doval", "Vikram Sood", "Samant Goel", "Shivshankar Menon"],
    answer: "Ajit Doval",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Principal Director General of the Press Information Bureau?",
    options: [
      "Dhirendra Ojha",
      "Jaideep Bhatnagar",
      "Frank Noronha",
      "Ravi Mittal",
    ],
    answer: "Dhirendra Ojha",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief of the Indian Tibetan Border Police?",
    options: ["Rahul Rasgotra", "Anand Kumar", "SS Deswal", "RK Pachnanda"],
    answer: "Rahul Rasgotra",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief of the Central Board of Direct Taxes (CBDT)?",
    options: [
      "Ravi Aggarwal",
      "Nitin Gupta",
      "Sangeeta Singh",
      "Pramod Chandra Mody",
    ],
    answer: "Ravi Aggarwal",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the first woman naval helicopter pilot in India?",
    options: [
      "Anamika B. Rajeev",
      "Shivangi Singh",
      "Mohana Singh",
      "Bhavna Kant",
    ],
    answer: "Anamika B. Rajeev",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief of Naval Staff of India?",
    options: [
      "Admiral Dinesh Kumar Tripathi",
      "Admiral R Hari Kumar",
      "Admiral Sunil Lanba",
      "Admiral DK Joshi",
    ],
    answer: "Admiral Dinesh Kumar Tripathi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chairman of the 16th Finance Commission of India?",
    options: [
      "Arvind Panagariya",
      "N.K. Singh",
      "C. Rangarajan",
      "Raghuram Rajan",
    ],
    answer: "Arvind Panagariya",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Chairman of the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (TRAI)?",
    options: [
      "Anil Kumar Lahoti",
      "Ram Sewak Sharma",
      "PD Vaghela",
      "R.S. Sharma",
    ],
    answer: "Anil Kumar Lahoti",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the new Lokpal of India?",
    options: [
      "Justice AM Khanwilkar",
      "Justice Pinaki Chandra Ghose",
      "Justice NV Ramana",
      "Justice SA Bobde",
    ],
    answer: "Justice AM Khanwilkar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Director General of the National Investigation Agency (NIA)?",
    options: [
      "Sadanand Vasant Date",
      "Dinkar Gupta",
      "Y.C. Modi",
      "Sharad Kumar",
    ],
    answer: "Sadanand Vasant Date",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Chairman of the National Commission for Scheduled Castes?",
    options: [
      "Kishor Makwana",
      "Ram Shankar Katheria",
      "Vijay Sampla",
      "Suraj Bhan",
    ],
    answer: "Kishor Makwana",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Brand Ambassador for Tobacco Control in India?",
    options: [
      "PV Sindhu",
      "Amitabh Bachchan",
      "Kangana Ranaut",
      "Neeraj Chopra",
    ],
    answer: "PV Sindhu",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Chairman of the Central Board of Secondary Education (CBSE)?",
    options: ["Rahul Singh", "Vineet Joshi", "Manoj Ahuja", "Anita Karwal"],
    answer: "Rahul Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of the Supreme Court Bar Association?",
    options: [
      "Kapil Sibal",
      "Harish Salve",
      "Abhishek Manu Singhvi",
      "Arvind Datar",
    ],
    answer: "Kapil Sibal",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chairman of the Staff Selection Commission (SSC)?",
    options: [
      "S. Gopalakrishnan",
      "Rajesh Agrawal",
      "Ashim Khurana",
      "KK Jalan",
    ],
    answer: "S. Gopalakrishnan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Vice Chancellor of India’s first Artificial Intelligence university, Universal AI University (Mumbai)?",
    options: [
      "Simon Mak",
      "Dr. Ramesh Pokhriyal",
      "Dr. Shankar B. Kulkarni",
      "Dr. Sushma Chauhan",
    ],
    answer: "Simon Mak",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Pro Tem Speaker of the Lok Sabha?",
    options: [
      "Bhartruhari Mahtab",
      "Om Birla",
      "Ravi Shankar Prasad",
      "Maneka Gandhi",
    ],
    answer: "Bhartruhari Mahtab",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief Minister of Sikkim?",
    options: [
      "Prem Singh Tamang",
      "Pawan Kumar Chamling",
      "Bhim Bahadur Gurung",
      "Nar Bahadur Bhandari",
    ],
    answer: "Prem Singh Tamang",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief Minister of Odisha?",
    options: [
      "Mohan Charan Majhi",
      "Naveen Patnaik",
      "Giridhar Gamang",
      "J.B. Patnaik",
    ],
    answer: "Mohan Charan Majhi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief Minister of Arunachal Pradesh?",
    options: ["Pema Khandu", "Dorjee Khandu", "Kalikho Pul", "Gegong Apang"],
    answer: "Pema Khandu",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief Minister of Andhra Pradesh?",
    options: [
      "Chandrababu Naidu",
      "YS Jagan Mohan Reddy",
      "K. Rosaiah",
      "N.T. Rama Rao",
    ],
    answer: "Chandrababu Naidu",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Chief Minister of Delhi?",
    options: ["Atishi", "Arvind Kejriwal", "Manish Sisodia", "Sheila Dikshit"],
    answer: "Atishi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Ambassador of India to the United Nations?",
    options: [
      "P. Harish",
      "Syed Akbaruddin",
      "T.S. Tirumurti",
      "Hardeep Singh Puri",
    ],
    answer: "P. Harish",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Burkina Faso?",
    options: [
      "Rimtalba Jean Emmanuel Ouedraogo",
      "Paul-Henri Sandaogo Damiba",
      "Christophe Dabire",
      "Roch Marc Christian Kabore",
    ],
    answer: "Rimtalba Jean Emmanuel Ouedraogo",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Ghana?",
    options: [
      "John Mahama",
      "Nana Akufo-Addo",
      "Jerry John Rawlings",
      "John Atta Mills",
    ],
    answer: "John Mahama",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of the International Hockey Federation?",
    options: ["Tayyab Ikram", "Narinder Batra", "Leandro Negre", "Jan Albers"],
    answer: "Tayyab Ikram",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the first female President of Namibia?",
    options: [
      "Netumbo Nandi Ndaitwa",
      "Hage Geingob",
      "Sam Nujoma",
      "Saara Kuugongelwa-Amadhila",
    ],
    answer: "Netumbo Nandi Ndaitwa",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of the Asian Development Bank?",
    options: [
      "Masato Kanda",
      "Takehiko Nakao",
      "Haruhiko Kuroda",
      "Yoshihiko Noda",
    ],
    answer: "Masato Kanda",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Director-General of the World Trade Organization (WTO)?",
    options: [
      "Ngozi Okonjo-Iweala",
      "Pascal Lamy",
      "Roberto Azevedo",
      "Supachai Panitchpakdi",
    ],
    answer: "Ngozi Okonjo-Iweala",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the 47th President of the United States, and who is the Vice President?",
    options: [
      "Donald Trump and JD Vance",
      "Joe Biden and Kamala Harris",
      "Ron DeSantis and Nikki Haley",
      "Barack Obama and Joe Biden",
    ],
    answer: "Donald Trump and JD Vance",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which political party does the 47th President of the United States belong to?",
    options: [
      "Republican Party",
      "Democratic Party",
      "Independent Party",
      "Green Party",
    ],
    answer: "Republican Party",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Director of National Intelligence in the United States?",
    options: ["Tulsi Gabbard", "Avril Haines", "Mike Pompeo", "James Clapper"],
    answer: "Tulsi Gabbard",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the head of the FBI?",
    options: [
      "Kash Patel",
      "Christopher Wray",
      "Robert Mueller",
      "James Comey",
    ],
    answer: "Kash Patel",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Botswana?",
    options: ["Duma Boko", "Mokgweetsi Masisi", "Ian Khama", "Festus Mogae"],
    answer: "Duma Boko",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Brand Ambassador for Thailand Tourism?",
    options: [
      "Sonu Sood",
      "Amitabh Bachchan",
      "Priyanka Chopra",
      "Shah Rukh Khan",
    ],
    answer: "Sonu Sood",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Mauritius?",
    options: [
      "Navin Ramgoolam",
      "Pravind Jugnauth",
      "Paul Berenger",
      "Anerood Jugnauth",
    ],
    answer: "Navin Ramgoolam",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Mali?",
    options: [
      "Abdoulaye Maiga",
      "Choguel Kokalla Maiga",
      "Soumeylou Boubeye Maiga",
      "Modibo Keita",
    ],
    answer: "Abdoulaye Maiga",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the head of the interim government in Bangladesh?",
    options: [
      "Muhammad Yunus",
      "Sheikh Hasina",
      "Ziaur Rahman",
      "Hossain Mohammad Ershad",
    ],
    answer: "Muhammad Yunus",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the first Indian President of the International Mind Sports Association (IMSA)?",
    options: [
      "Nandan Kumar Jha",
      "Vishy Anand",
      "Pullela Gopichand",
      "Prakash Padukone",
    ],
    answer: "Nandan Kumar Jha",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Haiti?",
    options: [
      "Alix Didier Fils-Aime",
      "Ariel Henry",
      "Jean-Claude Duvalier",
      "Laurent Lamothe",
    ],
    answer: "Alix Didier Fils-Aime",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Vietnam?",
    options: [
      "Luong Cuong",
      "Nguyen Xuan Phuc",
      "Tran Dai Quang",
      "Nguyen Phu Trong",
    ],
    answer: "Luong Cuong",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Indonesia?",
    options: [
      "Prabowo Subianto",
      "Joko Widodo",
      "Susilo Bambang Yudhoyono",
      "Megawati Sukarnoputri",
    ],
    answer: "Prabowo Subianto",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Tunisia?",
    options: [
      "Kais Saied",
      "Beji Caid Essebsi",
      "Zine El Abidine Ben Ali",
      "Rached Ghannouchi",
    ],
    answer: "Kais Saied",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Botswana?",
    options: ["Duma Boko", "Mokgweetsi Masisi", "Ian Khama", "Festus Mogae"],
    answer: "Duma Boko",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the CEO of Sony Pictures Entertainment?",
    options: ["Ravi Ahuja", "Tony Vinciquerra", "Michael Lynton", "Amy Pascal"],
    answer: "Ravi Ahuja",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Secretary General of NATO?",
    options: [
      "Mark Rutte",
      "Jens Stoltenberg",
      "Anders Fogh Rasmussen",
      "Jaap de Hoop Scheffer",
    ],
    answer: "Mark Rutte",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Sri Lanka?",
    options: [
      "Anura Kumara Dissanayake",
      "Ranil Wickremesinghe",
      "Maithripala Sirisena",
      "Gotabaya Rajapaksa",
    ],
    answer: "Anura Kumara Dissanayake",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Sri Lanka?",
    options: [
      "Harini Amarasuriya",
      "Dinesh Gunawardena",
      "Ranil Wickremesinghe",
      "Mahinda Rajapaksa",
    ],
    answer: "Harini Amarasuriya",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Jordan?",
    options: [
      "Jafar Hassan",
      "Bisher Al-Khasawneh",
      "Abdullah Ensour",
      "Omar Razzaz",
    ],
    answer: "Jafar Hassan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Algeria?",
    options: [
      "Abdelmadjid Tebboune",
      "Abdelaziz Bouteflika",
      "Ahmed Ouyahia",
      "Ali Benflis",
    ],
    answer: "Abdelmadjid Tebboune",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Thailand?",
    options: [
      "Paetongtarn Shinawatra",
      "Prayut Chan-o-cha",
      "Yingluck Shinawatra",
      "Thaksin Shinawatra",
    ],
    answer: "Paetongtarn Shinawatra",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Rwanda?",
    options: [
      "Paul Kagame",
      "Juvénal Habyarimana",
      "Pasteur Bizimungu",
      "Faustin Twagiramungu",
    ],
    answer: "Paul Kagame",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Pakistan?",
    options: [
      "Shehbaz Sharif",
      "Imran Khan",
      "Nawaz Sharif",
      "Yousaf Raza Gillani",
    ],
    answer: "Shehbaz Sharif",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of South Africa?",
    options: ["Cyril Ramaphosa", "Jacob Zuma", "Thabo Mbeki", "Nelson Mandela"],
    answer: "Cyril Ramaphosa",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Nepal?",
    options: [
      "KP Oli",
      "Puspa Kamal Dahal",
      "Sher Bahadur Deuba",
      "Sushil Koirala",
    ],
    answer: "KP Oli",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of FATF (Financial Action Task Force)?",
    options: [
      "Elisa de Anda Madrazo",
      "Marcus Pleyer",
      "Raja Kumar",
      "Marshall Billingslea",
    ],
    answer: "Elisa de Anda Madrazo",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Iran?",
    options: [
      "Masoud Pezeshkian",
      "Ebrahim Raisi",
      "Hassan Rouhani",
      "Mahmoud Ahmadinejad",
    ],
    answer: "Masoud Pezeshkian",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Britain?",
    options: ["Keir Starmer", "Rishi Sunak", "Boris Johnson", "Jeremy Corbyn"],
    answer: "Keir Starmer",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of the European Commission?",
    options: [
      "Ursula von der Leyen",
      "Jean-Claude Juncker",
      "José Manuel Barroso",
      "Romano Prodi",
    ],
    answer: "Ursula von der Leyen",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is Mexico's first woman President?",
    options: [
      "Claudia Sheinbaum",
      "Josefina Vázquez Mota",
      "Rosario Robles",
      "Elena Poniatowska",
    ],
    answer: "Claudia Sheinbaum",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Pakistan?",
    options: [
      "Asif Ali Zardari",
      "Arif Alvi",
      "Mamnoon Hussain",
      "Pervez Musharraf",
    ],
    answer: "Asif Ali Zardari",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of the Netherlands?",
    options: ["Dick Schoof", "Mark Rutte", "Piet de Jong", "Wim Kok"],
    answer: "Dick Schoof",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the first female Prime Minister of the Democratic Republic of the Congo?",
    options: [
      "Judith Suminwa",
      "Jeanine Mabunda",
      "Eve Bazaiba",
      "Olive Lembe",
    ],
    answer: "Judith Suminwa",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Slovakia?",
    options: [
      "Peter Pellegrini",
      "Zuzana Čaputová",
      "Andrej Kiska",
      "Ivan Gašparovič",
    ],
    answer: "Peter Pellegrini",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Managing Director of the International Monetary Fund (IMF)?",
    options: [
      "Kristalina Georgieva",
      "Christine Lagarde",
      "Dominique Strauss-Kahn",
      "Rodrigo Rato",
    ],
    answer: "Kristalina Georgieva",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Singapore?",
    options: [
      "Lawrence Wong",
      "Lee Hsien Loong",
      "Goh Chok Tong",
      "Halimah Yacob",
    ],
    answer: "Lawrence Wong",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of the International Court of Justice?",
    options: [
      "Lebanese Judge Nawaf Salam",
      "Joan Donoghue",
      "Peter Tomka",
      "Ronny Abraham",
    ],
    answer: "Lebanese Judge Nawaf Salam",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Yemen?",
    options: [
      "Ahmed Awad bin Mubarak",
      "Maeen Abdulmalik Saeed",
      "Ali Mohammed Mujawar",
      "Abdul Qadir Bajamal",
    ],
    answer: "Ahmed Awad bin Mubarak",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Venezuela?",
    options: ["Nicolas Maduro", "Hugo Chavez", "Juan Guaido", "Rafael Caldera"],
    answer: "Nicolas Maduro",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the President of Russia (serving his 5th term)?",
    options: [
      "Vladimir Putin",
      "Dmitry Medvedev",
      "Boris Yeltsin",
      "Mikhail Gorbachev",
    ],
    answer: "Vladimir Putin",
  },
  {
    question: "Which awards has Prime Minister Modi received?",
    options: [
      "Order of Excellence, Guyana; Honorary Order of Freedom, Barbados",
      "Grand Commander of the Order of Niger; Dominica Award of Honor",
      "Bhutan’s Order of the Druk Gyalpo ‘Ngadag Pel Gi Khorlo’",
      "Both A and B",
    ],
    answer: "Both A and B",
  },
  {
    question: "What did PM Modi gift to the Nigerian President?",
    options: [
      "Kolhapur’s ‘Silofar Panchamrit Kalash’",
      "Banaras Silk Saree",
      "Sandalwood Carving",
      "Gujarati Handicraft",
    ],
    answer: "Kolhapur’s ‘Silofar Panchamrit Kalash’",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who received the Companion of the Order of Fiji from President William Katonivere?",
    options: [
      "Droupadi Murmu",
      "Narendra Modi",
      "Sushma Swaraj",
      "Pranab Mukherjee",
    ],
    answer: "Droupadi Murmu",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who received the Grand Collar of the Order of Timor-Leste from President José Ramos-Horta?",
    options: [
      "Droupadi Murmu",
      "Narendra Modi",
      "Sonia Gandhi",
      "Ram Nath Kovind",
    ],
    answer: "Droupadi Murmu",
  },
  {
    question: "Which award did Prime Minister Modi receive from Bhutan?",
    options: [
      "Order of the Druk Gyalpo ‘Ngadag Pel Gi Khorlo’",
      "Order of Freedom, Barbados",
      "Dominica Award of Honor",
      "Grand Commander of the Order of Niger",
    ],
    answer: "Order of the Druk Gyalpo ‘Ngadag Pel Gi Khorlo’",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the theme of the 55th International Film Festival of India, Goa?",
    options: [
      "Young Filmmakers: The Future is Now",
      "Cinema for a Better Future",
      "Stories of Resilience",
      "Reimagining Cinema",
    ],
    answer: "Young Filmmakers: The Future is Now",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Best Film Award at the 55th International Film Festival of India?",
    options: [
      "Saule Bliuvaite for Toxic (Lithuania)",
      "Levan Akin for Crossing (Georgia)",
      "Phillip Noyce for Rabbit-Proof Fence",
      "Manoj Bajpayee for The Fable",
    ],
    answer: "Saule Bliuvaite for Toxic (Lithuania)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was awarded the Indian Film Personality of the Year at the 55th IFFI?",
    options: [
      "Vikrant Massey",
      "Naseeruddin Shah",
      "Rajkummar Rao",
      "Irrfan Khan",
    ],
    answer: "Vikrant Massey",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who received the Satyajit Ray Lifetime Achievement Award at the 55th IFFI?",
    options: [
      "Phillip Noyce (Australia)",
      "Steven Spielberg",
      "Christopher Nolan",
      "Quentin Tarantino",
    ],
    answer: "Phillip Noyce (Australia)",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the ICFT UNESCO Gandhi Medal at the 55th IFFI?",
    options: [
      "Levan Akin for Crossing (Georgia)",
      "Saule Bliuvaite for Toxic (Lithuania)",
      "Phillip Noyce for Rabbit-Proof Fence",
      "Manoj Bajpayee for The Fable",
    ],
    answer: "Levan Akin for Crossing (Georgia)",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the name of the Prasar Bharti OTT platform?",
    options: ["Waves", "Doordarshan+", "Prasar Stream", "Bharatiya Vision"],
    answer: "Waves",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which film won Best Film at the 38th Leeds International Film Festival?",
    options: [
      "The Fable (Manoj Bajpayee)",
      "Toxic (Saule Bliuvaite)",
      "Crossing (Levan Akin)",
      "The Tree of Life (Terrence Malick)",
    ],
    answer: "The Fable (Manoj Bajpayee)",
  },
  {
    question: "Who received the Indira Gandhi Peace Prize for 2024?",
    options: [
      "Veronica Michelle Bachelet",
      "Angela Merkel",
      "Aung San Suu Kyi",
      "Jacinda Ardern",
    ],
    answer: "Veronica Michelle Bachelet",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Booker Prize for 2024?",
    options: [
      "Samantha Harvey for Orbital",
      "Hilary Mantel for The Mirror & the Light",
      "Salman Rushdie for Quichotte",
      "Marlon James for Black Leopard, Red Wolf",
    ],
    answer: "Samantha Harvey for Orbital",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 73rd Miss Universe title?",
    options: [
      "Denmark’s Victoria Kjaer Thelvig",
      "India’s Harnaaz Sandhu",
      "USA’s R’Bonney Gabriel",
      "Philippines’ Celeste Cortesi",
    ],
    answer: "Denmark’s Victoria Kjaer Thelvig",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Organization for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons (OPCW) The Hague Prize 2024?",
    options: [
      "Indian Chemical Council",
      "Chemical Industry Association of Japan",
      "American Chemical Society",
      "European Chemical Council",
    ],
    answer: "Indian Chemical Council",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Rohini Nayyar Award 2024?",
    options: [
      "Anil Pradhan",
      "Kailash Satyarthi",
      "Arvind Gupta",
      "Sonam Wangchuk",
    ],
    answer: "Anil Pradhan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the International Astronautical Federation (IAF) World Space Award 2024?",
    options: [
      "Dr. S. Somanath for Chandrayaan-3",
      "Elon Musk for Starship",
      "Chris Hadfield for Lunar Gateway",
      "Jeff Bezos for Blue Origin’s Moon Mission",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. S. Somanath for Chandrayaan-3",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Indira Gandhi Peace Prize for 2023?",
    options: [
      "Daniel Barenboim and Ali Abu Awwad",
      "Greta Thunberg",
      "Malala Yousafzai",
      "Jacinda Ardern",
    ],
    answer: "Daniel Barenboim and Ali Abu Awwad",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which state won the Best Marine State Award at World Fisheries Day 2024?",
    options: ["Kerala", "Tamil Nadu", "Andhra Pradesh", "Goa"],
    answer: "Kerala",
  },
  {
    question: "Who received Fiji's highest civilian award?",
    options: [
      "Sri Sri Ravi Shankar",
      "Dalai Lama",
      "Mother Teresa",
      "Narendra Modi",
    ],
    answer: "Sri Sri Ravi Shankar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the EU Sakharov Prize?",
    options: [
      "Maria Corina Machado and Edmundo Gonzalez Urrutia",
      "Alexei Navalny",
      "Julian Assange",
      "Malala Yousafzai",
    ],
    answer: "Maria Corina Machado and Edmundo Gonzalez Urrutia",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the National Kishore Kumar Award?",
    options: [
      "Rajkumar Hirani",
      "Sanjay Leela Bhansali",
      "Anurag Kashyap",
      "Zoya Akhtar",
    ],
    answer: "Rajkumar Hirani",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay NIF Book Prize?",
    options: [
      "Ashok Gopal for A Part Apart",
      "Ramachandra Guha for Gandhi: The Years That Changed the World",
      "Ira Mukhoty for Akbar: The Great Mughal",
      "William Dalrymple for The Anarchy",
    ],
    answer: "Ashok Gopal for A Part Apart",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which state won the 1st place in the 5th National Water Awards 2023?",
    options: ["Odisha", "Kerala", "Maharashtra", "Gujarat"],
    answer: "Odisha",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which state won the 2nd place in the 5th National Water Awards 2023?",
    options: ["Uttar Pradesh", "Rajasthan", "Punjab", "Tamil Nadu"],
    answer: "Uttar Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Nobel Prize in Medicine in 2024?",
    options: [
      "Victor Ambros and Gary Ruvkun",
      "Jennifer Doudna and Emmanuelle Charpentier",
      "Har Gobind Khorana",
      "Svante Pääbo",
    ],
    answer: "Victor Ambros and Gary Ruvkun",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Nobel Prize in Physics in 2024?",
    options: [
      "John J. Hopfield and Geoffrey E. Hinton",
      "Roger Penrose",
      "Andrea Ghez",
      "Arthur Ashkin",
    ],
    answer: "John J. Hopfield and Geoffrey E. Hinton",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Nobel Prize in Chemistry in 2024?",
    options: [
      "David Baker, Demis Hassabis, and John M. Jumper",
      "Frances Arnold",
      "Jean-Pierre Sauvage",
      "Stanley Whittingham",
    ],
    answer: "David Baker, Demis Hassabis, and John M. Jumper",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Nobel Prize in Literature in 2024?",
    options: [
      "Han Kang",
      "Margaret Atwood",
      "Salman Rushdie",
      "Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie",
    ],
    answer: "Han Kang",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Nobel Peace Prize in 2024?",
    options: [
      "Nihon Hidankyo",
      "Greta Thunberg",
      "ICAN",
      "World Food Programme",
    ],
    answer: "Nihon Hidankyo",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Nobel Prize in Economics in 2024?",
    options: [
      "Daron Acemoglu, Simon Johnson, and James A. Robinson",
      "Paul Krugman",
      "Abhijit Banerjee",
      "Esther Duflo",
    ],
    answer: "Daron Acemoglu, Simon Johnson, and James A. Robinson",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Dadasaheb Phalke Award?",
    options: [
      "Mithun Chakraborty",
      "Amitabh Bachchan",
      "Rajinikanth",
      "Hema Malini",
    ],
    answer: "Mithun Chakraborty",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which village won the Best Tourism Villages Competition 2024 in the Heritage category?",
    options: [
      "Andro Village, Manipur",
      "Mawlynnong, Meghalaya",
      "Chilika, Odisha",
      "Hampi, Karnataka",
    ],
    answer: "Andro Village, Manipur",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Ekalabya Puraskar 2024?",
    options: [
      "Pratyasa Ray (Swimming)",
      "Neeraj Chopra (Athletics)",
      "PV Sindhu (Badminton)",
      "R Praggnanandhaa (Chess)",
    ],
    answer: "Pratyasa Ray (Swimming)",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Singapore Literature Prize?",
    options: [
      "Prasanthi Ram for Nine Yard Sarees",
      "Arundhati Roy for The Ministry of Utmost Happiness",
      "Salman Rushdie for Quichotte",
      "Jhumpa Lahiri for Whereabouts",
    ],
    answer: "Prasanthi Ram for Nine Yard Sarees",
  },
  {
    question: "Who received the Olympic Order in Gold?",
    options: [
      "Emmanuel Macron",
      "Narendra Modi",
      "Joe Biden",
      "Justin Trudeau",
    ],
    answer: "Emmanuel Macron",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which city won the Swachh Vayu Survekshan Award 2024 in the population over 10 lakh category?",
    options: ["Surat", "Delhi", "Mumbai", "Hyderabad"],
    answer: "Surat",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Ramon Magsaysay Award 2024 (Nobel Prize of Asia)?",
    options: [
      "Karma Phuntso (Bhutan)",
      "Malala Yousafzai (Pakistan)",
      "Greta Thunberg (Sweden)",
      "Jacinda Ardern (New Zealand)",
    ],
    answer: "Karma Phuntso (Bhutan)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which film won the Best Feature Film Award at the 70th National Film Awards 2024?",
    options: ["Aattam", "Kantara", "RRR", "Pathaan"],
    answer: "Aattam",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Best Actor Award at the 70th National Film Awards 2024?",
    options: [
      "Rishabh Shetty for Kantara",
      "Shah Rukh Khan for Pathaan",
      "Allu Arjun for Pushpa",
      "Ranbir Kapoor for Brahmastra",
    ],
    answer: "Rishabh Shetty for Kantara",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Best Actress Award at the 70th National Film Awards 2024?",
    options: [
      "Nithya Menen for Tiruchitrabalam",
      "Alia Bhatt for Gangubai Kathiawadi",
      "Kriti Sanon for Mimi",
      "Manasi Parekh for Kutch Express",
    ],
    answer: "Nithya Menen for Tiruchitrabalam",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Best Director Award at the 70th National Film Awards 2024?",
    options: [
      "Sooraj Barjatya for Uunchai",
      "SS Rajamouli for RRR",
      "Sanjay Leela Bhansali for Gangubai Kathiawadi",
      "Anurag Kashyap for Dobaaraa",
    ],
    answer: "Sooraj Barjatya for Uunchai",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which film won the Best Odia Film Award at the 70th National Film Awards 2024?",
    options: ["Daman", "Kalira Atita", "Adim Vichar", "Mu Raja Tu Rani"],
    answer: "Daman",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which film won the Best Malayalam Film Award at the 70th National Film Awards 2024?",
    options: [
      "Saudi Velakka",
      "Jallikattu",
      "The Great Indian Kitchen",
      "Bhoothakaalam",
    ],
    answer: "Saudi Velakka",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which film won the Best Marathi Film Award at the 70th National Film Awards 2024?",
    options: ["Vaalvi", "Sairat", "Court", "Natsamrat"],
    answer: "Vaalvi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which film won the Best Kannada Film Award at the 70th National Film Awards 2024?",
    options: [
      "KGF Chapter 2",
      "Kantara",
      "Baahubali: The Beginning",
      "Rajkumari",
    ],
    answer: "KGF Chapter 2",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which film won the Best Hindi Film Award at the 70th National Film Awards 2024?",
    options: ["Gulmohar", "Darlings", "Gangubai Kathiawadi", "Drishyam 2"],
    answer: "Gulmohar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Sastra Ramanujan Prize 2024?",
    options: [
      "Alexander Dunn of the Georgia Institute of Technology, US, for Mathematics",
      "Manjul Bhargava for Mathematics",
      "Andrew Wiles for Proof of Fermat's Last Theorem",
      "Tao Jiefu for Algebraic Geometry",
    ],
    answer:
      "Alexander Dunn of the Georgia Institute of Technology, US, for Mathematics",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Vigyan Team Award at the Rashtriya Vigyan Puraskar 2024?",
    options: [
      "ISRO Chandrayaan-3 Team",
      "DRDO Team for Smart Missiles",
      "ISRO Mars Orbiter Mission Team",
      "IIT Bombay Quantum Computing Team",
    ],
    answer: "ISRO Chandrayaan-3 Team",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Vigyan Ratna Award at the Rashtriya Vigyan Puraskar 2024?",
    options: [
      "Professor G. Padmanabhan",
      "Professor C.N.R. Rao",
      "Dr. A.P.J. Abdul Kalam",
      "Dr. Raghunath Anant Mashelkar",
    ],
    answer: "Professor G. Padmanabhan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who received the Olympic Order from the International Olympic Committee?",
    options: ["Abhinav Bindra", "Milkha Singh", "Sushil Kumar", "P.V. Sindhu"],
    answer: "Abhinav Bindra",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which film won the Grand Prix Award at the 77th Cannes Film Festival?",
    options: [
      "Payal Kapadia’s All We Imagine As Light",
      "Parasite",
      "The Pianist",
      "Blue Is the Warmest Colour",
    ],
    answer: "Payal Kapadia’s All We Imagine As Light",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the first Indian nominee for Best Director at the Golden Globe Awards?",
    options: ["Mira Nair", "Shekhar Kapur", "Deepa Mehta", "Satyajit Ray"],
    answer: "Shekhar Kapur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Best Actress Award at the 77th Cannes Film Festival?",
    options: [
      "Anasuya Sengupta for Shameless",
      "Cate Blanchett for Tár",
      "Marion Cotillard for Rust and Bone",
      "Julianne Moore for Maps to the Stars",
    ],
    answer: "Anasuya Sengupta for Shameless",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the International Booker Prize 2024?",
    options: [
      "Jenny Erpenbeck and translator Michael Hoffman for Kairos",
      "David Diop for At Night All Blood is Black",
      "Geetanjali Shree for Tomb of Sand",
      "Anuk Arudpragasam for A Passage North",
    ],
    answer: "Jenny Erpenbeck and translator Michael Hoffman for Kairos",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Miss World 2024 title?",
    options: [
      "Krystyna Pyszková from the Czech Republic",
      "Katrina Johnson from the USA",
      "Laura Martinez from Spain",
      "Maria Fernanda from Brazil",
    ],
    answer: "Krystyna Pyszková from the Czech Republic",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Femina Miss India 2024 title?",
    options: [
      "Nikita Porwal from Madhya Pradesh",
      "Shivani Jadhav from Maharashtra",
      "Anjali Sharma from Delhi",
      "Sneha Yadav from Telangana",
    ],
    answer: "Nikita Porwal from Madhya Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Miss Universe India 2024 title?",
    options: [
      "Rhea Singha",
      "Harnaaz Sandhu",
      "Nehal Chudasama",
      "Manushi Chhillar",
    ],
    answer: "Rhea Singha",
  },
  {
    question: "Who were the recipients of the Bharat Ratna Award 2024?",
    options: [
      "Karpoori Thakur (Posthumous), Lal Krishna Advani, P.V. Narasimha Rao (Posthumous), Chaudhary Charan Singh (Posthumous), M.S. Swaminathan",
      "Dr. B.R. Ambedkar, Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel, Jawaharlal Nehru, Subhas Chandra Bose, Maulana Abul Kalam Azad",
      "Indira Gandhi, Rajiv Gandhi, Atal Bihari Vajpayee, Pranab Mukherjee, Lata Mangeshkar",
      "C. N. R. Rao, K. Radhakrishnan, V. Shanta, S. Chandrasekhar",
    ],
    answer:
      "Karpoori Thakur (Posthumous), Lal Krishna Advani, P.V. Narasimha Rao (Posthumous), Chaudhary Charan Singh (Posthumous), M.S. Swaminathan",
  },
  {
    question: "How many Padma Awards were given in 2024?",
    options: ["132", "120", "145", "150"],
    answer: "132",
  },
  {
    question: "How many Padma Vibhushan awards were given in 2024?",
    options: ["5", "10", "3", "8"],
    answer: "5",
  },
  {
    question: "How many Padma Bhushan awards were given in 2024?",
    options: ["17", "20", "15", "12"],
    answer: "17",
  },
  {
    question: "How many Padma Shri awards were given in 2024?",
    options: ["110", "100", "120", "130"],
    answer: "110",
  },
  {
    question: "Who received the Padma Vibhushan Award in 2024?",
    options: [
      "Vyjayantimala Bali",
      "M. Venkaiah Naidu",
      "Konidela Chiranjeevi",
      "Bindeshwar Pathak",
      "Padma Subrahmanyam",
    ],
    answer: "Vyjayantimala Bali",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which field did M. Venkaiah Naidu receive the Padma Vibhushan Award in 2024?",
    options: ["Public Affairs", "Art", "Social Work", "Politics"],
    answer: "Public Affairs",
  },
  {
    question: "Who received the Padma Vibhushan Award posthumously in 2024?",
    options: [
      "Bindeshwar Pathak",
      "Konidela Chiranjeevi",
      "Vyjayantimala Bali",
      "Padma Subrahmanyam",
    ],
    answer: "Bindeshwar Pathak",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following individuals received the Padma Vibhushan Award for Art in 2024?",
    options: [
      "Vyjayantimala Bali",
      "M. Venkaiah Naidu",
      "Bindeshwar Pathak",
      "Padma Subrahmanyam",
    ],
    answer: "Padma Subrahmanyam",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Pritzker Prize 2024 (Nobel Prize for Architecture)?",
    options: ["Riken Yamamoto", "Zaha Hadid", "Frank Gehry", "Norman Foster"],
    answer: "Riken Yamamoto",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 58th Jnanpith Award 2023?",
    options: [
      "Gulzar",
      "Jagadguru Rambhadracharya",
      "Prabha Verma",
      "Ravindra Kelekar",
    ],
    answer: "Gulzar and Jagadguru Rambhadracharya",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the 33rd Saraswati Samman for 2023 for the novel Rudra Sathwikam?",
    options: ["Prabha Verma", "Gulzar", "Vikram Seth", "Ravindra Kelekar"],
    answer: "Prabha Verma",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Major Dhyan Chand Khel Ratna Award 2024?",
    options: ["Chirag Shetty", "Satwiksairaj", "Virat Kohli", "Neeraj Chopra"],
    answer: "Chirag Shetty and Satwiksairaj",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Goldman Environmental Prize 2024 (Green Nobel)?",
    options: [
      "Alok Shukla",
      "Greta Thunberg",
      "Sundar Pichai",
      "David Attenborough",
    ],
    answer: "Alok Shukla",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Nelson Mandela Lifetime Achievement Award 2024?",
    options: [
      "Vinod Ganatra",
      "Amartya Sen",
      "Mahatma Gandhi",
      "Arundhati Roy",
    ],
    answer: "Vinod Ganatra",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Best Actor Award at the Oscars 2024?",
    options: ["Cillian Murphy", "Brad Pitt", "Leonardo DiCaprio", "Tom Hanks"],
    answer: "Cillian Murphy",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Best Director Award at the Oscars 2024?",
    options: [
      "Christopher Nolan",
      "Martin Scorsese",
      "Steven Spielberg",
      "Quentin Tarantino",
    ],
    answer: "Christopher Nolan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Best Actress Award at the Oscars 2024?",
    options: ["Emma Stone", "Margot Robbie", "Cate Blanchett", "Nicole Kidman"],
    answer: "Emma Stone",
  },
  {
    question: "Which film won the Best Picture Award at the Oscars 2024?",
    options: [
      "Oppenheimer",
      "The Fablemans",
      "Everything Everywhere All at Once",
      "Avatar: The Way of Water",
    ],
    answer: "Oppenheimer",
  },
  {
    question: "How many Oscars did Oppenheimer win in 2024?",
    options: ["7 Oscars", "10 Oscars", "5 Oscars", "12 Oscars"],
    answer: "7 Oscars",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which film won the Best Film Award at the Golden Globe Awards 2024?",
    options: ["Oppenheimer", "The Fablemans", "Barbie", "The Whale"],
    answer: "Oppenheimer",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which film won the Best Film Award at the British Academy Film Awards (BAFTA) 2024?",
    options: [
      "Oppenheimer",
      "The Fablemans",
      "Avatar: The Way of Water",
      "The Whale",
    ],
    answer: "Oppenheimer",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Subhash Chandra Bose Aapda Prabandhan Puraskar 2024?",
    options: [
      "60 Parachute Field Hospital, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Indore Disaster Management Team",
      "Kolkata Disaster Relief Team",
      "Uttarakhand Rescue Team",
    ],
    answer: "60 Parachute Field Hospital, Uttar Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which airport was named the World’s Best Airport in the 2024 Skytrax World Airport Awards?",
    options: [
      "Hamad International Airport, Doha, Qatar",
      "Changi Airport, Singapore",
      "Dubai International Airport, UAE",
      "Tokyo Haneda Airport, Japan",
    ],
    answer: "Hamad International Airport, Doha, Qatar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Best Water Management Award at the Smart Cities India Awards 2024?",
    options: [
      "Indore Smart City Development Limited",
      "Pune Smart City Development",
      "Chandigarh Smart City",
      "Surat Smart City",
    ],
    answer: "Indore Smart City Development Limited",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the 14th Dr. M.S. Swaminathan Award for Leadership in Agriculture?",
    options: [
      "Professor B.R. Kamboj",
      "Professor M.S. Swaminathan",
      "Dr. Ramesh Chand",
      "Dr. Ashok Gulati",
    ],
    answer: "Professor B.R. Kamboj",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Lifetime Achievement Award at the National Geoscience Awards 2023?",
    options: [
      "Professor Dhiraj Mohan Banerjee",
      "Professor M. Rajaram",
      "Dr. S.K. Gupta",
      "Dr. H.S. Rawat",
    ],
    answer: "Professor Dhiraj Mohan Banerjee",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the National Lata Mangeshkar Award from the Madhya Pradesh Government for the year 2023?",
    options: ["K.S. Chithra", "Asha Bhosle", "Sonu Nigam", "Hariharan"],
    answer: "K.S. Chithra",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Pen Pinter Prize 2024?",
    options: ["Arundhati Roy", "Salman Rushdie", "Kiran Desai", "Vikram Seth"],
    answer: "Arundhati Roy",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is India's rank in the Climate Change Performance Index 2025?",
    options: ["10th", "5th", "15th", "20th"],
    answer: "10th",
  },
  {
    question: "What is India's rank in the Sustainable Business Index 2024?",
    options: ["23rd", "18th", "30th", "25th"],
    answer: "23rd",
  },
  {
    question: "What is India's rank in the Network Readiness Index 2024?",
    options: ["49th", "55th", "40th", "45th"],
    answer: "49th",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is India's rank in the Global AI Readiness Index (Artificial Intelligence Preparedness Index) by the IMF?",
    options: ["72nd", "60th", "80th", "65th"],
    answer: "72nd",
  },
  {
    question: "What is India's rank in the Henley Passport Index?",
    options: ["83rd", "80th", "75th", "90th"],
    answer: "83rd",
  },
  {
    question: "What is India's rank in the Global Hunger Index 2024?",
    options: ["105th", "110th", "98th", "120th"],
    answer: "105th",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is India's rank in the Global Nature Conservation Index 2024?",
    options: ["176th", "180th", "160th", "170th"],
    answer: "176th",
  },
  {
    question: "What is India's rank in the Global Innovation Index 2024?",
    options: ["39th", "40th", "45th", "35th"],
    answer: "39th",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What were the top 3 states in the 6th Food Safety Index by FSSAI?",
    options: [
      "Kerala, Tamil Nadu, Jammu Kashmir",
      "Uttar Pradesh, Bihar, Maharashtra",
      "Kerala, Punjab, Tamil Nadu",
      "Rajasthan, Kerala, Uttarakhand",
    ],
    answer: "Kerala, Tamil Nadu, Jammu Kashmir",
  },
  {
    question: "Which country is the world’s largest 5G smartphone market?",
    options: ["China", "India", "USA", "South Korea"],
    answer: "China",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which institute topped the National Institutional Ranking Framework 2024?",
    options: ["IIT Madras", "IIT Bombay", "IIT Delhi", "IIT Kanpur"],
    answer: "IIT Madras",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is India's rank in the Travel and Tourism Development Index 2024?",
    options: ["39th", "35th", "50th", "45th"],
    answer: "39th",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is India's score in the NITI Aayog’s 4th SDG India Index 2023-24?",
    options: ["71", "75", "70", "68"],
    answer: "71",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which states were the top performers in the 4th SDG India Index 2023-24?",
    options: [
      "Kerala and Uttarakhand",
      "Tamil Nadu and Kerala",
      "Uttarakhand and Punjab",
      "Maharashtra and Karnataka",
    ],
    answer: "Kerala and Uttarakhand",
  },
  {
    question: "What is India’s rank in the World Press Freedom Index 2024?",
    options: ["159th", "160th", "145th", "150th"],
    answer: "159th",
  },
  {
    question: "What is India's rank in the World Happiness Report?",
    options: ["126th", "120th", "130th", "140th"],
    answer: "126th",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is India's rank in the Global Gender Gap Index 2024 by WEF?",
    options: ["129th", "120th", "135th", "140th"],
    answer: "129th",
  },
  {
    question: "What is India's rank in the Global Peace Index 2024?",
    options: ["116th", "110th", "120th", "125th"],
    answer: "116th",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is India's rank in the Human Development Index 2023/24 by UNDP?",
    options: ["134th", "130th", "140th", "120th"],
    answer: "134th",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is India's rank in the Environmental Performance Index 2024 by Yale Center for Environmental Law and Policy?",
    options: ["176th", "170th", "180th", "150th"],
    answer: "176th",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is India's rank in the International Intellectual Property Index 2024?",
    options: ["42nd", "50th", "45th", "40th"],
    answer: "42nd",
  },
  {
    question: "What is India's rank in the World Air Quality Report by IQAir?",
    options: [
      "3rd most polluted country",
      "2nd most polluted country",
      "1st most polluted country",
      "4th most polluted country",
    ],
    answer: "3rd most polluted country",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which country is the most polluted according to the World Air Quality Report by IQAir?",
    options: ["Bangladesh", "India", "Pakistan", "China"],
    answer: "Bangladesh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which is the most polluted capital city according to the World Air Quality Report by IQAir?",
    options: ["Delhi", "Dhaka", "Islamabad", "Beijing"],
    answer: "Delhi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which is the most polluted metropolitan area according to the World Air Quality Report by IQAir?",
    options: [
      "Begusarai in Bihar",
      "Kanpur in Uttar Pradesh",
      "Delhi",
      "Ludhiana in Punjab",
    ],
    answer: "Begusarai in Bihar",
  },
  {
    question: "What is India's rank in the Corruption Perceptions Index 2023?",
    options: ["93rd", "100th", "95th", "80th"],
    answer: "93rd",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Men’s Asia Cup Under-19 2024?",
    options: ["Bangladesh", "India", "Sri Lanka", "Pakistan"],
    answer: "Bangladesh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the runner-up in the Men’s Asia Cup Under-19 2024?",
    options: ["India", "Sri Lanka", "Pakistan", "Afghanistan"],
    answer: "India",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the Men’s Asia Cup Under-19 2024 held?",
    options: ["Dubai, UAE", "Kolkata, India", "Sharjah, UAE", "Mumbai, India"],
    answer: "Dubai, UAE",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the FIDE World Chess Championship 2024 held?",
    options: ["Singapore", "New York, USA", "Moscow, Russia", "London, UK"],
    answer: "Singapore",
  },
  {
    question: "Where were the Northeast Para Games 2024 held?",
    options: ["Guwahati", "Imphal", "Shillong", "Kohima"],
    answer: "Guwahati",
  },
  {
    question: "Which state ranked 1st in the Northeast Para Games 2024?",
    options: ["Assam", "Manipur", "Nagaland", "Meghalaya"],
    answer: "Assam",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the mascot of the Northeast Para Games 2024?",
    options: ["Puhor", "Pohor", "Uttor", "Bikash"],
    answer: "Puhor",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was the World Pickleball Championship Series held in 2024?",
    options: ["Mumbai", "Bengaluru", "Chennai", "Delhi"],
    answer: "Mumbai",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How many medals did India win in the World Pickleball Championship Series 2024?",
    options: ["28", "25", "30", "35"],
    answer: "28",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the brand ambassador for the World Pickleball Championship Series 2024?",
    options: [
      "Mandira Bedi",
      "Deepika Padukone",
      "Priyanka Chopra",
      "Kareena Kapoor",
    ],
    answer: "Mandira Bedi",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the Tata Steel Chess Blitz held?",
    options: ["Kolkata", "New Delhi", "Chennai", "Mumbai"],
    answer: "Kolkata",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Tata Steel Chess Blitz?",
    options: [
      "Magnus Carlsen",
      "Levon Aronian",
      "Hikaru Nakamura",
      "Viswanathan Anand",
    ],
    answer: "Magnus Carlsen",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Olympics did the Indian Olympic Association formally bid to host?",
    options: [
      "2036 Olympics",
      "2032 Olympics",
      "2028 Olympics",
      "2024 Olympics",
    ],
    answer: "2036 Olympics",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 8th Women’s Asian Champions Trophy for Hockey 2024?",
    options: ["India", "China", "Japan", "South Korea"],
    answer: "India",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the runner-up in the 8th Women’s Asian Champions Trophy for Hockey 2024?",
    options: ["China", "Japan", "South Korea", "Malaysia"],
    answer: "China",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was the 8th Women’s Asian Champions Trophy for Hockey 2024 held?",
    options: ["Bihar", "New Delhi", "Chandigarh", "Bengaluru"],
    answer: "Bihar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Chennai Grandmasters Chess Tournament?",
    options: [
      "GM Aravindh Chitthambaram",
      "GM Viswanathan Anand",
      "GM Magnus Carlsen",
      "GM Levon Aronian",
    ],
    answer: "GM Aravindh Chitthambaram",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the women’s title at the Syed Modi International Badminton Competition 2024?",
    options: ["PV Sindhu", "Saina Nehwal", "Malvika Bansod", "Ashmita Chaliha"],
    answer: "PV Sindhu",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the men’s title at the Syed Modi International Badminton Competition 2024?",
    options: [
      "Lakshya Sen",
      "Kidambi Srikanth",
      "H.S. Prannoy",
      "Sameer Verma",
    ],
    answer: "Lakshya Sen",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the 2024 Blind T20 World Cup hosted?",
    options: ["Pakistan", "India", "Sri Lanka", "Bangladesh"],
    answer: "Pakistan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 2024 Blind T20 World Cup?",
    options: ["Pakistan", "India", "Sri Lanka", "Bangladesh"],
    answer: "Pakistan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 14th Senior National Hockey Championship?",
    options: ["Odisha", "Punjab", "Haryana", "Uttar Pradesh"],
    answer: "Odisha",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the WBF Super Featherweight title?",
    options: [
      "Mandeep Jangra",
      "Vijender Singh",
      "Neeraj Goyat",
      "Gurpreet Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Mandeep Jangra",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the 1st Kho Kho World Cup 2025 be held?",
    options: ["Delhi", "Mumbai", "Bengaluru", "Kolkata"],
    answer: "Delhi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will the Khelo India Youth Games and Para Games 2025 be hosted?",
    options: ["Bihar", "Haryana", "Madhya Pradesh", "Maharashtra"],
    answer: "Bihar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the 28th World Title at the IBSF World Billiards Championship 2024?",
    options: [
      "Pankaj Advani",
      "Geet Sethi",
      "Ashok Shandilya",
      "Manan Chandra",
    ],
    answer: "Pankaj Advani",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Formula 1 title for the fourth consecutive time?",
    options: [
      "Max Verstappen",
      "Lewis Hamilton",
      "Sebastian Vettel",
      "Charles Leclerc",
    ],
    answer: "Max Verstappen",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Davis Cup 2024?",
    options: [
      "The Italian men’s tennis team",
      "The Serbian men’s tennis team",
      "The Spanish men’s tennis team",
      "The French men’s tennis team",
    ],
    answer: "The Italian men’s tennis team",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Billie Jean King Cup title for the fifth time?",
    options: [
      "The Italian women’s tennis team",
      "The USA women’s tennis team",
      "The Czech women’s tennis team",
      "The Russian women’s tennis team",
    ],
    answer: "The Italian women’s tennis team",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the most expensive player in IPL 2024?",
    options: ["Rishabh Pant", "Shubman Gill", "Prithvi Shaw", "Hardik Pandya"],
    answer: "Rishabh Pant",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the youngest player to be signed in IPL 2024?",
    options: [
      "Vaibhav Suryavanshi",
      "Shivam Dube",
      "Arjun Tendulkar",
      "Abhishek Sharma",
    ],
    answer: "Vaibhav Suryavanshi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What award has the Sports Ministry discontinued, and what new award has been introduced?",
    options: [
      "The Dhyan Chand Lifetime Award, replaced by the Arjuna Award (Lifetime)",
      "The Arjuna Award, replaced by the Khel Ratna Lifetime",
      "The National Sports Award, replaced by the Padma Bhushan",
      "The Major Dhyan Chand Award, replaced by the Khel Ratna",
    ],
    answer:
      "The Dhyan Chand Lifetime Award, replaced by the Arjuna Award (Lifetime)",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the 38th National Games 2025 be hosted?",
    options: ["Uttarakhand", "Madhya Pradesh", "Uttar Pradesh", "Kerala"],
    answer: "Uttarakhand",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the ICC Women’s T20 World Cup 2024 be hosted?",
    options: ["UAE", "South Africa", "Australia", "England"],
    answer: "UAE",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the ICC Women’s T20 World Cup 2024?",
    options: ["New Zealand", "Australia", "India", "South Africa"],
    answer: "New Zealand",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the Asian Arm Wrestling Cup 2024 be hosted?",
    options: ["Mumbai", "Delhi", "Kolkata", "Chennai"],
    answer: "Mumbai",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Asian Arm Wrestling Cup 2024?",
    options: ["Kazakhstan", "India", "Russia", "China"],
    answer: "Kazakhstan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the runner-up in the Asian Arm Wrestling Cup 2024?",
    options: ["India", "Kazakhstan", "Russia", "Iran"],
    answer: "India",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the 12th Sultan Johor Cup Hockey Tournament held?",
    options: ["Malaysia", "India", "Singapore", "Australia"],
    answer: "Malaysia",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 12th Sultan Johor Cup Hockey Tournament?",
    options: ["Great Britain", "Australia", "India", "Malaysia"],
    answer: "Great Britain",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the runner-up in the 12th Sultan Johor Cup Hockey Tournament?",
    options: ["Australia", "India", "Great Britain", "Pakistan"],
    answer: "Australia",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the bronze medal in the 12th Sultan Johor Cup Hockey Tournament?",
    options: ["India", "Australia", "Great Britain", "Malaysia"],
    answer: "India",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Ballon d'Or 2024 (Men)?",
    options: ["Rodri", "Lionel Messi", "Kylian Mbappé", "Erling Haaland"],
    answer: "Rodri",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Ballon d'Or 2024 (Women)?",
    options: [
      "Aitana Bonmati",
      "Alexia Putella",
      "Sam Kerr",
      "Vivianne Miedema",
    ],
    answer: "Aitana Bonmati",
  },
  {
    question: "Who were the champions of the Santosh Trophy 2023/24 Football?",
    options: ["Services", "Goa", "Kerala", "Punjab"],
    answer: "Services",
  },
  {
    question: "Who were the runner-up of the Santosh Trophy 2023/24 Football?",
    options: ["Goa", "Kerala", "West Bengal", "Maharashtra"],
    answer: "Goa",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 45th Chess Olympiad 2024?",
    options: [
      "The Indian men’s and women’s chess teams",
      "The Russian men’s and women’s chess teams",
      "The Chinese men’s and women’s chess teams",
      "The USA men’s and women’s chess teams",
    ],
    answer: "The Indian men’s and women’s chess teams",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the 45th Chess Olympiad 2024 held?",
    options: [
      "Budapest, Hungary",
      "Moscow, Russia",
      "Beijing, China",
      "New York, USA",
    ],
    answer: "Budapest, Hungary",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which teams had previously won both men’s and women’s gold medals in the Chess Olympiad before India?",
    options: [
      "The Soviet Union and China",
      "The USA and Russia",
      "India and China",
      "Russia and France",
    ],
    answer: "The Soviet Union and China",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the 2024 Asian Champions Trophy Hockey held?",
    options: ["China", "India", "Malaysia", "Pakistan"],
    answer: "China",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 2024 Asian Champions Trophy Hockey?",
    options: ["India", "Pakistan", "China", "South Korea"],
    answer: "India",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the runner-up in the 2024 Asian Champions Trophy Hockey?",
    options: ["China", "Pakistan", "South Korea", "Japan"],
    answer: "China",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 133rd Durand Cup 2024?",
    options: [
      "Northeast United Football Club",
      "Mohun Bagan Super Giant",
      "Kerala Blasters",
      "Bengaluru FC",
    ],
    answer: "Northeast United Football Club",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the runner-up in the 133rd Durand Cup 2024?",
    options: [
      "Mohun Bagan Super Giant",
      "Northeast United Football Club",
      "Goa FC",
      "Chennaiyin FC",
    ],
    answer: "Mohun Bagan Super Giant",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was Neeraj Chopra's performance in the Doha Diamond League 2024?",
    options: ["Second", "First", "Third", "Fourth"],
    answer: "Second",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was Neeraj Chopra's performance in the Paavo Nurmi Games, Finland 2024?",
    options: ["First", "Second", "Third", "Fourth"],
    answer: "First",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was Neeraj Chopra's performance in the Paris Olympics 2024?",
    options: ["Second", "First", "Third", "Fourth"],
    answer: "Second",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was Neeraj Chopra's performance in the Lausanne Diamond League, Switzerland 2024?",
    options: ["Second", "First", "Third", "Fourth"],
    answer: "Second",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was Neeraj Chopra's performance in the Brussels Diamond League, Belgium 2024?",
    options: ["Second", "First", "Third", "Fourth"],
    answer: "Second",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 2024 Australian Open Men's Singles title?",
    options: [
      "Jannik Sinner",
      "Daniil Medvedev",
      "Carlos Alcaraz",
      "Novak Djokovic",
    ],
    answer: "Jannik Sinner",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the runner-up in the 2024 Australian Open Men's Singles?",
    options: [
      "Daniil Medvedev",
      "Carlos Alcaraz",
      "Novak Djokovic",
      "Taylor Fritz",
    ],
    answer: "Daniil Medvedev",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 2024 French Open Men's Singles title?",
    options: [
      "Carlos Alcaraz",
      "Alexander Zverev",
      "Novak Djokovic",
      "Rafael Nadal",
    ],
    answer: "Carlos Alcaraz",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the runner-up in the 2024 French Open Men's Singles?",
    options: [
      "Alexander Zverev",
      "Carlos Alcaraz",
      "Daniil Medvedev",
      "Novak Djokovic",
    ],
    answer: "Alexander Zverev",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 2024 Wimbledon Men's Singles title?",
    options: [
      "Carlos Alcaraz",
      "Novak Djokovic",
      "Daniil Medvedev",
      "Rafael Nadal",
    ],
    answer: "Carlos Alcaraz",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the runner-up in the 2024 Wimbledon Men's Singles?",
    options: [
      "Novak Djokovic",
      "Carlos Alcaraz",
      "Daniil Medvedev",
      "Rafael Nadal",
    ],
    answer: "Novak Djokovic",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 2024 US Open Men's Singles title?",
    options: [
      "Jannik Sinner",
      "Taylor Fritz",
      "Carlos Alcaraz",
      "Novak Djokovic",
    ],
    answer: "Jannik Sinner",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the runner-up in the 2024 US Open Men's Singles?",
    options: [
      "Taylor Fritz",
      "Carlos Alcaraz",
      "Jannik Sinner",
      "Daniil Medvedev",
    ],
    answer: "Taylor Fritz",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 2024 Australian Open Women's Singles title?",
    options: [
      "Aryna Sabalenka",
      "Iga Świątek",
      "Jessica Pegula",
      "Zheng Qinwen",
    ],
    answer: "Aryna Sabalenka",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the runner-up in the 2024 Australian Open Women's Singles?",
    options: [
      "Zheng Qinwen",
      "Iga Świątek",
      "Aryna Sabalenka",
      "Jessica Pegula",
    ],
    answer: "Zheng Qinwen",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 2024 French Open Women's Singles title?",
    options: [
      "Iga Świątek",
      "Jessica Pegula",
      "Jasmine Paolini",
      "Aryna Sabalenka",
    ],
    answer: "Iga Świątek",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the runner-up in the 2024 French Open Women's Singles?",
    options: [
      "Jasmine Paolini",
      "Iga Świątek",
      "Aryna Sabalenka",
      "Jessica Pegula",
    ],
    answer: "Jasmine Paolini",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 2024 Wimbledon Women's Singles title?",
    options: [
      "Barbora Krejcikova",
      "Jasmine Paolini",
      "Iga Świątek",
      "Aryna Sabalenka",
    ],
    answer: "Barbora Krejcikova",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the runner-up in the 2024 Wimbledon Women's Singles?",
    options: [
      "Jasmine Paolini",
      "Barbora Krejcikova",
      "Aryna Sabalenka",
      "Iga Świątek",
    ],
    answer: "Jasmine Paolini",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 2024 US Open Women's Singles title?",
    options: [
      "Aryna Sabalenka",
      "Jessica Pegula",
      "Iga Świątek",
      "Jasmine Paolini",
    ],
    answer: "Aryna Sabalenka",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the runner-up in the 2024 US Open Women's Singles?",
    options: [
      "Jessica Pegula",
      "Aryna Sabalenka",
      "Iga Świątek",
      "Jasmine Paolini",
    ],
    answer: "Jessica Pegula",
  },
  {
    question: "Who were the winners of the 63rd Subroto Cup 2024?",
    options: [
      "Manipur’s TG English School (U-17 Boys)",
      "Kerala Football Academy",
      "Goa’s Soccer School",
      "Maharashtra's Navi Mumbai Football Academy",
    ],
    answer: "Manipur’s TG English School (U-17 Boys)",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the 63rd Subroto Cup 2024 hosted?",
    options: ["New Delhi", "Kolkata", "Chennai", "Mumbai"],
    answer: "New Delhi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the ICC Chairman?",
    options: [
      "Jay Shah",
      "Sourav Ganguly",
      "Shashank Manohar",
      "N. Srinivasan",
    ],
    answer: "Jay Shah",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 2024 T20 World Cup (9th Edition)?",
    options: ["India", "South Africa", "England", "New Zealand"],
    answer: "India",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the 2024 T20 World Cup held?",
    options: [
      "West Indies and USA",
      "India and Sri Lanka",
      "Australia",
      "United Arab Emirates",
    ],
    answer: "West Indies and USA",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the venue for the final of the 2024 T20 World Cup?",
    options: [
      "Kensington Oval, Bridgetown, Barbados",
      "Lord's Cricket Ground, London",
      "Melbourne Cricket Ground, Melbourne",
      "Eden Gardens, Kolkata",
    ],
    answer: "Kensington Oval, Bridgetown, Barbados",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the runner-up in the 2024 T20 World Cup?",
    options: ["South Africa", "Australia", "England", "New Zealand"],
    answer: "South Africa",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Player of the Series in the 2024 T20 World Cup?",
    options: ["Jasprit Bumrah", "Virat Kohli", "Hardik Pandya", "Rohit Sharma"],
    answer: "Jasprit Bumrah",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the Player of the Match in the 2024 T20 World Cup final?",
    options: ["Virat Kohli", "Rohit Sharma", "Hardik Pandya", "KL Rahul"],
    answer: "Virat Kohli",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the captain of South Africa in the 2024 T20 World Cup?",
    options: [
      "Aiden Markram",
      "Quinton de Kock",
      "Kagiso Rabada",
      "Temba Bavuma",
    ],
    answer: "Aiden Markram",
  },
  {
    question: "When will the next edition of the T20 World Cup be held?",
    options: [
      "2026 in India and Sri Lanka",
      "2028 in Australia",
      "2025 in the USA and the West Indies",
      "2027 in South Africa",
    ],
    answer: "2026 in India and Sri Lanka",
  },
  {
    question: "What rank did India secure in the 2024 Paris Olympics?",
    options: ["71st", "50th", "100th", "25th"],
    answer: "71st",
  },
  {
    question: "How many medals did India win at the 2024 Paris Olympics?",
    options: [
      "6 (1 silver, 5 bronze)",
      "10 (4 gold, 3 silver, 3 bronze)",
      "5 (1 gold, 3 silver, 1 bronze)",
      "8 (2 gold, 3 silver, 3 bronze)",
    ],
    answer: "6 (1 silver, 5 bronze)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who were the flagbearers for India during the closing ceremony of the 2024 Paris Olympics?",
    options: [
      "Sreejesh and Manu Bhaker",
      "Neeraj Chopra and Sreejesh",
      "Manu Bhaker and Vinesh Phogat",
      "Ravi Kumar Dahiya and Mary Kom",
    ],
    answer: "Sreejesh and Manu Bhaker",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who carried the Indian Olympic torch during the 2024 Paris Olympics?",
    options: ["Abhinav Bindra", "Sreejesh", "Neeraj Chopra", "P.V. Sindhu"],
    answer: "Abhinav Bindra",
  },
  {
    question: "How many athletes represented India at the 2024 Paris Olympics?",
    options: ["117", "125", "150", "100"],
    answer: "117",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which event earned Manu Bhaker a bronze medal at the 2024 Paris Olympics?",
    options: [
      "Women’s 10m Air Pistol",
      "Women’s 25m Pistol",
      "Women’s 10m Air Rifle",
      "Women’s 50m Rifle Prone",
    ],
    answer: "Women’s 10m Air Pistol",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who were the bronze medalists in the 10m Air Pistol Mixed Team event at the 2024 Paris Olympics?",
    options: [
      "Manu Bhaker and Sarabjot Singh",
      "Abhinav Bindra and Mehuli Ghosh",
      "Saurabh Chaudhary and Apurvi Chandela",
      "Ravi Kumar Dahiya and Vinesh Phogat",
    ],
    answer: "Manu Bhaker and Sarabjot Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Indian athlete won a bronze medal in the Men's 50m Rifle 3 Positions at the 2024 Paris Olympics?",
    options: [
      "Swapnil Kusale",
      "Aishwarya Pratap Singh Tomar",
      "Saurabh Chaudhary",
      "Deepak Kumar",
    ],
    answer: "Swapnil Kusale",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which event did the Indian hockey team win a bronze medal in at the 2024 Paris Olympics?",
    options: [
      "Hockey",
      "Men’s 4x100m Relay",
      "Men’s Javelin",
      "Badminton Mixed Doubles",
    ],
    answer: "Hockey",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Indian wrestler won a bronze medal in the Men’s 57kg Freestyle event at the 2024 Paris Olympics?",
    options: [
      "Aman Sehrawat",
      "Bajrang Punia",
      "Ravi Kumar Dahiya",
      "Deepak Poonia",
    ],
    answer: "Aman Sehrawat",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the silver medal in the Men’s Javelin event at the 2024 Paris Olympics?",
    options: ["Neeraj Chopra", "Rohit Yadav", "Vikas Yadav", "Keshav Yadav"],
    answer: "Neeraj Chopra",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the mascot for the 2024 Paris Olympics?",
    options: ["Phrygian cap", "Lion", "Olympic Flame", "Parisian Owl"],
    answer: "Phrygian cap",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which country topped the medal tally at the 2024 Paris Olympics?",
    options: ["USA", "China", "Russia", "Germany"],
    answer: "USA",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What rank did India secure in the 2024 Paralympic Games in Paris?",
    options: ["18th", "15th", "25th", "10th"],
    answer: "18th",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How many total medals did India win at the 2024 Paralympic Games?",
    options: [
      "29 (7 gold, 9 silver, 13 bronze)",
      "20 (5 gold, 8 silver, 7 bronze)",
      "25 (10 gold, 8 silver, 7 bronze)",
      "30 (9 gold, 10 silver, 11 bronze)",
    ],
    answer: "29 (7 gold, 9 silver, 13 bronze)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who were the flag bearers for India at the 2024 Paralympic Games?",
    options: [
      "Harvinder and Preeti Pal",
      "Neeraj Chopra and Sreejesh",
      "Manu Bhaker and Vinesh Phogat",
      "Pramod Bhagat and Deepa Malik",
    ],
    answer: "Harvinder and Preeti Pal",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which athlete won a gold medal in badminton at the 2024 Paralympic Games?",
    options: ["Nitesh Kumar", "Manoj Sarkar", "Pramod Bhagat", "Krishna Nagar"],
    answer: "Nitesh Kumar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the gold medal in Men’s Javelin F64 at the 2024 Paralympic Games?",
    options: ["Sumit Antil", "Navdeep Singh", "Ravindra Kumar", "Dinesh Kumar"],
    answer: "Sumit Antil",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the gold medal in Archery at the 2024 Paralympic Games?",
    options: [
      "Harvinder Singh",
      "Deepa Malik",
      "Mangal Singh Champia",
      "Rajinder Singh Rahelu",
    ],
    answer: "Harvinder Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which athlete won the gold medal in Club Throw at the 2024 Paralympic Games?",
    options: [
      "Dharambir Nain",
      "Karam Singh",
      "Joginder Singh",
      "Devender Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Dharambir Nain",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the gold medal in High Jump at the 2024 Paralympic Games?",
    options: ["Praveen Kumar", "Sandeep Singh", "Ravi Kumar", "Ajeet Kumar"],
    answer: "Praveen Kumar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which athlete won the gold medal in Javelin Throw F41 at the 2024 Paralympic Games?",
    options: [
      "Navdeep Singh",
      "Sandeep Kumar",
      "Ravi Chaudhary",
      "Ramesh Kumar",
    ],
    answer: "Navdeep Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the gold medal in Women’s R2 10m Air Rifle Standing SH1 at the 2024 Paralympic Games?",
    options: ["Avani Lekhara", "Manu Bhaker", "Rahi Sarnobat", "Pooja Kumar"],
    answer: "Avani Lekhara",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which country topped the medal tally at the 2024 Paralympic Games?",
    options: ["China", "United States", "Russia", "India"],
    answer: "China",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 2024 Indian Premier League (IPL) championship?",
    options: [
      "Kolkata Knight Riders (KKR)",
      "Mumbai Indians (MI)",
      "Chennai Super Kings (CSK)",
      "Delhi Capitals (DC)",
    ],
    answer: "Kolkata Knight Riders (KKR)",
  },
  {
    question: "Which team was the runner-up in the 2024 IPL?",
    options: [
      "Sunrisers Hyderabad (SRH)",
      "Rajasthan Royals (RR)",
      "Royal Challengers Bangalore (RCB)",
      "Punjab Kings (PBKS)",
    ],
    answer: "Sunrisers Hyderabad (SRH)",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was named the Most Valuable Player (MVP) in the 2024 IPL?",
    options: [
      "Sunil Narine of KKR",
      "Virat Kohli of RCB",
      "Hardik Pandya of MI",
      "Rohit Sharma of MI",
    ],
    answer: "Sunil Narine of KKR",
  },
  {
    question: "Who scored the most runs in the 2024 IPL season?",
    options: ["Virat Kohli", "David Warner", "Shubman Gill", "Ruturaj Gaikwad"],
    answer: "Virat Kohli",
  },
  {
    question: "Who took the most wickets in the 2024 IPL season?",
    options: [
      "Harshal Patel of PBKS",
      "Yuzvendra Chahal of RR",
      "Rashid Khan of SRH",
      "Jasprit Bumrah of MI",
    ],
    answer: "Harshal Patel of PBKS",
  },
  {
    question: "Which team won the 2024 Women's Premier League?",
    options: [
      "Royal Challengers Bangalore (RCB)",
      "Mumbai Indians (MI)",
      "Delhi Capitals",
      "Gujarat Giants",
    ],
    answer: "Royal Challengers Bangalore (RCB)",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the captain of RCB in the 2024 Women's Premier League?",
    options: [
      "Smriti Mandhana",
      "Harmanpreet Kaur",
      "Mithali Raj",
      "Devika Vaidya",
    ],
    answer: "Smriti Mandhana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which team was the runner-up in the 2024 Women's Premier League?",
    options: [
      "Delhi Capitals",
      "Mumbai Indians",
      "Gujarat Giants",
      "UP Warriorz",
    ],
    answer: "Delhi Capitals",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the captain of Delhi Capitals in the 2024 Women's Premier League?",
    options: [
      "Meg Lanning",
      "Harmanpreet Kaur",
      "Smriti Mandhana",
      "Jemimah Rodrigues",
    ],
    answer: "Meg Lanning",
  },
  {
    question: "Who took the most wickets in the 2024 Women's Premier League?",
    options: [
      "Shreyanka Patil of RCB",
      "Pooja Vastrakar of MI",
      "Rajeshwari Gayakwad of RCB",
      "Deepti Sharma of DC",
    ],
    answer: "Shreyanka Patil of RCB",
  },
  {
    question: "Who scored the most runs in the 2024 Women's Premier League?",
    options: [
      "Ellyse Perry of RCB",
      "Smriti Mandhana of RCB",
      "Harmanpreet Kaur of MI",
      "Meg Lanning of DC",
    ],
    answer: "Ellyse Perry of RCB",
  },
  {
    question: "Which country will host the 2026 Commonwealth Games?",
    options: ["Scotland", "Australia", "India", "Canada"],
    answer: "Scotland",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the ICC World Test Championship Final 2025 be held?",
    options: [
      "Lord’s, England",
      "Melbourne Cricket Ground, Australia",
      "Wankhede Stadium, India",
      "Newlands, South Africa",
    ],
    answer: "Lord’s, England",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the 2024 Thomas and Uber Cup for badminton held?",
    options: ["China", "Indonesia", "India", "Japan"],
    answer: "China",
  },
  {
    question: "Which team won the 2024 Thomas Cup?",
    options: ["China", "India", "Indonesia", "Japan"],
    answer: "China",
  },
  {
    question: "Which team won the 2024 Uber Cup?",
    options: ["China", "Indonesia", "Japan", "South Korea"],
    answer: "China",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the 2024 Men’s Hockey5s World Cup held?",
    options: ["Oman", "Qatar", "Malaysia", "India"],
    answer: "Oman",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How many teams participated in the 2024 Men’s Hockey5s World Cup?",
    options: ["16 teams", "12 teams", "20 teams", "8 teams"],
    answer: "16 teams",
  },
  {
    question: "Which team won the 2024 Men’s Hockey5s World Cup?",
    options: ["The Netherlands", "Australia", "India", "Germany"],
    answer: "The Netherlands",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which team was the runner-up in the 2024 Men’s Hockey5s World Cup?",
    options: ["Malaysia", "Pakistan", "Australia", "India"],
    answer: "Malaysia",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the mascot of the 4th Khelo India University Games 2024?",
    options: ["Ashtalakshmi", "Veera Mangai", "Shan", "Ravi"],
    answer: "Ashtalakshmi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which university topped the medal tally at the 4th Khelo India University Games 2024?",
    options: [
      "Chandigarh University",
      "Punjabi University Patiala",
      "Banaras Hindu University",
      "Jawaharlal Nehru University",
    ],
    answer: "Chandigarh University",
  },
  {
    question: "Where were the Khelo India Youth Games 2024 held?",
    options: ["Tamil Nadu", "Haryana", "Maharashtra", "Uttar Pradesh"],
    answer: "Tamil Nadu",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the mascot of the Khelo India Youth Games 2024?",
    options: ["Veera Mangai", "Shan", "Ashtalakshmi", "Chingnu"],
    answer: "Veera Mangai",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which state topped the medal tally at the Khelo India Youth Games 2024?",
    options: ["Maharashtra", "Haryana", "Uttar Pradesh", "Rajasthan"],
    answer: "Maharashtra",
  },
  {
    question: "Where were the Khelo India Winter Games held in 2024?",
    options: [
      "Leh, Ladakh, and Gulmarg, Jammu Kashmir",
      "Manali, Himachal Pradesh",
      "Nainital, Uttarakhand",
      "Shimla, Himachal Pradesh",
    ],
    answer: "Leh, Ladakh, and Gulmarg, Jammu Kashmir",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the mascot of the Khelo India Winter Games 2024?",
    options: ["Sheen-e She (Shan)", "Veera Mangai", "Shivraj", "Gulmarg"],
    answer: "Sheen-e She (Shan)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which team won the Men's title at the Badminton Asia Team Championships 2024?",
    options: ["China", "India", "Indonesia", "Japan"],
    answer: "China",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which team won the Women's title at the Badminton Asia Team Championships 2024?",
    options: ["India", "China", "South Korea", "Thailand"],
    answer: "India",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the 2024 Ranji Trophy?",
    options: ["Mumbai", "Vidarbha", "Saurashtra", "Karnataka"],
    answer: "Mumbai",
  },
  {
    question: "Who were the runners-up in the 2024 Ranji Trophy?",
    options: ["Vidarbha", "Saurashtra", "Karnataka", "Delhi"],
    answer: "Vidarbha",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the ACC Paracanoe Asia Championship 2024?",
    options: [
      "Prachi Yadav",
      "Aditi Chauhan",
      "Priyanka Kadian",
      "Radhika Agarwal",
    ],
    answer: "Prachi Yadav",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which banks have been classified as Domestic Systemically Important Banks (D-SIBs) in India?",
    options: [
      "SBI, HDFC, and ICICI",
      "SBI, Axis Bank, and ICICI",
      "SBI, HDFC, and PNB",
      "SBI, ICICI, and Kotak Mahindra",
    ],
    answer: "SBI, HDFC, and ICICI",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will India’s first Google Safety Engineering Centre be set up?",
    options: ["Hyderabad", "Bangalore", "Chennai", "Pune"],
    answer: "Hyderabad",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will Prime Minister Modi launch the 'Bima Sakhi Yojana'?",
    options: ["Panipat", "Gurgaon", "Faridabad", "Ambala"],
    answer: "Panipat",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the objective of the 'Bima Sakhi Yojana'?",
    options: [
      "Women will become agents of the LIC",
      "Provide financial aid to women farmers",
      "Train women in insurance sector management",
      "Empower women through health insurance schemes",
    ],
    answer: "Women will become agents of the LIC",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was the 12th edition of the 'International Tourism Mart' held?",
    options: ["Kaziranga National Park", "Sundarbans", "Taj Mahal", "Manali"],
    answer: "Kaziranga National Park",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the 9th International Gita Mahotsav held?",
    options: [
      "Kurukshetra, Haryana",
      "Haridwar, Uttarakhand",
      "Varanasi, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Delhi",
    ],
    answer: "Kurukshetra, Haryana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which country and state were selected as the partner country and state for the 9th International Gita Mahotsav?",
    options: [
      "Tanzania and Odisha",
      "Nepal and Punjab",
      "Sri Lanka and Himachal Pradesh",
      "Bangladesh and Rajasthan",
    ],
    answer: "Tanzania and Odisha",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was the 59th 'All India Director General of Police' and 'Inspector General Conference' held?",
    options: ["Bhubaneswar", "Kolkata", "Chandigarh", "Bhopal"],
    answer: "Bhubaneswar",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the Mahabodhi Utsav 2024 held?",
    options: [
      "Sanchi, Madhya Pradesh",
      "Bodh Gaya, Bihar",
      "Varanasi, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Ajmer, Rajasthan",
    ],
    answer: "Sanchi, Madhya Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was the first modern, self-sustaining Gaushala with a state-of-the-art compressed biogas (CBG) plant set up?",
    options: [
      "Gwalior, Madhya Pradesh",
      "Indore, Madhya Pradesh",
      "Bhopal, Madhya Pradesh",
      "Kolkata, West Bengal",
    ],
    answer: "Gwalior, Madhya Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was India’s first all-women battalion of the Central Industrial Security Force established?",
    options: ["India", "Kolkata", "Delhi", "Mumbai"],
    answer: "India",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will the world’s first multi-material chip fabrication unit, 'Shakti', be set up?",
    options: [
      "Jewar, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Hyderabad, Telangana",
      "Pune, Maharashtra",
      "Bangalore, Karnataka",
    ],
    answer: "Jewar, Uttar Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the 1st Asian Buddhist Summit held?",
    options: ["New Delhi", "Bangkok", "Kathmandu", "Colombo"],
    answer: "New Delhi",
  },
  {
    question: "What is India’s GDP growth rate according to the G20 report?",
    options: ["7%", "6.5%", "8%", "7.5%"],
    answer: "7%",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What word has Oxford University Press announced as the Oxford Word of the Year for 2024?",
    options: ["Brain rot", "Metaverse", "Sustainability", "Crypto"],
    answer: "Brain rot",
  },
  {
    question: "What are India’s 56th and 57th tiger reserves?",
    options: [
      "Guru Ghasidas-Tamor Pingla Tiger Reserve and Ratapani Tiger Reserve",
      "Sundarbans Tiger Reserve and Panna Tiger Reserve",
      "Kaziranga Tiger Reserve and Manas Tiger Reserve",
      "Bandipur Tiger Reserve and Jim Corbett Tiger Reserve",
    ],
    answer:
      "Guru Ghasidas-Tamor Pingla Tiger Reserve and Ratapani Tiger Reserve",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the world’s 5th and India’s 1st night safari located?",
    options: ["Lucknow", "Agra", "Jaipur", "Bengaluru"],
    answer: "Lucknow",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for the celebrations ‘Hamara Samvidhan, Hamara Swabhimaan’?",
    options: [
      "Continuing until November 26, 2025",
      "Celebrating Constitution Day",
      "Promoting Indian Constitution globally",
      "Empowering citizens through the Constitution",
    ],
    answer: "Continuing until November 26, 2025",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is India’s first Constitution Museum located?",
    options: ["Sonipat, Haryana", "New Delhi", "Chandigarh", "Patna, Bihar"],
    answer: "Sonipat, Haryana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was Asia’s first water transport service, Uber Shikara, launched?",
    options: [
      "Dal Lake, Jammu and Kashmir",
      "Kochi, Kerala",
      "Goa",
      "Mumbai, Maharashtra",
    ],
    answer: "Dal Lake, Jammu and Kashmir",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is India’s first green hydrogen fuelling station located?",
    options: [
      "Leh, Ladakh",
      "Bangalore, Karnataka",
      "Pune, Maharashtra",
      "Gurgaon, Haryana",
    ],
    answer: "Leh, Ladakh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which state in India has been recognized by UNESCO for its tourism sector as a top destination for heritage tourism?",
    options: ["West Bengal", "Rajasthan", "Uttar Pradesh", "Tamil Nadu"],
    answer: "West Bengal",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the first ‘Ashtalakshmi Mahotsav’ held?",
    options: [
      "New Delhi",
      "Bhopal, Madhya Pradesh",
      "Kolkata, West Bengal",
      "Chennai, Tamil Nadu",
    ],
    answer: "New Delhi",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will India’s Army Day celebrations be held in 2025?",
    options: [
      "Pune, Maharashtra",
      "New Delhi",
      "Chandigarh",
      "Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh",
    ],
    answer: "Pune, Maharashtra",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will the 10th ‘India International Science Festival’ 2024 be held?",
    options: ["IIT Guwahati", "IIT Delhi", "IIT Bombay", "IIT Madras"],
    answer: "IIT Guwahati",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the new FDI limit in the insurance sector in India?",
    options: ["100%", "74%", "49%", "51%"],
    answer: "100%",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the TULIP program?",
    options: [
      "Traditional Artisans Upliftment Livelihood Programme",
      "Technology Upliftment for Labour in India Programme",
      "Transforming Urban Landscape & Infrastructure Programme",
      "Tribal Upliftment and Livelihood Improvement Programme",
    ],
    answer: "Traditional Artisans Upliftment Livelihood Programme",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the ‘Shilp Sangam Mela 2024’ be held?",
    options: ["Delhi", "Mumbai", "Lucknow", "Bangalore"],
    answer: "Delhi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where did the National Thermal Power Corporation inaugurate the world’s first CO2-to-methanol conversion plant?",
    options: [
      "NTPC Vindhyachal facility, India",
      "NTPC Barh, Bihar",
      "NTPC Dadri, Uttar Pradesh",
      "NTPC Khedar, Haryana",
    ],
    answer: "NTPC Vindhyachal facility, India",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which state in India is the first to implement a dedicated semiconductor policy?",
    options: ["Gujarat", "Maharashtra", "Uttar Pradesh", "Karnataka"],
    answer: "Gujarat",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where did PM Modi and Spanish PM Pedro Sanchez inaugurate the Tata Aircraft Complex for the manufacturing of C-295 military aircraft?",
    options: [
      "Vadodara, Gujarat",
      "Bangalore, Karnataka",
      "Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Hyderabad, Telangana",
    ],
    answer: "Vadodara, Gujarat",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the significance of the Tata Aircraft Complex in Vadodara?",
    options: [
      "India’s first private sector final assembly line for military aircraft",
      "India’s largest private aircraft manufacturing plant",
      "First military aircraft production facility by DRDO",
      "India’s first helicopter assembly unit",
    ],
    answer:
      "India’s first private sector final assembly line for military aircraft",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was the Major Atmospheric Cherenkov Experiment (MACE) observatory inaugurated?",
    options: [
      "Hanle, Ladakh",
      "Leh, Ladakh",
      "Kangra, Himachal Pradesh",
      "Mount Abu, Rajasthan",
    ],
    answer: "Hanle, Ladakh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who built the telescope for the MACE observatory?",
    options: [
      "Bhabha Atomic Research Centre (BARC)",
      "Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO)",
      "Defence Research and Development Organisation (DRDO)",
      "Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA)",
    ],
    answer: "Bhabha Atomic Research Centre (BARC)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to the WHO, what public health problem has India eliminated?",
    options: ["Trachoma", "Polio", "Leprosy", "Malaria"],
    answer: "Trachoma",
  },
  {
    question: "What is trachoma?",
    options: [
      "A bacterial infection that affects the eyes",
      "A viral infection causing fever and rash",
      "A skin infection causing ulcers",
      "A parasitic disease affecting the lungs",
    ],
    answer: "A bacterial infection that affects the eyes",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is India’s first Hindi Literary Museum located?",
    options: [
      "Kashi (Varanasi)",
      "Bhopal, Madhya Pradesh",
      "Agra, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Patna, Bihar",
    ],
    answer: "Kashi (Varanasi)",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is India’s first demonstration facility for biopolymers?",
    options: [
      "Pune, Maharashtra",
      "Chandigarh, Punjab",
      "Bengaluru, Karnataka",
      "Surat, Gujarat",
    ],
    answer: "Pune, Maharashtra",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the 17th ‘India Urban Mobility’ event 2024 be held?",
    options: [
      "Gandhinagar, Gujarat",
      "Chennai, Tamil Nadu",
      "New Delhi",
      "Hyderabad, Telangana",
    ],
    answer: "Gandhinagar, Gujarat",
  },
  {
    question: "Which city has the most sustainable transport system in India?",
    options: ["Kochi", "Mumbai", "Bengaluru", "Kolkata"],
    answer: "Kochi",
  },
  {
    question: "Which city has the best public transport system in India?",
    options: ["Bhubaneswar", "Mumbai", "Delhi", "Pune"],
    answer: "Bhubaneswar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which city has the best non-motorized transport system in India?",
    options: ["Srinagar", "Pune", "Bengaluru", "Ahmedabad"],
    answer: "Srinagar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which city has the best safety and security system and record in India?",
    options: ["Gandhinagar", "Chandigarh", "Bhopal", "New Delhi"],
    answer: "Gandhinagar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which city has the best intelligent transport system in India?",
    options: ["Surat", "Mumbai", "Bengaluru", "Chennai"],
    answer: "Surat",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which city has the most innovative financing mechanism in India for transport?",
    options: ["Jammu", "Hyderabad", "Delhi", "Kolkata"],
    answer: "Jammu",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which city has the best record of public involvement in transport in India?",
    options: ["Bengaluru", "Mumbai", "Pune", "Ahmedabad"],
    answer: "Bengaluru",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which metro rail system has the best multi-modal integration in India?",
    options: [
      "Bengaluru Metro Rail",
      "Delhi Metro Rail",
      "Kolkata Metro Rail",
      "Chennai Metro Rail",
    ],
    answer: "Bengaluru Metro Rail",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which metro rail system has the best passenger services and satisfaction in India?",
    options: [
      "Mumbai Metro Rail",
      "Delhi Metro Rail",
      "Kolkata Metro Rail",
      "Bengaluru Metro Rail",
    ],
    answer: "Mumbai Metro Rail",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where is India’s first heli ambulance service ‘Sanjeevani’ located?",
    options: [
      "Rishikesh, Uttarakhand",
      "Haridwar, Uttarakhand",
      "Dehradun, Uttarakhand",
      "Nainital, Uttarakhand",
    ],
    answer: "Rishikesh, Uttarakhand",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where is India’s first airport indoor air quality monitoring facility ‘Pavana Chitra’ located?",
    options: [
      "Thiruvananthapuram Airport",
      "Kochi Airport",
      "New Delhi Airport",
      "Bengaluru Airport",
    ],
    answer: "Thiruvananthapuram Airport",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who created the new statue of the Goddess of Justice in the Supreme Court of India?",
    options: ["Vinod Goswami", "Subodh Gupta", "Anish Kapoor", "M.F. Hussain"],
    answer: "Vinod Goswami",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who commissioned the statue of the Goddess of Justice in the Supreme Court of India?",
    options: [
      "Chief Justice DY Chandrachud",
      "Prime Minister Narendra Modi",
      "President of India",
      "Union Law Minister",
    ],
    answer: "Chief Justice DY Chandrachud",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is India’s newest port ‘Galathea Bay’ located?",
    options: ["Andaman and Nicobar Islands", "Lakshadweep", "Goa", "Kochi"],
    answer: "Andaman and Nicobar Islands",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What road did PM Modi name in front of the Jamaica High Commission?",
    options: [
      "Jamaica Marg",
      "Caribbean Lane",
      "West Indies Street",
      "Indo-Jamaica Boulevard",
    ],
    answer: "Jamaica Marg",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Jamaica?",
    options: [
      "Andrew Holness",
      "Portia Simpson Miller",
      "Bruce Golding",
      "Owen Arthur",
    ],
    answer: "Andrew Holness",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the world’s first breeding center located?",
    options: [
      "Maharajganj, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Aligarh, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Dehradun, Uttarakhand",
    ],
    answer: "Maharajganj, Uttar Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the status of Rajyamata Gomata in Maharashtra?",
    options: [
      "Goddess",
      "Sacred animal",
      "National monument",
      "Religious icon",
    ],
    answer: "Goddess",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did Cyclone Remal form?",
    options: ["Bay of Bengal", "Arabian Sea", "Indian Ocean", "Andaman Sea"],
    answer: "Bay of Bengal",
  },
  {
    question: "Who gave the name ‘Cyclone Remal’?",
    options: ["Oman", "India", "Bangladesh", "Sri Lanka"],
    answer: "Oman",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did Cyclone Asna form?",
    options: ["Arabian Sea", "Bay of Bengal", "Indian Ocean", "Andaman Sea"],
    answer: "Arabian Sea",
  },
  {
    question: "Who gave the name ‘Cyclone Asna’?",
    options: ["Pakistan", "India", "Sri Lanka", "Bangladesh"],
    answer: "Pakistan",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did Cyclone Dana form?",
    options: ["Bay of Bengal", "Arabian Sea", "Indian Ocean", "Andaman Sea"],
    answer: "Bay of Bengal",
  },
  {
    question: "Who gave the name ‘Cyclone Dana’?",
    options: ["Qatar", "India", "Bangladesh", "Oman"],
    answer: "Qatar",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did Cyclone Fengal form?",
    options: ["Bay of Bengal", "Arabian Sea", "Indian Ocean", "Andaman Sea"],
    answer: "Bay of Bengal",
  },
  {
    question: "Who gave the name ‘Cyclone Fengal’?",
    options: ["Saudi Arabia", "Pakistan", "Oman", "Sri Lanka"],
    answer: "Saudi Arabia",
  },
  {
    question: "What is India’s first ‘Rice ATM’?",
    options: ["Annapurti Grain ATM", "Kisan ATM", "Ration Rice ATM", "FoodATM"],
    answer: "Annapurti Grain ATM",
  },
  {
    question: "Which state won the Best Agriculture State Award for 2024?",
    options: ["Maharashtra", "Punjab", "Uttar Pradesh", "Tamil Nadu"],
    answer: "Maharashtra",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will PM Modi inaugurate the first Bodoland Mahotsav?",
    options: ["Delhi", "Guwahati", "Kolkata", "Bhopal"],
    answer: "Delhi",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the theme for the 78th Independence Day 2024?",
    options: [
      "Viksit Bharat",
      "Atmanirbhar Bharat",
      "Bharat Ki Udaan",
      "Naya Bharat",
    ],
    answer: "Viksit Bharat",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote the song 'Vande Mataram'?",
    options: [
      "Bankim Chandra Chatterjee",
      "Rabindranath Tagore",
      "Sarojini Naidu",
      "Lalit Mohan Sharma",
    ],
    answer: "Bankim Chandra Chatterjee",
  },
  {
    question: "When was 'Jana Gana Mana' first sung?",
    options: [
      "22nd December, 1911",
      "15th August, 1947",
      "26th January, 1950",
      "15th August, 1948",
    ],
    answer: "22nd December, 1911",
  },
  {
    question: "Who designed India's national flag?",
    options: [
      "Pingali Venkayya",
      "Lal Bahadur Shastri",
      "Sardar Patel",
      "Mahatma Gandhi",
    ],
    answer: "Pingali Venkayya",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will India’s first integrated agri-export facility be established?",
    options: [
      "Mumbai’s Jawaharlal Nehru Port Authority (JNPA)",
      "Kolkata Port",
      "Chennai Port",
      "Mangalore Port",
    ],
    answer: "Mumbai’s Jawaharlal Nehru Port Authority (JNPA)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What new names have been given to the Durbar Hall and Ashoka Hall in the Rashtrapati Bhavan?",
    options: [
      "Ganatantra Mandap and Ashoka Mandap",
      "Republic Mandap and Ashoka Mandap",
      "Durbar Mandap and Republic Hall",
      "Freedom Mandap and Ashoka Mandap",
    ],
    answer: "Ganatantra Mandap and Ashoka Mandap",
  },
  {
    question: "Which site became India's 43rd UNESCO World Heritage Site?",
    options: [
      "Charaideo Maidam",
      "Kaziranga National Park",
      "Taj Mahal",
      "Red Fort",
    ],
    answer: "Charaideo Maidam",
  },
  {
    question: "What is Assam’s third UNESCO World Heritage Site?",
    options: [
      "Charaideo Maidam",
      "Kaziranga National Park",
      "Manas National Park",
      "Sivasagar",
    ],
    answer: "Charaideo Maidam",
  },
  {
    question: "How many cultural world heritage sites are there in India?",
    options: ["35", "32", "40", "45"],
    answer: "35",
  },
  {
    question: "How many natural world heritage sites are there in India?",
    options: ["7", "5", "10", "12"],
    answer: "7",
  },
  {
    question: "How many mixed world heritage sites are there in India?",
    options: ["1", "3", "5", "2"],
    answer: "1",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which city in India was named the first UNESCO 'City of Literature'?",
    options: ["Kozhikode", "Chennai", "Kolkata", "Bhubaneswar"],
    answer: "Kozhikode",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which institution developed India's first quantum diamond microchip imager?",
    options: ["IIT Bombay", "IIT Delhi", "IIT Madras", "IIT Kanpur"],
    answer: "IIT Bombay",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which company launched the world’s first CNG-powered motorcycle?",
    options: [
      "Bajaj Auto",
      "Hero MotoCorp",
      "TVS Motor Company",
      "Honda Motorcycle and Scooter India",
    ],
    answer: "Bajaj Auto",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will the world’s highest tunnel, the Shinkun La Tunnel, be constructed?",
    options: ["Ladakh", "Himachal Pradesh", "Uttarakhand", "Jammu and Kashmir"],
    answer: "Ladakh",
  },
  {
    question: "What is India’s first Namo Bharat Rapid Rail project?",
    options: [
      "Between Bhuj and Ahmedabad",
      "Between Delhi and Agra",
      "Between Mumbai and Pune",
      "Between Bangalore and Chennai",
    ],
    answer: "Between Bhuj and Ahmedabad",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did a massive landslide occur in Papua New Guinea?",
    options: ["Mount Mungalo", "Mount Semeru", "Mount Merapi", "Mount Fuji"],
    answer: "Mount Mungalo",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is India’s first writer village located?",
    options: ["Uttarakhand", "Madhya Pradesh", "Kerala", "Tamil Nadu"],
    answer: "Uttarakhand",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Ustad Allauddin Khan Festival held?",
    options: [
      "Maihar, Madhya Pradesh",
      "Varanasi, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Delhi",
    ],
    answer: "Maihar, Madhya Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which state became the first to implement a 'Dalit Sub-Quota'?",
    options: ["Haryana", "Punjab", "Maharashtra", "Uttar Pradesh"],
    answer: "Haryana",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the new lion safari being built in Gujarat?",
    options: [
      "Barda Wildlife Sanctuary",
      "Gir National Park",
      "Sasan Gir",
      "Kutch Wildlife Sanctuary",
    ],
    answer: "Barda Wildlife Sanctuary",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who has been included in the Ayushman Bharat Pradhan Mantri Jan Arogya Yojana (AB PMJAY) scheme?",
    options: [
      "Senior citizens aged 70 years or above",
      "Children under 5 years",
      "Pregnant women",
      "Persons with disabilities",
    ],
    answer: "Senior citizens aged 70 years or above",
  },
  {
    question: "Which festival is celebrated in Tripura?",
    options: ["Kharchi Puja", "Baisakhi", "Durga Puja", "Maghi Mela"],
    answer: "Kharchi Puja",
  },
  {
    question: "What change has the Kerala Assembly unanimously passed?",
    options: [
      "Change of the state's name to Keralam",
      "Introduction of a new flag",
      "Formation of a new district",
      "Removal of state-specific taxes",
    ],
    answer: "Change of the state's name to Keralam",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the ASMITA project?",
    options: [
      "An initiative to develop 22,000 books in Indian languages",
      "A scheme for providing digital literacy to students",
      "A project for increasing the number of universities in India",
      "A plan for upgrading school infrastructure",
    ],
    answer: "An initiative to develop 22,000 books in Indian languages",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where is the Hemis Festival, celebrating Tibetan Buddhism, held?",
    options: ["Ladakh", "Sikkim", "Leh", "Himachal Pradesh"],
    answer: "Ladakh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which city was awarded the World Craft City tag by the World Crafts Council?",
    options: ["Srinagar", "Jaipur", "Kolkata", "Chennai"],
    answer: "Srinagar",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is India’s first graphene centre located?",
    options: ["Kerala", "Tamil Nadu", "Maharashtra", "Delhi"],
    answer: "Kerala",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the first all-girl Sainik School inaugurated?",
    options: [
      "Vrindavan, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Bhubaneswar, Odisha",
      "Patiala, Punjab",
      "Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh",
    ],
    answer: "Vrindavan, Uttar Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the chief guest at the 75th Republic Day celebrations?",
    options: ["Emmanuel Macron", "Boris Johnson", "Joe Biden", "Narendra Modi"],
    answer: "Emmanuel Macron",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the theme of the 75th Republic Day?",
    options: [
      '"Viksit Bharat" and "Bharat - Loktantraki Matruka"',
      '"Atmanirbhar Bharat" and "Jai Hind"',
      '"Swasth Bharat" and "Bharat ki Shakti"',
      '"Mahatma Gandhi" and "Azadi Ka Amrit Mahotsav"',
    ],
    answer: '"Viksit Bharat" and "Bharat - Loktantraki Matruka"',
  },
  {
    question: "What will DD Kisan launch to assist in news delivery?",
    options: [
      "Two AI anchors named Krish and Bhoomi",
      "AI news delivery robots",
      "Interactive news portals",
      "Digital kiosks",
    ],
    answer: "Two AI anchors named Krish and Bhoomi",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is India's longest sea bridge located?",
    options: ["Mumbai", "Chennai", "Kochi", "Kolkata"],
    answer: "Mumbai",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is India's first Constitution Park located?",
    options: ["Pune", "Delhi", "Bhubaneswar", "Mumbai"],
    answer: "Pune",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Medaram Jethara festival held?",
    options: ["Telangana", "Andhra Pradesh", "Madhya Pradesh", "Uttarakhand"],
    answer: "Telangana",
  },
  {
    question: 'Who chaired the "One Nation, One Election" report?',
    options: [
      "Former President Ram Nath Kovind",
      "Former PM Manmohan Singh",
      "President Pranab Mukherjee",
      "Former Vice-President M. Venkaiah Naidu",
    ],
    answer: "Former President Ram Nath Kovind",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where is India’s first astro-tourism initiative, 'Nakshtra Sabha,' located?",
    options: ["Uttarakhand", "Himachal Pradesh", "Rajasthan", "Madhya Pradesh"],
    answer: "Uttarakhand",
  },
  {
    question: "Which airport received the Zero Waste to Landfill accolade?",
    options: [
      "Thiruvananthapuram International Airport",
      "Delhi International Airport",
      "Chennai International Airport",
      "Bangalore International Airport",
    ],
    answer: "Thiruvananthapuram International Airport",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the first Skill India Centre of the country located?",
    options: ["Odisha", "Uttar Pradesh", "Rajasthan", "Gujarat"],
    answer: "Odisha",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is India’s first septic tank cleaning robot called, and where was it developed?",
    options: [
      "'Homosep Atom' developed at IIT Madras",
      "'SewageBot' developed at IIT Delhi",
      "'SafaiBot' developed at IIT Bombay",
      "'CleanTank' developed at IIT Kanpur",
    ],
    answer: "'Homosep Atom' developed at IIT Madras",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the world’s first Vedic clock installed?",
    options: [
      "Ujjain, Madhya Pradesh",
      "Varanasi, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Haridwar, Uttarakhand",
      "Patna, Bihar",
    ],
    answer: "Ujjain, Madhya Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What will replace IPC 1860, CRPC 1973, and the Indian Evidence Act of 1872?",
    options: [
      "Bharatiya Nyaya Sanhita, 2023, Bharatiya Nagrik Suraksha Sanhita, 2023, and Bharatiya Sakshya, 2023",
      "Bharatiya Penal Code, 2023",
      "Indian Criminal Justice System, 2023",
      "Constitutional Laws of India, 2023",
    ],
    answer:
      "Bharatiya Nyaya Sanhita, 2023, Bharatiya Nagrik Suraksha Sanhita, 2023, and Bharatiya Sakshya, 2023",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which state/union territory was the first to fully implement the new criminal laws in India?",
    options: ["Chandigarh", "Delhi", "Puducherry", "Goa"],
    answer: "Chandigarh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where is Sudarshan Setu, India’s longest cable-stayed bridge, located?",
    options: [
      "Beyt Dwarka Island, Gulf of Kutch",
      "Kochi, Kerala",
      "Kolkata, West Bengal",
      "Mumbai, Maharashtra",
    ],
    answer: "Beyt Dwarka Island, Gulf of Kutch",
  },
  {
    question: "Which airport has the first green hydrogen plant in India?",
    options: [
      "Cochin International Airport",
      "Delhi International Airport",
      "Bangalore International Airport",
      "Chennai International Airport",
    ],
    answer: "Cochin International Airport",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is India’s first transshipment port located?",
    options: [
      "Vizhinjam Port, Kerala",
      "Jawaharlal Nehru Port, Maharashtra",
      "Paradip Port, Odisha",
      "Kochi Port, Kerala",
    ],
    answer: "Vizhinjam Port, Kerala",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How many snow leopards are there in India, and where is the highest population?",
    options: [
      "718 snow leopards, with the highest population in Ladakh",
      "580 snow leopards, with the highest population in Himachal Pradesh",
      "700 snow leopards, with the highest population in Uttarakhand",
      "750 snow leopards, with the highest population in Sikkim",
    ],
    answer: "718 snow leopards, with the highest population in Ladakh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which state has the highest number of leopards in India?",
    options: ["Madhya Pradesh", "Uttarakhand", "Maharashtra", "Rajasthan"],
    answer: "Madhya Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the new naval base INS Jatayu commissioned in India?",
    options: [
      "Minicoy Island, Lakshadweep",
      "Kochi, Kerala",
      "Andaman and Nicobar Islands",
      "Goa",
    ],
    answer: "Minicoy Island, Lakshadweep",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which port emerged as India’s top cargo-handling port in 2023-24?",
    options: [
      "Paradip Port",
      "Jawaharlal Nehru Port",
      "Kochi Port",
      "Mumbai Port",
    ],
    answer: "Paradip Port",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was the 125-foot bronze statue of Ahom General Lachit Borphukan unveiled by PM Modi?",
    options: [
      "Jorhat, Assam",
      "Guwahati, Assam",
      "Shillong, Meghalaya",
      "Imphal, Manipur",
    ],
    answer: "Jorhat, Assam",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was India’s first underwater metro train service launched by PM Modi?",
    options: ["Kolkata", "Mumbai", "Delhi", "Chennai"],
    answer: "Kolkata",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What significant infrastructure project did PM Modi virtually inaugurate in Tawang, Arunachal Pradesh?",
    options: [
      "Sela Tunnel",
      "Brahmaputra Bridge",
      "Teesta Dam",
      "Namdapha National Park",
    ],
    answer: "Sela Tunnel",
  },
  {
    question: "Who built the Sela Tunnel in Arunachal Pradesh?",
    options: [
      "Border Road Organization (BRO)",
      "National Highways Authority of India (NHAI)",
      "Indian Army Corps of Engineers",
      "Public Works Department (PWD)",
    ],
    answer: "Border Road Organization (BRO)",
  },
  {
    question: "What is significant about the Sela Tunnel in Arunachal Pradesh?",
    options: [
      "It is the world’s longest twin tunnel built at an altitude of above 13,000 feet",
      "It is the longest underwater tunnel in India",
      "It is India’s first tunnel for high-speed trains",
      "It connects the eastern and western borders of Arunachal Pradesh",
    ],
    answer:
      "It is the world’s longest twin tunnel built at an altitude of above 13,000 feet",
  },
  {
    question: "Which state has been recognized as 'Tsunami Ready' by UNESCO?",
    options: ["Odisha", "Kerala", "Andhra Pradesh", "Tamil Nadu"],
    answer: "Odisha",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which state in India implemented the first 'Dedicated Semiconductor Policy'?",
    options: ["Gujarat", "Maharashtra", "Tamil Nadu", "Uttar Pradesh"],
    answer: "Gujarat",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which president fled Damascus as Syrian rebel forces claimed control of the city?",
    options: [
      "President Assad",
      "President Bashar al-Assad",
      "President Khaled Khoja",
      "President Saad Hariri",
    ],
    answer: "President Assad",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries did PM Modi visit in his recent trip?",
    options: [
      "Nigeria, Brazil, and Guyana",
      "Brazil, Argentina, and Egypt",
      "Nigeria, South Africa, and Kenya",
      "Brazil, China, and Russia",
    ],
    answer: "Nigeria, Brazil, and Guyana",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the current president of Nigeria?",
    options: [
      "Bola Ahmed Tinubu",
      "Muhammadu Buhari",
      "Goodluck Jonathan",
      "Atiku Abubakar",
    ],
    answer: "Bola Ahmed Tinubu",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the president of Guyana?",
    options: ["Irfaan Ali", "David Granger", "Barack Obama", "Nicolás Maduro"],
    answer: "Irfaan Ali",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the president of Argentina?",
    options: [
      "Lula da Silva",
      "Alberto Fernández",
      "Cristina Fernández de Kirchner",
      "Mauricio Macri",
    ],
    answer: "Lula da Silva",
  },
  {
    question: "Why did Ecuador declare a state of emergency?",
    options: [
      "Due to forest fires and water shortage",
      "Due to an economic crisis",
      "Due to political unrest",
      "Due to a volcanic eruption",
    ],
    answer: "Due to forest fires and water shortage",
  },
  {
    question: "What significant event occurred in Gabon recently?",
    options: [
      "Approved a new constitution in a referendum",
      "Held presidential elections",
      "Declared independence from France",
      "Signed a peace agreement with rebels",
    ],
    answer: "Approved a new constitution in a referendum",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Why was French Prime Minister Michel Barnier’s government removed?",
    options: [
      "Through a no-confidence vote",
      "Due to economic failure",
      "Due to a scandal",
      "Due to a military coup",
    ],
    answer: "Through a no-confidence vote",
  },
  {
    question: "Which country implemented a controversial burqa ban?",
    options: ["Switzerland", "France", "Germany", "Belgium"],
    answer: "Switzerland",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where did China inaugurate its first atmospheric monitoring station?",
    options: [
      "Zhongshan Station, Antarctica",
      "Mount Everest, Nepal",
      "Beijing, China",
      "Tianjin, China",
    ],
    answer: "Zhongshan Station, Antarctica",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where is the world’s first ‘high-altitude’ para sports center located?",
    options: [
      "Leh, Ladakh",
      "Srinagar, Jammu & Kashmir",
      "Manali, Himachal Pradesh",
      "Kullu, Himachal Pradesh",
    ],
    answer: "Leh, Ladakh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme of the 43rd Indian International Trade Fair (IITF) 2024?",
    options: [
      "Viksit Bharat @2047",
      "Atmanirbhar Bharat",
      "Sustainable Development Goals",
      "Digital India",
    ],
    answer: "Viksit Bharat @2047",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How many metric tons of food grains and edibles did India ship to Suriname as part of social welfare aid?",
    options: [
      "425 metric tons",
      "350 metric tons",
      "500 metric tons",
      "600 metric tons",
    ],
    answer: "425 metric tons",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How many looted artefacts worth $10 million were returned from the USA to India?",
    options: ["More than 1400", "500", "200", "1000"],
    answer: "More than 1400",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the nature of the ceasefire deal between Israel and Hezbollah?",
    options: [
      "A ceasefire deal was reached",
      "A peace treaty was signed",
      "A trade agreement was established",
      "A prisoner swap took place",
    ],
    answer: "A ceasefire deal was reached",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where did the 31st Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC) summit take place?",
    options: ["Lima, Peru", "Sydney, Australia", "Tokyo, Japan", "Singapore"],
    answer: "Lima, Peru",
  },
  {
    question: "What happened to a Saurya Airlines plane on July 24?",
    options: [
      "The plane crashed, killing 18 people",
      "The plane was hijacked",
      "The plane made an emergency landing",
      "The plane was struck by lightning",
    ],
    answer: "The plane crashed, killing 18 people",
  },
  {
    question: "What gift was presented to the Russian president from India?",
    options: [
      "Sohrai painting",
      "Madhubani painting",
      "Warli art",
      "Tanjore painting",
    ],
    answer: "Sohrai painting",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which country was declared malaria-free by the World Health Organization (WHO)?",
    options: ["Egypt", "India", "Sri Lanka", "Thailand"],
    answer: "Egypt",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Why did India recall its high commissioner and other diplomats from Canada?",
    options: [
      "Due to diplomatic tensions",
      "Due to trade disagreements",
      "Due to national security issues",
      "Due to a spy scandal",
    ],
    answer: "Due to diplomatic tensions",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How much is the deal between India and the USA for predator drones and an MRO facility?",
    options: ["32,000 crore", "25,000 crore", "50,000 crore", "40,000 crore"],
    answer: "32,000 crore",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which country became the first in the world to eliminate leprosy?",
    options: ["Jordan", "India", "Brazil", "Thailand"],
    answer: "Jordan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which country has been officially authorized to join the BRICS New Development Bank?",
    options: ["Algeria", "Egypt", "Argentina", "Turkey"],
    answer: "Algeria",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did IIT Delhi open its first international campus?",
    options: ["Abu Dhabi", "Singapore", "Dubai", "London"],
    answer: "Abu Dhabi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which country has banned social media for children below the age of 16?",
    options: ["Australia", "Germany", "France", "USA"],
    answer: "Australia",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the current Prime Minister and President of Poland?",
    options: [
      "Donald Tusk, Andrzej Duda",
      "Mateusz Morawiecki, Andrzej Duda",
      "Jarosław Kaczyński, Bronisław Komorowski",
      "Władysław Kosiniak-Kamysz, Andrzej Duda",
    ],
    answer: "Donald Tusk, Andrzej Duda",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which country is the first in the world to allow voters to elect judges?",
    options: ["Mexico", "USA", "Switzerland", "South Korea"],
    answer: "Mexico",
  },
  {
    question: "Which country became the first to lose all of its glaciers?",
    options: ["Venezuela", "Iceland", "Nepal", "Switzerland"],
    answer: "Venezuela",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the first overseas Jan Aushadhi Kendra opened?",
    options: ["Mauritius", "Nepal", "Sri Lanka", "Bangladesh"],
    answer: "Mauritius",
  },
  {
    question: "Why were eight former Indian Navy personnel detained in Qatar?",
    options: [
      "On espionage charges but were later released",
      "For illegal fishing activities",
      "For violating immigration laws",
      "For involvement in a diplomatic dispute",
    ],
    answer: "On espionage charges but were later released",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the AI-generated spokesperson for Ukraine?",
    options: [
      "Victoria Shi",
      "Sophie Liu",
      "Olga Petrovna",
      "Irina Konstantinova",
    ],
    answer: "Victoria Shi",
  },
  {
    question: "Which country is home to the world’s first AI diplomat?",
    options: ["Ukraine", "USA", "China", "Russia"],
    answer: "Ukraine",
  },
  {
    question:
      "From which country did India receive the highest Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) in 2023-24?",
    options: ["Singapore", "USA", "Japan", "United Kingdom"],
    answer: "Singapore",
  },
  {
    question: "Which country introduced new 3D holographic banknotes?",
    options: ["Japan", "South Korea", "USA", "Australia"],
    answer: "Japan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which two countries signed an agreement regarding Chabahar port?",
    options: [
      "India and Iran",
      "India and Afghanistan",
      "India and Pakistan",
      "Iran and Afghanistan",
    ],
    answer: "India and Iran",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which country became the first Southeast Asian country to recognize same-sex marriage?",
    options: ["Thailand", "Vietnam", "Singapore", "Malaysia"],
    answer: "Thailand",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Mongla port located?",
    options: ["Bangladesh", "India", "Sri Lanka", "Myanmar"],
    answer: "Bangladesh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which country is home to Dar es Salaam port?",
    options: ["Tanzania", "Kenya", "Uganda", "Mozambique"],
    answer: "Tanzania",
  },
  {
    question: "In which country is Haifa port located?",
    options: ["Israel", "Jordan", "Turkey", "Lebanon"],
    answer: "Israel",
  },
  {
    question: "How did Iranian President Ebrahim Raisi die?",
    options: [
      "In a helicopter crash",
      "In a car accident",
      "From a heart attack",
      "Due to poisoning",
    ],
    answer: "In a helicopter crash",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What recent law did Iraq’s parliament pass regarding same-sex relationships?",
    options: [
      "Criminalizing same-sex relationships with a 15-year prison sentence",
      "Decriminalizing same-sex relationships",
      "Allowing civil unions",
      "Imposing a death penalty for same-sex relationships",
    ],
    answer:
      "Criminalizing same-sex relationships with a 15-year prison sentence",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which country became the first globally to embed abortion rights into its constitution?",
    options: ["France", "USA", "Mexico", "Canada"],
    answer: "France",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where did PM Modi inaugurate the first Hindu temple in Abu Dhabi?",
    options: [
      "BAPS Mandir",
      "ISKCON Temple",
      "Shirdi Sai Baba Temple",
      "Lakshmi Narayan Temple",
    ],
    answer: "BAPS Mandir",
  },
  {
    question: "Which overseas port did India secure as its second?",
    options: [
      "Sittwe port in Myanmar",
      "Chabahar port in Iran",
      "Cochin port in India",
      "Hamad port in Qatar",
    ],
    answer: "Sittwe port in Myanmar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which country introduced ZiG, a new gold-backed currency?",
    options: ["Zimbabwe", "South Africa", "Nigeria", "Venezuela"],
    answer: "Zimbabwe",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was the 16th session of the United Nations Convention to Combat Desertification (UNCCD) held?",
    options: [
      "Riyadh, Saudi Arabia",
      "Geneva, Switzerland",
      "New York, USA",
      "Cairo, Egypt",
    ],
    answer: "Riyadh, Saudi Arabia",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the theme of COP 16 (UNCCD)?",
    options: [
      "Our land. Our future.",
      "Climate action for a better world",
      "Sustainability in the desert",
      "Restoring ecosystems, rethinking progress",
    ],
    answer: "Our land. Our future.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will the World Maritime Technology Conference 2024 be held?",
    options: ["Chennai, India", "Singapore", "Dubai, UAE", "London, UK"],
    answer: "Chennai, India",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which session of the UN Commission on Narcotic Drugs will India chair for the first time?",
    options: ["68th session", "70th session", "72nd session", "66th session"],
    answer: "68th session",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the World Hydrogen Summit 2024 take place?",
    options: [
      "Rotterdam, Netherlands",
      "Berlin, Germany",
      "Paris, France",
      "Oslo, Norway",
    ],
    answer: "Rotterdam, Netherlands",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the 2nd India-CARICOM Summit held?",
    options: ["Georgetown", "Port of Spain", "New Delhi", "Kingston"],
    answer: "Georgetown",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did the 19th G20 Summit take place?",
    options: ["Rio, Brazil", "New Delhi, India", "London, UK", "Paris, France"],
    answer: "Rio, Brazil",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the motto of the 19th G20 Summit?",
    options: [
      "Building a just world and a sustainable planet.",
      "Strengthening global partnerships for growth",
      "Empowering the future of economies",
      "A fairer world for sustainable development",
    ],
    answer: "Building a just world and a sustainable planet.",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the next G20 Summit take place?",
    options: [
      "Johannesburg, South Africa",
      "Berlin, Germany",
      "Bali, Indonesia",
      "New York, USA",
    ],
    answer: "Johannesburg, South Africa",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the Global Cooperative Conference 2024 held?",
    options: ["Delhi, India", "London, UK", "Paris, France", "New York, USA"],
    answer: "Delhi, India",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the theme of the Global Cooperative Conference 2024?",
    options: [
      "Cooperation creates prosperity for all.",
      "Unity in global prosperity",
      "Building sustainable economies",
      "Collaboration for social equity",
    ],
    answer: "Cooperation creates prosperity for all.",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the 2024 BRICS summit be held?",
    options: [
      "Kazan, Russia",
      "New Delhi, India",
      "Beijing, China",
      "Brasília, Brazil",
    ],
    answer: "Kazan, Russia",
  },
  {
    question: "Which new countries have joined BRICS in 2024?",
    options: [
      "Iran, Egypt, Ethiopia, UAE, Saudi Arabia",
      "Pakistan, Argentina, Bangladesh, Mexico, Algeria",
      "Nigeria, Indonesia, South Korea, Turkey, Brazil",
      "Turkey, Egypt, Bangladesh, Qatar, Venezuela",
    ],
    answer: "Iran, Egypt, Ethiopia, UAE, Saudi Arabia",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the 2024 NATO Summit be held?",
    options: [
      "Washington, USA",
      "Berlin, Germany",
      "London, UK",
      "Paris, France",
    ],
    answer: "Washington, USA",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was the 2024 SCO (Shanghai Cooperation Organization) Summit held?",
    options: [
      "Astana, Kazakhstan",
      "Tashkent, Uzbekistan",
      "Bishkek, Kyrgyzstan",
      "Beijing, China",
    ],
    answer: "Astana, Kazakhstan",
  },
  {
    question: "Which country became the 10th member of the SCO?",
    options: ["Belarus", "Turkey", "Iran", "India"],
    answer: "Belarus",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the SCO Heads of Government Summit held in 2024?",
    options: [
      "Islamabad, Pakistan",
      "Astana, Kazakhstan",
      "New Delhi, India",
      "Moscow, Russia",
    ],
    answer: "Islamabad, Pakistan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will the 29th session of the UN Climate Change Conference (COP 29) be held?",
    options: [
      "Baku, Azerbaijan",
      "Paris, France",
      "New York, USA",
      "Berlin, Germany",
    ],
    answer: "Baku, Azerbaijan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will the 30th session of the UN Climate Change Conference (COP 30) be held in 2025?",
    options: ["Brazil", "Australia", "India", "South Africa"],
    answer: "Brazil",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What global initiative was launched by the UAE during COP 29 in Azerbaijan?",
    options: [
      "Global Energy Efficiency Alliance",
      "Green Earth Initiative",
      "Carbon Emission Reduction Pact",
      "International Solar Energy Partnership",
    ],
    answer: "Global Energy Efficiency Alliance",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will the 2nd Asia Pacific Ministerial Conference on Civil Aviation 2024 be held?",
    options: [
      "New Delhi, India",
      "Tokyo, Japan",
      "Sydney, Australia",
      "Singapore",
    ],
    answer: "New Delhi, India",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the G7 Summit organized?",
    options: [
      "Apulia, Italy",
      "Berlin, Germany",
      "Paris, France",
      "London, UK",
    ],
    answer: "Apulia, Italy",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the G7 Summit be held in 2025?",
    options: [
      "Alberta, Canada",
      "Berlin, Germany",
      "New York, USA",
      "London, UK",
    ],
    answer: "Alberta, Canada",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will the 46th Antarctic Treaty Consultative Meeting be held?",
    options: [
      "Kochi, Kerala",
      "New Delhi, India",
      "Cape Town, South Africa",
      "Melbourne, Australia",
    ],
    answer: "Kochi, Kerala",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the Global IndiaAI Summit 2024 be held?",
    options: [
      "New Delhi, India",
      "Bangalore, India",
      "Singapore",
      "Tokyo, Japan",
    ],
    answer: "New Delhi, India",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the ASEAN Summit 2024 be held?",
    options: [
      "Vientiane, Laos",
      "Manila, Philippines",
      "Singapore",
      "Jakarta, Indonesia",
    ],
    answer: "Vientiane, Laos",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the ASEAN Summit 2025 be held?",
    options: ["Malaysia", "Thailand", "Vietnam", "Singapore"],
    answer: "Malaysia",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the 21st ASEAN-India Summit 2024 be held?",
    options: [
      "Vientiane, Laos PDR",
      "New Delhi, India",
      "Manila, Philippines",
      "Singapore",
    ],
    answer: "Vientiane, Laos PDR",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the 19th East Asia Summit be held?",
    options: [
      "Vientiane, Laos PDR",
      "Tokyo, Japan",
      "Singapore",
      "Beijing, China",
    ],
    answer: "Vientiane, Laos PDR",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was the 46th UNESCO World Heritage Committee session held?",
    options: [
      "Bharat Mandapam, New Delhi",
      "Paris, France",
      "Rome, Italy",
      "Berlin, Germany",
    ],
    answer: "Bharat Mandapam, New Delhi",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the 3rd Voice of Global South Summit 2024 be held?",
    options: ["India", "Brazil", "South Africa", "Indonesia"],
    answer: "India",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the 19th NAM Summit 2024 be held?",
    options: ["Uganda", "Egypt", "Pakistan", "Turkey"],
    answer: "Uganda",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did the 16th World Future Energy Summit commence in 2024?",
    options: ["Abu Dhabi, UAE", "Dubai, UAE", "Cairo, Egypt", "Singapore"],
    answer: "Abu Dhabi, UAE",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the 9th Raisina Dialogue 2024 be held?",
    options: ["Delhi, India", "London, UK", "Paris, France", "Berlin, Germany"],
    answer: "Delhi, India",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who joined as the chief guest for the 9th Raisina Dialogue 2024?",
    options: [
      "Greece’s Prime Minister Kyriakos Mitsotakis",
      "Canada’s Prime Minister Justin Trudeau",
      "Japan’s Prime Minister Fumio Kishida",
      "Germany’s Chancellor Olaf Scholz",
    ],
    answer: "Greece’s Prime Minister Kyriakos Mitsotakis",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the 7th Indian Ocean Conference 2024 be held?",
    options: [
      "Perth, Australia",
      "Colombo, Sri Lanka",
      "New Delhi, India",
      "Singapore",
    ],
    answer: "Perth, Australia",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the World Government Summit 2024 be held?",
    options: ["Dubai, UAE", "Doha, Qatar", "Abu Dhabi, UAE", "Manama, Bahrain"],
    answer: "Dubai, UAE",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will the World Sustainable Development Summit 2024 be held?",
    options: [
      "New Delhi, India",
      "Paris, France",
      "Copenhagen, Denmark",
      "Berlin, Germany",
    ],
    answer: "New Delhi, India",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the annual flagship event of The Energy and Resources Institute (TERI)?",
    options: [
      "World Sustainable Development Summit 2024",
      "Global Renewable Energy Summit",
      "Energy Efficiency Expo",
      "International Climate Change Conference",
    ],
    answer: "World Sustainable Development Summit 2024",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will the Quad Summit 2024 be held?",
    options: [
      "Delaware, USA",
      "Sydney, Australia",
      "New Delhi, India",
      "Tokyo, Japan",
    ],
    answer: "Delaware, USA",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries are part of the Quad?",
    options: [
      "Australia, India, Japan, and the USA",
      "India, Japan, China, and Russia",
      "USA, UK, Canada, and Australia",
      "India, Pakistan, Bangladesh, and Sri Lanka",
    ],
    answer: "Australia, India, Japan, and the USA",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the Cancer Moonshot Initiative?",
    options: [
      "A global initiative aimed at accelerating the development of cancer treatments",
      "A space program to send scientists to the moon",
      "A campaign to raise awareness about cancer prevention",
      "A health program for childhood cancer",
    ],
    answer:
      "A global initiative aimed at accelerating the development of cancer treatments",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will the 64th International Sugar Organization Council Meeting be held?",
    options: [
      "New Delhi, India",
      "London, UK",
      "Paris, France",
      "Bangkok, Thailand",
    ],
    answer: "New Delhi, India",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will World Food India 2024 be held?",
    options: [
      "Bharat Mandapam, New Delhi",
      "Mumbai, India",
      "Singapore",
      "Cairo, Egypt",
    ],
    answer: "Bharat Mandapam, New Delhi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will the International Telecommunication Union (ITU) and World Telecommunication Standardization Assembly (WTSA) 2024 be held?",
    options: [
      "New Delhi, India",
      "Geneva, Switzerland",
      "Abu Dhabi, UAE",
      "Paris, France",
    ],
    answer: "New Delhi, India",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was India's first-ever space exercise conducted by the Defence Space Agency?",
    options: [
      "Antariksha Abhyas",
      "Vayu Shakti",
      "Suraksha Abhyas",
      "Space Vanguard",
    ],
    answer: "Antariksha Abhyas",
  },
  {
    question: "Where will Harimau Shakti 2024 be held?",
    options: [
      "Banting Camp, Pahang, Malaysia",
      "Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia",
      "Singapore",
      "Perth, Australia",
    ],
    answer: "Banting Camp, Pahang, Malaysia",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where will the National Maritime Search and Rescue Exercise (SAREX-24) be held?",
    options: ["Kochi, India", "Mumbai, India", "Chennai, India", "Goa, India"],
    answer: "Kochi, India",
  },
  {
    question: "What is CINBAX, and which countries participate in it?",
    options: [
      "A defence exercise between India and Cambodia",
      "A trade partnership between India and Cambodia",
      "A maritime exercise between India and Bangladesh",
      "A military exercise between India and China",
    ],
    answer: "A defence exercise between India and Cambodia",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries are involved in the Agni Warrior exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Singapore",
      "India and USA",
      "India and Japan",
      "India and Australia",
    ],
    answer: "India and Singapore",
  },
  {
    question: "What countries participate in the Austrahind exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Australia",
      "India and Singapore",
      "India and the USA",
      "India and Malaysia",
    ],
    answer: "India and Australia",
  },
  {
    question: "What countries participate in the Vinbax exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Vietnam",
      "India and Malaysia",
      "India and Thailand",
      "India and Sri Lanka",
    ],
    answer: "India and Vietnam",
  },
  {
    question: "What countries are involved in the Garud Shakti exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Indonesia",
      "India and Singapore",
      "India and Sri Lanka",
      "India and Nepal",
    ],
    answer: "India and Indonesia",
  },
  {
    question: "What countries are involved in the Vajra Prahar exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and the USA",
      "India and Japan",
      "India and the UK",
      "India and Russia",
    ],
    answer: "India and the USA",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the First Maritime Partnership Exercise (MPX), and which countries participate in it?",
    options: [
      "India and Germany",
      "India and France",
      "India and Japan",
      "India and the USA",
    ],
    answer: "India and Germany",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries participate in the Kazind exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Kazakhstan",
      "India and Kyrgyzstan",
      "India and Pakistan",
      "India and Uzbekistan",
    ],
    answer: "India and Kazakhstan",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries are involved in the Malabar naval exercise?",
    options: [
      "Australia, India, Japan, and the USA",
      "India, USA, UK, and Japan",
      "India, Singapore, USA, and Russia",
      "India, Japan, South Korea, and the USA",
    ],
    answer: "Australia, India, Japan, and the USA",
  },
  {
    question: "What countries participate in the IBSAMAR maritime exercise?",
    options: [
      "India, Brazil, and South Africa",
      "India, Brazil, and China",
      "India, South Africa, and Russia",
      "India, Brazil, and Australia",
    ],
    answer: "India, Brazil, and South Africa",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Naseem-al-Bahr naval exercise held?",
    options: [
      "Off the coast of Goa, India",
      "In the Arabian Sea",
      "In the Bay of Bengal",
      "Off the coast of Sri Lanka",
    ],
    answer: "Off the coast of Goa, India",
  },
  {
    question: "What countries are involved in the Simbex maritime exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Singapore",
      "India and Japan",
      "India and Malaysia",
      "India and South Korea",
    ],
    answer: "India and Singapore",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries participate in the Al Najah V exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Oman",
      "India and Saudi Arabia",
      "India and Qatar",
      "India and UAE",
    ],
    answer: "India and Oman",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the focus of the Yudh Abhyas exercise, and which countries participate?",
    options: [
      "Ground operations, India and the USA",
      "Naval operations, India and Japan",
      "Air operations, India and Australia",
      "Peacekeeping, India and Sri Lanka",
    ],
    answer: "Ground operations, India and the USA",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries are involved in the Mitra Shakti exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Sri Lanka",
      "India and Pakistan",
      "India and Bangladesh",
      "India and Myanmar",
    ],
    answer: "India and Sri Lanka",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the focus of the Udara Shakti exercise, and which countries participate?",
    options: [
      "Air force operations, India and Malaysia",
      "Naval operations, India and Singapore",
      "Ground operations, India and Indonesia",
      "Peacekeeping, India and Bangladesh",
    ],
    answer: "Air force operations, India and Malaysia",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How many countries participate in the Tarang Shakti air exercise?",
    options: ["30 countries", "25 countries", "35 countries", "20 countries"],
    answer: "30 countries",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which countries are involved in the Maritime Partnership Exercise (MPX)?",
    options: [
      "India and Russia",
      "India and China",
      "India and the USA",
      "India and Japan",
    ],
    answer: "India and Russia",
  },
  {
    question: "How many countries participate in the Khaan Quest exercise?",
    options: ["23 countries", "20 countries", "25 countries", "30 countries"],
    answer: "23 countries",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the focus of the Pitch Black air exercise, and which countries participate?",
    options: [
      "Air force operations, India and Australia",
      "Naval operations, India and Japan",
      "Ground operations, India and the USA",
      "Peacekeeping, India and Sri Lanka",
    ],
    answer: "Air force operations, India and Australia",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries are involved in the Maitree exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Thailand",
      "India and Sri Lanka",
      "India and Myanmar",
      "India and Vietnam",
    ],
    answer: "India and Thailand",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries are involved in the Nomadic Elephant exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Mongolia",
      "India and Bhutan",
      "India and Nepal",
      "India and Pakistan",
    ],
    answer: "India and Mongolia",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How many countries participate in the Rim of the Pacific (RIMPAC) exercise?",
    options: ["29 countries", "25 countries", "30 countries", "35 countries"],
    answer: "29 countries",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which countries are members of the Shanghai Cooperation Organization (SCO) that participate in military interactions?",
    options: [
      "All SCO members",
      "India, China, and Russia",
      "India, Pakistan, and Iran",
      "India, Kazakhstan, and Uzbekistan",
    ],
    answer: "All SCO members",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries are involved in the Red Flag air exercise?",
    options: [
      "Singapore, Germany, the USA, the UK, the Netherlands, and India",
      "India, Russia, and China",
      "India, Japan, and South Korea",
      "India, USA, and Australia",
    ],
    answer: "Singapore, Germany, the USA, the UK, the Netherlands, and India",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries are involved in the Jimex naval exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Japan",
      "India and USA",
      "India and Singapore",
      "India and Malaysia",
    ],
    answer: "India and Japan",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries are involved in the Hopex air exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Egypt",
      "India and Israel",
      "India and Saudi Arabia",
      "India and UAE",
    ],
    answer: "India and Egypt",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries participate in the Tarkash exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and the USA",
      "India and China",
      "India and Pakistan",
      "India and Sri Lanka",
    ],
    answer: "India and the USA",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the focus of the Shakti exercise, and which countries participate?",
    options: [
      "Counter-terrorism, India and France",
      "Naval operations, India and Japan",
      "Air force operations, India and Australia",
      "Ground operations, India and the USA",
    ],
    answer: "Counter-terrorism, India and France",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which countries are involved in the Maritime Partnership Exercise (MPX) with India and the Philippines?",
    options: [
      "India and the Philippines",
      "India and Russia",
      "India and Singapore",
      "India and Vietnam",
    ],
    answer: "India and the Philippines",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which countries are involved in the Maritime Partnership Exercise (MPX) between India and the UK?",
    options: [
      "India and the UK",
      "India and the USA",
      "India and Russia",
      "India and Japan",
    ],
    answer: "India and the UK",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries participate in the Dustlik exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Uzbekistan",
      "India and Kazakhstan",
      "India and Russia",
      "India and Sri Lanka",
    ],
    answer: "India and Uzbekistan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the focus of the Samudra Laksamana exercise, and which countries participate?",
    options: [
      "Maritime exercise, India and Malaysia",
      "Naval exercise, India and Singapore",
      "Air force exercise, India and the USA",
      "Ground operations, India and Bangladesh",
    ],
    answer: "Maritime exercise, India and Malaysia",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries participate in the Sea Defenders exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and the USA",
      "India and Russia",
      "India and Japan",
      "India and China",
    ],
    answer: "India and the USA",
  },
  {
    question: "How many countries participate in the Cutlass Express exercise?",
    options: ["16 countries", "18 countries", "20 countries", "22 countries"],
    answer: "16 countries",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries are involved in the Lamitiye exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Seychelles",
      "India and Mauritius",
      "India and the Maldives",
      "India and Sri Lanka",
    ],
    answer: "India and Seychelles",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the focus of the Tiger Triumph exercise, and which countries participate?",
    options: [
      "Joint military exercise, India and the USA",
      "Counter-terrorism, India and France",
      "Peacekeeping, India and Japan",
      "Ground operations, India and Russia",
    ],
    answer: "Joint military exercise, India and the USA",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries participate in the IMT exercise?",
    options: [
      "India, Mozambique, and Tanzania",
      "India, Kenya, and Ethiopia",
      "India, Sri Lanka, and Bangladesh",
      "India, Thailand, and Myanmar",
    ],
    answer: "India, Mozambique, and Tanzania",
  },
  {
    question: "How many countries participate in the Milan (Naval) exercise?",
    options: ["51 countries", "48 countries", "55 countries", "60 countries"],
    answer: "51 countries",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries participate in the Dosti-16 exercise?",
    options: [
      "India, Sri Lanka, and the Maldives",
      "India, Bangladesh, and Nepal",
      "India, Pakistan, and China",
      "India, Afghanistan, and Bhutan",
    ],
    answer: "India, Sri Lanka, and the Maldives",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the focus of the Dharma Guardian exercise, and which countries participate?",
    options: [
      "Counter-terrorism, India and Japan",
      "Peacekeeping, India and Sri Lanka",
      "Maritime security, India and the USA",
      "Air force operations, India and Russia",
    ],
    answer: "Counter-terrorism, India and Japan",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries are involved in the Desert Cyclone exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and the UAE",
      "India and Saudi Arabia",
      "India and Qatar",
      "India and Bahrain",
    ],
    answer: "India and the UAE",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries are involved in the Sea Dragon exercise?",
    options: [
      "India, Japan, South Korea, Australia, and the USA",
      "India, Singapore, Malaysia, and Indonesia",
      "India, Russia, China, and Japan",
      "India, the UK, the USA, and Canada",
    ],
    answer: "India, Japan, South Korea, Australia, and the USA",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the focus of the Sahyog Kaijin exercise, and which countries participate?",
    options: [
      "Maritime exercise, India and Japan",
      "Counter-terrorism, India and China",
      "Ground operations, India and Indonesia",
      "Peacekeeping, India and Nepal",
    ],
    answer: "Maritime exercise, India and Japan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which countries are involved in the Ex-Ayutthaya (Naval) exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Thailand",
      "India and Vietnam",
      "India and Myanmar",
      "India and Malaysia",
    ],
    answer: "India and Thailand",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries participate in the Cyclone exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Egypt",
      "India and UAE",
      "India and Sri Lanka",
      "India and Australia",
    ],
    answer: "India and Egypt",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries participate in the Khanjar exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Kyrgyzstan",
      "India and Kazakhstan",
      "India and Afghanistan",
      "India and Tajikistan",
    ],
    answer: "India and Kyrgyzstan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the focus of the Desert Knight (Air) exercise, and which countries participate?",
    options: [
      "Air defense, India, France, and the UAE",
      "Naval warfare, India, the USA, and the UK",
      "Ground operations, India and Russia",
      "Peacekeeping, India and Nepal",
    ],
    answer: "Air defense, India, France, and the UAE",
  },
  {
    question: "Which countries are involved in the Sada Tanseeq exercise?",
    options: [
      "India and Saudi Arabia",
      "India and Qatar",
      "India and Oman",
      "India and Kuwait",
    ],
    answer: "India and Saudi Arabia",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where were the Anti-submarine warfare vessels 'Malpe' and 'Mulki' launched?",
    options: [
      "Cochin Shipyard",
      "Goa Shipyard",
      "Mazagon Dock Shipbuilders",
      "Hindustan Shipyard",
    ],
    answer: "Cochin Shipyard",
  },
  {
    question: "Which ships were built by Goa Shipyard Limited?",
    options: [
      "Fast patrol vessels 'Adamya' and 'Akshar'",
      "Submarines 'Arihant' and 'Arighaat'",
      "Frigates 'Tushil' and 'Talwar'",
      "Aircraft carriers 'Vikrant' and 'Viraat'",
    ],
    answer: "Fast patrol vessels 'Adamya' and 'Akshar'",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When was the second nuclear submarine INS Arighaat commissioned into the Indian Navy?",
    options: ["In Vishakhapatnam", "In Mumbai", "In Kochi", "In Goa"],
    answer: "In Vishakhapatnam",
  },
  {
    question: "Which was the first nuclear submarine of India?",
    options: ["INS Arihant", "INS Arighaat", "INS Chakra", "INS Sindhuvijay"],
    answer: "INS Arihant",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What missile did the Indian Navy successfully test-fire from its nuclear-powered submarine INS Arighaat?",
    options: [
      "K-4 missile",
      "K-15 missile",
      "Agni-3 missile",
      "Prithvi-2 missile",
    ],
    answer: "K-4 missile",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the new missile testing range located?",
    options: [
      "Nagayalanka, Andhra Pradesh",
      "Pokhran, Rajasthan",
      "Balasore, Odisha",
      "Chandipur, Odisha",
    ],
    answer: "Nagayalanka, Andhra Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question: "What is 'Samarthak,' and where was it constructed?",
    options: [
      "India's first indigenous multi-purpose vessel, L&T Shipyard",
      "India's first nuclear submarine, Vishakhapatnam",
      "India's first aircraft carrier, Kochi",
      "India's first stealth frigate, Mazagon Dock",
    ],
    answer: "India's first indigenous multi-purpose vessel, L&T Shipyard",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Indian company developed the Indian light tank 'Zorawar'?",
    options: [
      "Larsen & Toubro (L&T)",
      "Bharat Heavy Electricals Limited (BHEL)",
      "Tata Motors",
      "Mahindra Defence",
    ],
    answer: "Larsen & Toubro (L&T)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the name of the long-range glide bomb developed by India?",
    options: ["'Gaurav'", "'Akash'", "'Nirbhay'", "'Shakti'"],
    answer: "'Gaurav'",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which new multi-role stealth guided missile frigate was commissioned into the Indian Navy?",
    options: ["INS Tushil", "INS Vikrant", "INS Talwar", "INS Kamorta"],
    answer: "INS Tushil",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was India’s first analog space mission conducted?",
    options: [
      "Leh, Ladakh",
      "Sriharikota, Andhra Pradesh",
      "Bangalore, Karnataka",
      "Dehradun, Uttarakhand",
    ],
    answer: "Leh, Ladakh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the goal of Chandrayaan 4, and which country is collaborating with India on this mission?",
    options: [
      "To land at the moon’s south pole by 2030, with Japan",
      "To explore Mars, with Russia",
      "To study the sun, with the USA",
      "To send humans to the moon, with China",
    ],
    answer: "To land at the moon’s south pole by 2030, with Japan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the name of the Venus orbiting satellite mission scheduled for 2028?",
    options: ["Shukrayaan", "Mars-1", "Venus-2", "Suryan-1"],
    answer: "Shukrayaan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which country is set to test the world’s first wooden satellite?",
    options: ["Japan", "Germany", "USA", "India"],
    answer: "Japan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the goal of the Proba-3 mission of the European Space Agency, and where was it launched?",
    options: [
      "To study the corona of the sun, launched from Sriharikota",
      "To study Mars, launched from Cape Canaveral",
      "To observe Jupiter, launched from Baikonur",
      "To observe Saturn, launched from Guiana",
    ],
    answer: "To study the corona of the sun, launched from Sriharikota",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which countries signed the implementation agreement for the Gaganyaan mission?",
    options: [
      "India and Australia",
      "India and USA",
      "India and Japan",
      "India and Russia",
    ],
    answer: "India and Australia",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the objective of NASA’s Europa Clipper mission?",
    options: [
      "To search for life on Jupiter and its moon, Europa",
      "To study the sun’s corona",
      "To explore Mars’ moons",
      "To map the surface of Venus",
    ],
    answer: "To search for life on Jupiter and its moon, Europa",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which mission did NASA and SpaceX launch to bring back astronauts Sunita Williams and Butch Wilmore?",
    options: [
      "Crew-9 mission",
      "Crew-8 mission",
      "Crew-7 mission",
      "Crew-6 mission",
    ],
    answer: "Crew-9 mission",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Tamil Nadu-based startup developed India’s first reusable hybrid rocket, RHUMI-1?",
    options: [
      "Space Zone India",
      "Skyroot Aerospace",
      "Astra Space",
      "Agni Rocketry",
    ],
    answer: "Space Zone India",
  },
  {
    question: "What is a reusable launch vehicle?",
    options: [
      "A spacecraft designed to be launched, recovered, and launched again multiple times",
      "A spacecraft designed for one-time use only",
      "A satellite designed for multiple orbits",
      "A cargo capsule designed to travel to Mars",
    ],
    answer:
      "A spacecraft designed to be launched, recovered, and launched again multiple times",
  },
  {
    question: "What is SpaceX’s Polaris Dawn mission known for?",
    options: [
      "First private spacewalk at 700 kilometers above Earth",
      "First mission to the moon",
      "First Mars rover mission",
      "First commercial space station mission",
    ],
    answer: "First private spacewalk at 700 kilometers above Earth",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When is National Space Day 2024 observed, and what is its theme?",
    options: [
      "23 August 2024, 'Touching Lives While Touching the Moon'",
      "15 July 2024, 'Exploring New Frontiers'",
      "5 October 2024, 'Reaching for the Stars'",
      "12 April 2024, 'Space for All'",
    ],
    answer: "23 August 2024, 'Touching Lives While Touching the Moon'",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the Axiom (Ax-4) mission, and who will pilot it?",
    options: [
      "A mission to the International Space Station, piloted by Group Captain Shubhanshu Shukla",
      "A mission to the Moon, piloted by Commander Rakesh Sharma",
      "A mission to Mars, piloted by Captain Sunita Williams",
      "A mission to the International Space Station, piloted by Dr. Kalpana Chawla",
    ],
    answer:
      "A mission to the International Space Station, piloted by Group Captain Shubhanshu Shukla",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the name of India’s deep-ocean mission and which vehicle is being developed for it?",
    options: [
      "Matsya 6000, deep submergence vehicle developed by NIOT and ISRO",
      "Samudra 5000, submersible vehicle by DRDO",
      "Matsya 5000, submersible by ISRO",
      "Dhanush 6000, deep-ocean research vehicle by CSIR",
    ],
    answer: "Matsya 6000, deep submergence vehicle developed by NIOT and ISRO",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which countries have already achieved successful deep-ocean crewed missions?",
    options: [
      "USA, Russia, China, France, Japan",
      "USA, Germany, Russia, China, Brazil",
      "India, Russia, China, Japan, South Korea",
      "USA, Japan, Germany, UK, France",
    ],
    answer: "USA, Russia, China, France, Japan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who made history by joining Blue Origin’s New Shepard-25 mission?",
    options: [
      "Gopichand Thotakura",
      "Rakesh Sharma",
      "Sunita Williams",
      "Kalpana Chawla",
    ],
    answer: "Gopichand Thotakura",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the world’s first 6G device launched?",
    options: ["Japan", "USA", "South Korea", "China"],
    answer: "Japan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was Asia’s first health research ‘pre-clinical network facility’ inaugurated?",
    options: [
      "Faridabad, Haryana",
      "Chandigarh, Punjab",
      "Bangalore, Karnataka",
      "Mumbai, Maharashtra",
    ],
    answer: "Faridabad, Haryana",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the Chang’e 6 spacecraft, and what is its significance?",
    options: [
      "First sampling and return mission from the far side of the moon, launched by China",
      "First rover on Mars, launched by China",
      "First satellite to study Venus, launched by India",
      "First manned mission to the Moon, launched by China",
    ],
    answer:
      "First sampling and return mission from the far side of the moon, launched by China",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the Indo-French infrared earth observation satellite mission TRISHNA designed to monitor?",
    options: [
      "Surface temperature and water management",
      "Air quality and climate change",
      "Oceans and marine life",
      "Soil moisture and agricultural health",
    ],
    answer: "Surface temperature and water management",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the Pushpak reusable launch vehicle, and what is its purpose?",
    options: [
      "A rocket designed to be used multiple times for space missions",
      "A satellite designed to orbit Earth for data collection",
      "A rover designed to explore Mars",
      "A cargo spacecraft for transporting supplies",
    ],
    answer: "A rocket designed to be used multiple times for space missions",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the name of India’s first gene therapy for cancer, and where was it launched?",
    options: [
      "CAR-T cell therapy, launched by President Draupadi Murmu at IIT Bombay",
      "ImmunoCure, launched by PM Narendra Modi at AIIMS",
      "GeneX, launched by the Ministry of Health at NITI Aayog",
      "OncoHeal, launched by the Union Minister of Science and Technology",
    ],
    answer:
      "CAR-T cell therapy, launched by President Draupadi Murmu at IIT Bombay",
  },
  {
    question: "What is NASA’s Dragonfly rotorcraft mission to Titan about?",
    options: [
      "Set to launch in 2028 to explore Saturn’s moon Titan",
      "Set to explore Mars in 2026",
      "Set to study Jupiter’s moon Europa in 2027",
      "Set to explore the sun's corona in 2030",
    ],
    answer: "Set to launch in 2028 to explore Saturn’s moon Titan",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the significance of Agnikul Cosmos’ Agnibaan rocket?",
    options: [
      "World’s first rocket powered by a fully 3D-printed engine",
      "First fully reusable rocket launched by India",
      "First rocket to be launched from the Indian Ocean",
      "First private satellite launcher by ISRO",
    ],
    answer: "World’s first rocket powered by a fully 3D-printed engine",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which private company launched India’s first private Earth observation satellite?",
    options: ["Tata", "Reliance", "Bharti Airtel", "HCL"],
    answer: "Tata",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is Mission Divyastra, and what technology does it mark the integration of?",
    options: [
      "The integration of Agni-5 missile with MIRV technology",
      "The development of the first Indian hypersonic missile",
      "The first satellite for national security",
      "The integration of the Chandrayaan-3 rover with AI technology",
    ],
    answer: "The integration of Agni-5 missile with MIRV technology",
  },
  {
    question: "What is NASA’s FLOAT mission, and what is its purpose?",
    options: [
      "To construct the first lunar railway system for payload transport on the moon",
      "To develop a space station for lunar research",
      "To explore the surface of Venus",
      "To send astronauts to Mars in 2035",
    ],
    answer:
      "To construct the first lunar railway system for payload transport on the moon",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is India’s Gaganyaan mission, and when is it expected to take place?",
    options: [
      "To send astronauts into space with a crew of humans to an orbit 400 km above Earth, scheduled for 2026",
      "To launch India’s first crewed Mars mission, scheduled for 2025",
      "To establish India’s first space station, scheduled for 2027",
      "To send a robotic rover to Venus, scheduled for 2026",
    ],
    answer:
      "To send astronauts into space with a crew of humans to an orbit 400 km above Earth, scheduled for 2026",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the name of the rocket that will launch India’s Gaganyaan mission?",
    options: [
      "GSLV Mk III (LVM-3)",
      "PSLV-C45",
      "GSLV Mk II",
      "Chandrayaan 2 rocket",
    ],
    answer: "GSLV Mk III (LVM-3)",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the author of 'Why Bharat Matters'?",
    options: [
      "Dr. S. Jaishankar",
      "Shashi Tharoor",
      "Nitin Gadkari",
      "Amit Shah",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. S. Jaishankar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote 'Tipu Sultan: The Saga of the Mysore Interregnum'?",
    options: [
      "Vikram Sampath",
      "William Dalrymple",
      "Ramachandra Guha",
      "Shashi Tharoor",
    ],
    answer: "Vikram Sampath",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the book 'Friends: India’s Closest Strategic Partners' about, and who is its author?",
    options: [
      "It discusses India’s strategic partnerships, authored by Prof. Sreeram Chaulia",
      "It is about India’s cultural ties with its neighbors, authored by Shashi Tharoor",
      "It explores India’s space collaborations, authored by Dr. S. Jaishankar",
      "It discusses India’s military alliances, authored by Manohar Parrikar",
    ],
    answer:
      "It discusses India’s strategic partnerships, authored by Prof. Sreeram Chaulia",
  },
  {
    question: "Who co-authored 'Sakshi Malik’s Memoir ‘Witness’'?",
    options: [
      "Sakshi Malik and Jonathan Selvaraj",
      "Sakshi Malik and Shailendra Singh",
      "Sakshi Malik and Kiran Bedi",
      "Sakshi Malik and Ravi Shastri",
    ],
    answer: "Sakshi Malik and Jonathan Selvaraj",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the author of 'Maa-Mother'?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Davendra Kumar Dhodawat",
      "Arundhati Roy",
      "M. J. Akbar",
      "Sudeep Chakravarti",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. Davendra Kumar Dhodawat",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme of 'Speaking with Nature: The Origins of Indian Environmentalism', and who wrote it?",
    options: [
      "It explores the history of environmentalism in India, written by Ramachandra Guha",
      "It discusses the role of religion in environmental protection, written by Ramesh Chandra",
      "It presents a scientific approach to conservation, written by Vandana Shiva",
      "It explores urban pollution, written by Sunita Narain",
    ],
    answer:
      "It explores the history of environmentalism in India, written by Ramachandra Guha",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the author of 'Beyond the Higgs Boson: The W Boson'?",
    options: [
      "Manik Kotwal",
      "Srinivasa Ramanujan",
      "C. N. R. Rao",
      "Subramanyan Chandrasekhar",
    ],
    answer: "Manik Kotwal",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the focus of 'Jamsetji Tata: Powerful Learnings for Corporate Success', and who are the authors?",
    options: [
      "It focuses on Jamsetji Tata's corporate philosophy, authored by R. Gopalakrishnan and Harish Bhat",
      "It discusses Tata Group’s history, authored by Ratan Tata and Shashi Tharoor",
      "It focuses on Jamsetji Tata's life story, authored by Gurcharan Das and Vikram Sampath",
      "It provides a business strategy based on Tata Group, authored by Deepak Parekh and Arvind Gupta",
    ],
    answer:
      "It focuses on Jamsetji Tata's corporate philosophy, authored by R. Gopalakrishnan and Harish Bhat",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote 'Ratan Tata: A Life'?",
    options: [
      "Thomas Mathew",
      "R. Gopalakrishnan",
      "Vikram Sampath",
      "Shashi Tharoor",
    ],
    answer: "Thomas Mathew",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is 'Mountain Mammals of the World' about, and who authored it?",
    options: [
      "It is a book about mountain-dwelling mammals, authored by M. K. Ranjitsinh",
      "It is a book on the ecology of mountain ranges, authored by Ramachandra Guha",
      "It is a photographic journey through the Himalayas, authored by Ruskin Bond",
      "It is a study of Himalayan biodiversity, authored by Ravi Chandra",
    ],
    answer:
      "It is a book about mountain-dwelling mammals, authored by M. K. Ranjitsinh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who authored 'Gandhi: A Life in Three Campaigns'?",
    options: [
      "M. J. Akbar",
      "Shashi Tharoor",
      "Ramachandra Guha",
      "Manohar Malgonkar",
    ],
    answer: "M. J. Akbar",
  },
  {
    question: "What is 'Mother Mary Comes to Me' by Arundhati Roy about?",
    options: [
      "A literary work exploring spirituality and narrative",
      "A novel set in the time of British India",
      "A book on contemporary Indian politics",
      "A travelogue of Roy’s journey to Kashmir",
    ],
    answer: "A literary work exploring spirituality and narrative",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the author of 'Power Within'?",
    options: [
      "Dr. R. Balasubramaniam",
      "Dr. S. Jaishankar",
      "Swami Vivekananda",
      "Narendra Modi",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. R. Balasubramaniam",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who wrote 'At the Wheel of Research: An Exclusive Biography of Dr. Soumya Swaminathan'?",
    options: [
      "Anuradha Mascarenhas",
      "Vikram Sampath",
      "Ramachandra Guha",
      "Shashi Tharoor",
    ],
    answer: "Anuradha Mascarenhas",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the author of 'Imperial Games in Tibet'?",
    options: [
      "Dilip Sinha",
      "Shashi Tharoor",
      "Ramachandra Guha",
      "William Dalrymple",
    ],
    answer: "Dilip Sinha",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the author of 'Call of the Gir'?",
    options: [
      "Parimal Nathwani",
      "Rajiv Gandhi",
      "Narendra Modi",
      "Jagdish Chandra",
    ],
    answer: "Parimal Nathwani",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote 'Save America'?",
    options: ["Donald Trump", "Barack Obama", "Joe Biden", "Ted Cruz"],
    answer: "Donald Trump",
  },
  {
    question: "'I Have the Streets' is authored by which Indian cricketer?",
    options: ["R. Ashwin", "Sachin Tendulkar", "Virat Kohli", "Yuvraj Singh"],
    answer: "R. Ashwin",
  },
  {
    question: "Who penned 'A Fly on the RBI Wall'?",
    options: [
      "Alpana Killawala",
      "D. Subbarao",
      "Raghuram Rajan",
      "Y. V. Reddy",
    ],
    answer: "Alpana Killawala",
  },
  {
    question: "'Source Code' is written by which tech pioneer?",
    options: ["Bill Gates", "Steve Jobs", "Mark Zuckerberg", "Elon Musk"],
    answer: "Bill Gates",
  },
  {
    question: "Who are the authors of 'Echoes of Faith'?",
    options: [
      "Ashok Lavasa and Novel Lavasa",
      "Kailash Satyarthi and Ashok Lavasa",
      "Dalai Lama and Kailash Satyarthi",
      "Dalai Lama and Novel Lavasa",
    ],
    answer: "Ashok Lavasa and Novel Lavasa",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the theme of 'The Book of Compassion' and who wrote it?",
    options: [
      "It focuses on kindness and humanity, co-authored by Dalai Lama and Kailash Satyarthi",
      "It discusses the environment, written by Vandana Shiva and Dalai Lama",
      "It covers Indian spirituality, written by Swami Vivekananda and Dalai Lama",
      "It discusses mental health, written by Kailash Satyarthi and Ashok Lavasa",
    ],
    answer:
      "It focuses on kindness and humanity, co-authored by Dalai Lama and Kailash Satyarthi",
  },
  {
    question: "'Breaking Rocks and Barriers' is authored by which geologist?",
    options: [
      "Sudipta Sengupta",
      "B. K. Agarwal",
      "Satyendra Tiwari",
      "Sushil Kumar",
    ],
    answer: "Sudipta Sengupta",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the author of 'The Prisoner of Bhopal'?",
    options: [
      "Tim Walker",
      "Brijendra Soni",
      "Chetan Bhagat",
      "Shashi Tharoor",
    ],
    answer: "Tim Walker",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the International Booker Prize 2024, and for which book?",
    options: [
      "Jenny Erpenbeck for 'Kairos', translated by Michael Hoffman",
      "Olga Tokarczuk for 'The Books of Jacob', translated by Jennifer Croft",
      "Georgi Gospodinov for 'Time Shelter', translated by Angela Rodel",
      "Han Kang for 'The White Book', translated by Deborah Smith",
    ],
    answer: "Jenny Erpenbeck for 'Kairos', translated by Michael Hoffman",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote 'Knife'?",
    options: ["Salman Rushdie", "Arundhati Roy", "Vikram Seth", "Kiran Desai"],
    answer: "Salman Rushdie",
  },
  {
    question: "'The Winner’s Mindset' is written by which former cricketer?",
    options: [
      "Shane Watson",
      "Ricky Ponting",
      "Michael Clarke",
      "Adam Gilchrist",
    ],
    answer: "Shane Watson",
  },
  {
    question: "Who authored 'India - The Road to Renaissance'?",
    options: [
      "Bhimeswara Challa",
      "R. Gopalakrishnan",
      "Sandeep Unnithan",
      "Nitin Gadkari",
    ],
    answer: "Bhimeswara Challa",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the focus of 'India’s Nuclear Titans', and who wrote it?",
    options: [
      "It explores India's nuclear history and leadership, authored by Soumya Awasthi",
      "It covers India's nuclear diplomacy, authored by K. Subrahmanyam",
      "It discusses India's nuclear energy policy, authored by Dr. Manmohan Singh",
      "It explores India’s atomic weapons program, authored by Shyam Saran",
    ],
    answer:
      "It explores India's nuclear history and leadership, authored by Soumya Awasthi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote 'Swallowing the Sun'?",
    options: [
      "Lakshmi Murdeshwar Puri",
      "Arundhati Roy",
      "Nayantara Sehgal",
      "Kiran Desai",
    ],
    answer: "Lakshmi Murdeshwar Puri",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the author of 'Just a Mercenary'?",
    options: ["D. Subbarao", "Raghuram Rajan", "C. Rangarajan", "Y. V. Reddy"],
    answer: "D. Subbarao",
  },
  {
    question: "'Ek Samandar, Mere Andar' is written by which author?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Sanjeev Kumar Joshi",
      "Dr. Harivansh Rai Bachchan",
      "Amitav Ghosh",
      "Ravinder Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. Sanjeev Kumar Joshi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who penned 'Dabbling in Diplomacy'?",
    options: ["S.D. Muni", "S. Jaishankar", "Shyam Saran", "K. Raghunath"],
    answer: "S.D. Muni",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who translated 'Fool Bahadur' into English, and who is the original author?",
    options: [
      "Abhay K. translated Jayanath Pati",
      "R. K. Narayan translated V. S. Naipaul",
      "Amitav Ghosh translated Rabindranath Tagore",
      "Vikram Seth translated Chetan Bhagat",
    ],
    answer: "Abhay K. translated Jayanath Pati",
  },
  {
    question: "'Sanskriti Ke Ayaam' is authored by which writer?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Manorama Mishra",
      "Dr. Rajendra Prasad",
      "Dr. Subhash Chandra",
      "Dr. Harish Chandra",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. Manorama Mishra",
  },
  {
    question: "'Anger Management' is written by which author?",
    options: [
      "Ajay Bisaria",
      "Amitabh Bachchan",
      "Chetan Bhagat",
      "Sudha Murthy",
    ],
    answer: "Ajay Bisaria",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'Assam’s Braveheart Lachit Barphukan' is written by which author?",
    options: [
      "Arup Kumar Dutta",
      "Homen Borgohain",
      "Mani Shankar Mukherjee",
      "Ramesh Chandra",
    ],
    answer: "Arup Kumar Dutta",
  },
  {
    question: "'Conversations with Aurangzeb' is authored by whom?",
    options: [
      "Charu Nivedita",
      "Shashi Tharoor",
      "William Dalrymple",
      "K.K. Aziz",
    ],
    answer: "Charu Nivedita",
  },
  {
    question: "Who penned 'The Cooking of Books'?",
    options: [
      "Ramachandra Guha",
      "Amartya Sen",
      "Arundhati Roy",
      "Nandan Nilekani",
    ],
    answer: "Ramachandra Guha",
  },
  {
    question: "Sashikant Ruia is associated with which business group?",
    options: ["Essar", "Reliance", "Tata Group", "Adani Group"],
    answer: "Essar",
  },
  {
    question: "Vardara Kamalakar Rao is a scholar in which musical instrument?",
    options: ["Mridangam", "Tabla", "Flute", "Sitar"],
    answer: "Mridangam",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the world's oldest person who passed away in England at the age of 112?",
    options: [
      "John Tinniswood",
      "Kane Tanaka",
      "Maria Braunschvig",
      "Jiroemon Kimura",
    ],
    answer: "John Tinniswood",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Harjit Singh Bedi served as a former judge in which institution?",
    options: [
      "Supreme Court of India",
      "High Court of Punjab and Haryana",
      "Delhi High Court",
      "Bombay High Court",
    ],
    answer: "Supreme Court of India",
  },
  {
    question: "Raj Manchanda is associated with which sport?",
    options: ["Squash", "Badminton", "Tennis", "Table Tennis"],
    answer: "Squash",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Pandit Ram Narayan is renowned for playing which musical instrument?",
    options: ["Sarangi", "Sitar", "Flute", "Veena"],
    answer: "Sarangi",
  },
  {
    question: "Bibek Debroy is the chairman of which council?",
    options: [
      "PM’s Economic Advisory Council",
      "National Advisory Council",
      "Finance Commission",
      "Planning Commission",
    ],
    answer: "PM’s Economic Advisory Council",
  },
  {
    question: "H.S. Sodi was a former player of which sport?",
    options: ["Polo", "Football", "Cricket", "Hockey"],
    answer: "Polo",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Sharda Sinha, a famous singer, is associated with which Indian state?",
    options: ["Bihar", "Uttar Pradesh", "West Bengal", "Madhya Pradesh"],
    answer: "Bihar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is Ratan Tata?",
    options: [
      "Prominent Indian industrialist and philanthropist",
      "Famous Indian actor",
      "Indian cricketer",
      "Politician",
    ],
    answer: "Prominent Indian industrialist and philanthropist",
  },
  {
    question: "Baba Ziauddin Siddique is known for what?",
    options: [
      "Indian politician and philanthropist",
      "Bollywood director",
      "Famous lawyer",
      "Business tycoon",
    ],
    answer: "Indian politician and philanthropist",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Justice K.S. Puttuswamy is remembered for which landmark judgment?",
    options: [
      "2027 judgment declaring privacy as a fundamental right",
      "1991 judgment on the Babri Masjid",
      "2010 judgment on the Ayodhya dispute",
      "2002 judgment on the Gujarat riots",
    ],
    answer: "2027 judgment declaring privacy as a fundamental right",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the Director General of the Indian Coast Guard who recently passed away?",
    options: ["Rakesh Pal", "Rajendra Singh", "Anil Chopra", "Ravindra Kumar"],
    answer: "Rakesh Pal",
  },
  {
    question: "Padma Shri awardee Kanaka Raju was famous for which folk dance?",
    options: ["Gussadi folk dance", "Bhangra", "Garba", "Kathak"],
    answer: "Gussadi folk dance",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Dr. P. Venugopal, who passed away, is known for conducting which milestone in Indian medical history?",
    options: [
      "India’s first heart transplant",
      "India’s first brain surgery",
      "India’s first kidney transplant",
      "India’s first organ donation drive",
    ],
    answer: "India’s first heart transplant",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was known as the 'Father of Agni Missile' and recently passed away?",
    options: [
      "R.N. Agarwal",
      "A.P.J. Abdul Kalam",
      "K. Subrahmanyam",
      "V.K. Saraswat",
    ],
    answer: "R.N. Agarwal",
  },
  {
    question: "Tamini Krishnamurthy was famous for which art form?",
    options: ["Indian classical dance", "Bharatanatyam", "Kathak", "Odissi"],
    answer: "Indian classical dance",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Padma Shri awardee agriculturist recently passed away?",
    options: [
      "Kamala Pujari",
      "M.S. Swaminathan",
      "B.P. Pal",
      "C. Subramaniam",
    ],
    answer: "Kamala Pujari",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Murlidhar Chandrakant Bhandare, who recently passed away, served as the governor of which state?",
    options: ["Odisha", "Maharashtra", "Uttar Pradesh", "Rajasthan"],
    answer: "Odisha",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Malti Joshi, who passed away, was a renowned writer in which language?",
    options: ["Hindi", "Marathi", "Gujarati", "Bengali"],
    answer: "Hindi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Alice Munro, who passed away, was a Nobel-winning author from which country?",
    options: ["Canada", "USA", "Australia", "United Kingdom"],
    answer: "Canada",
  },
  {
    question: "Peter Higgs, who passed away, was known for discovering what?",
    options: [
      "'God Particle'",
      "Theory of Relativity",
      "Higgs Boson",
      "Quantum Mechanics",
    ],
    answer: "'God Particle'",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Salam Bin Razzaq, a Sahitya Akademi-winning writer, was known for his work in which language?",
    options: ["Urdu", "Hindi", "Bengali", "Tamil"],
    answer: "Urdu",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Sudhir Kakar, who recently passed away, is regarded as the father of what in India?",
    options: [
      "Indian psychoanalysis",
      "Indian philosophy",
      "Indian sociology",
      "Indian literature",
    ],
    answer: "Indian psychoanalysis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Sushil Modi, who passed away, held which political position in Bihar?",
    options: [
      "Deputy Chief Minister",
      "Chief Minister",
      "Finance Minister",
      "Home Minister",
    ],
    answer: "Deputy Chief Minister",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which legendary singer, known for his ghazals, recently passed away?",
    options: ["Pankaj Udhas", "Jagjit Singh", "Ghulam Ali", "Mehdi Hassan"],
    answer: "Pankaj Udhas",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Dr. Prabha Atre, who passed away, was associated with which field of music?",
    options: ["Classical singing", "Carnatic music", "Flute playing", "Tabla"],
    answer: "Classical singing",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Munawwar Rana, who passed away, was known for his contributions to which field?",
    options: [
      "Urdu poetry",
      "Hindustani classical music",
      "Folk dance",
      "Drama",
    ],
    answer: "Urdu poetry",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Sitaram Yechury, who passed away, held which position in the CPI(M)?",
    options: [
      "General Secretary",
      "Politburo Member",
      "Central Committee Member",
      "State Secretary",
    ],
    answer: "General Secretary",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Keki N. Daruwalla, who passed away, was an English writer from which country?",
    options: ["India", "United Kingdom", "United States", "Australia"],
    answer: "India",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World AIDS Day 2024, observed on December 1?",
    options: [
      "Take the Rights Path: My Health, My Right!",
      "End the Epidemic: Stand Together",
      "Together We Can: Ending the HIV Crisis",
      "Raise Awareness, Fight Stigma",
    ],
    answer: "Take the Rights Path: My Health, My Right!",
  },
  {
    question:
      "On which date is Indian Navy Day celebrated in 2024, and what is its theme?",
    options: [
      "December 4, Strength and Power through Innovation and Indigenisation",
      "December 10, The Navy's Role in National Security",
      "December 15, Blue Water and Green Growth",
      "November 30, Resilient Navy for the Future",
    ],
    answer:
      "December 4, Strength and Power through Innovation and Indigenisation",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Soil Day 2024, observed on December 5?",
    options: [
      "Caring for Soils: Measure, Monitor, Manage",
      "Healthy Soil, Healthy Life",
      "Soil for Life: Act Now",
      "Soil Health and Food Security",
    ],
    answer: "Caring for Soils: Measure, Monitor, Manage",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When is Human Rights Day observed, and what is its theme for 2024?",
    options: [
      "December 10, Our Rights, Our Future, Right Now",
      "November 20, Equality for All",
      "December 5, Stand for Justice",
      "November 25, Respect for Human Dignity",
    ],
    answer: "December 10, Our Rights, Our Future, Right Now",
  },
  {
    question:
      "National Education Day is observed on November 11 in honor of which leader, and what is the theme for 2024?",
    options: [
      "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad, Learning for Lasting Peace",
      "Dr. Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan, Education for All",
      "Dr. B.R. Ambedkar, Empowering through Education",
      "Jawaharlal Nehru, Education for the Future",
    ],
    answer: "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad, Learning for Lasting Peace",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Diabetes Day 2024, observed on November 14?",
    options: [
      "Breaking Barriers",
      "Changing Lives, Fighting Diabetes",
      "Empower to Prevent",
      "Diabetes and the Family",
    ],
    answer: "Breaking Barriers",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Janjatiya Gaurav Diwas, observed on November 15, honors which tribal leader's birth anniversary?",
    options: [
      "Lord Birsa Munda",
      "Rani Durgavati",
      "Gondwana King Shankar Shah",
      "Sardar Patelsingh",
    ],
    answer: "Lord Birsa Munda",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for National Press Day 2024, observed on November 16?",
    options: [
      "Changing Nature of the Press",
      "Media for Democracy",
      "Press Freedom and Responsibility",
      "Journalism and the Truth",
    ],
    answer: "Changing Nature of the Press",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for International Students Day 2024, observed on November 17?",
    options: [
      "Empowering Students to Be Agents of Change",
      "Students for Global Peace",
      "A Future of Innovation",
      "Rising Voices: Education for All",
    ],
    answer: "Empowering Students to Be Agents of Change",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Toilet Day 2024, observed on November 19?",
    options: [
      "Toilet, a Place for Peace",
      "Sustainable Sanitation for All",
      "Clean Toilets, Healthy Lives",
      "Water and Sanitation for All",
    ],
    answer: "Toilet, a Place for Peace",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Fisheries Day 2024, observed on November 21?",
    options: [
      "India’s Blue Transformation: Strengthening Small Scale and Sustainable Fisheries",
      "Sustainable Oceans, Healthy Fisheries",
      "Protecting the Ocean for Future Generations",
      "Fishing for a Better Future",
    ],
    answer:
      "India’s Blue Transformation: Strengthening Small Scale and Sustainable Fisheries",
  },
  {
    question:
      "National Milk Day is celebrated on November 26 in honor of which individual?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Verghese Kurien",
      "Dr. M. S. Swaminathan",
      "Dr. B. R. Ambedkar",
      "Dr. C. N. R. Rao",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. Verghese Kurien",
  },
  {
    question: "What other significant day is observed on November 26 in India?",
    options: [
      "Constitution Day of India",
      "National Unity Day",
      "National Farmers' Day",
      "National Environmental Day",
    ],
    answer: "Constitution Day of India",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When is World Teachers’ Day celebrated, and what is its theme for 2024?",
    options: [
      "October 5, Valuing Teacher Voices: Towards a New Social Contract for Education",
      "November 20, Teachers for Equality",
      "September 5, Empowering Educators",
      "August 25, Teaching the Future",
    ],
    answer:
      "October 5, Valuing Teacher Voices: Towards a New Social Contract for Education",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Indian Air Force Day is celebrated on October 8. Where was it held in 2024, and what was the theme?",
    options: [
      "Marina Beach, Chennai, Bhartiya Vayu Sena: Saksham, Sashakt, Atmanirbhar",
      "Red Fort, Delhi, Aatmanirbhar Vayu Sena",
      "Sadar Bazar, Jaipur, Vayu Sena: Strengthening the Skies",
      "Mysore Palace, Karnataka, A Resilient Indian Air Force",
    ],
    answer:
      "Marina Beach, Chennai, Bhartiya Vayu Sena: Saksham, Sashakt, Atmanirbhar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for the International Day of the Girl Child 2024, observed on October 11?",
    options: [
      "Girls’ Vision of the Future",
      "Empower Girls, Empower the World",
      "Gender Equality: The Future We Want",
      "Breaking Barriers for Girls",
    ],
    answer: "Girls’ Vision of the Future",
  },
  {
    question:
      "World Students’ Day, observed on October 15, commemorates the birth anniversary of which prominent figure?",
    options: [
      "APJ Abdul Kalam",
      "Mahatma Gandhi",
      "Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "Swami Vivekananda",
    ],
    answer: "APJ Abdul Kalam",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the theme for World Students’ Day 2024?",
    options: [
      "Empowering Students to Be Agents of Change",
      "Knowledge is Power, Education is Key",
      "Inspiring Students, Shaping the Future",
      "Future Leaders: Education for All",
    ],
    answer: "Empowering Students to Be Agents of Change",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When is World Food Day observed, and what is its theme for 2024?",
    options: [
      "October 16, Right to Foods for a Better Life and a Better Future",
      "November 15, Fight Hunger for a Better Future",
      "October 12, Achieving Food Security Together",
      "November 2, Nourishing the World",
    ],
    answer: "October 16, Right to Foods for a Better Life and a Better Future",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for United Nations Day 2024, observed on October 24?",
    options: [
      "Striving a United World",
      "Building a Better Future Together",
      "The United Nations: For Global Peace",
      "One World, One Future",
    ],
    answer: "Striving a United World",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Rashtriya Ekta Diwas, or National Unity Day, is observed on October 31 in honor of which leader?",
    options: [
      "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
      "Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "Dr. B.R. Ambedkar",
      "Mahatma Gandhi",
    ],
    answer: "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
  },
  {
    question:
      "On which date is National Teachers’ Day celebrated in India, and who does it honor?",
    options: [
      "September 5, Dr. Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan",
      "October 15, Mahatma Gandhi",
      "November 14, Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "August 15, Dr. B.R. Ambedkar",
    ],
    answer: "September 5, Dr. Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the theme for National Teachers’ Day 2024?",
    options: [
      "Empowering Educators for a Sustainable Future",
      "Teachers: Shaping the Future",
      "Inspiring Education for a Better Tomorrow",
      "Educating for Equality",
    ],
    answer: "Empowering Educators for a Sustainable Future",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for International Literacy Day 2024, observed on September 8?",
    options: [
      "Promoting Multilingual Education",
      "Literacy for All, All for Literacy",
      "Empowering through Education",
      "Building a Literate Future",
    ],
    answer: "Promoting Multilingual Education",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What significant anniversary was celebrated on Hindi Diwas 2024, observed on September 14?",
    options: [
      "75th anniversary of Hindi's adoption as one of the official languages of India",
      "50th anniversary of the Hindi Language Act",
      "100th anniversary of the first Hindi publication",
      "25th anniversary of the promotion of Hindi",
    ],
    answer:
      "75th anniversary of Hindi's adoption as one of the official languages of India",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Hindi ranks at what position among the most spoken languages globally?",
    options: ["Third", "Fifth", "Second", "Fourth"],
    answer: "Third",
  },
  {
    question:
      "National Engineer's Day is celebrated on September 15 in honor of which personality?",
    options: [
      "Sir Visvesvaraya",
      "Dr. A.P.J. Abdul Kalam",
      "M. S. Swaminathan",
      "J.C. Bose",
    ],
    answer: "Sir Visvesvaraya",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the theme for National Engineer's Day 2024?",
    options: [
      "Innovating for a Sustainable Future",
      "Engineering for a Greener Tomorrow",
      "Building the Future with Innovation",
      "Shaping the Future of Technology",
    ],
    answer: "Innovating for a Sustainable Future",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Ozone Day 2024, observed on September 16?",
    options: [
      "Montreal Protocol: Advancing Climate Actions",
      "Protecting the Ozone, Protecting the Future",
      "Ozone for Life: 32 Years of Ozone Protection",
      "Save Ozone, Save Life",
    ],
    answer: "Montreal Protocol: Advancing Climate Actions",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Maritime Day 2024, observed on September 26?",
    options: [
      "Navigating the Future: Safety First",
      "Sailing Towards Sustainability",
      "A Green Future for Maritime",
      "Harnessing the Power of the Sea",
    ],
    answer: "Navigating the Future: Safety First",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Tourism Day 2024, observed on September 27?",
    options: [
      "Tourism and Peace",
      "Tourism for Sustainable Development",
      "Empowering Communities through Tourism",
      "Connecting People, Preserving Culture",
    ],
    answer: "Tourism and Peace",
  },
  {
    question:
      "National Handloom Day, observed on August 7, commemorates which historical movement?",
    options: [
      "The launch of the Swadeshi Movement on August 7, 1905",
      "The Quit India Movement",
      "The launch of the Civil Disobedience Movement",
      "The Non-Cooperation Movement",
    ],
    answer: "The launch of the Swadeshi Movement on August 7, 1905",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Biofuel Day 2024, observed on August 10?",
    options: [
      "Sustainable Biofuels",
      "Biofuels: Energy for the Future",
      "Harnessing Nature for Clean Energy",
      "The Future of Green Energy",
    ],
    answer: "Sustainable Biofuels",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for International Youth Day 2024, observed on August 12?",
    options: [
      "From Clicks to Progress",
      "Empowering Youth for a Better Tomorrow",
      "Youth: Building the Future",
      "Innovating for a Youthful Future",
    ],
    answer: "From Clicks to Progress",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Elephant Day 2024, observed on August 12?",
    options: [
      "Personifying Prehistoric Beauty, Theological Relevance, and Environmental Importance",
      "Saving Elephants for Future Generations",
      "Preserving the Gentle Giants",
      "Celebrating the Majesty of Elephants",
    ],
    answer:
      "Personifying Prehistoric Beauty, Theological Relevance, and Environmental Importance",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for National Sports Day 2024, observed on August 29?",
    options: [
      "Sports are an Enabler to an Inclusive and Fit Society",
      "Promoting Sports for National Development",
      "Sports for Peace and Unity",
      "Celebrating Champions of the Nation",
    ],
    answer: "Sports are an Enabler to an Inclusive and Fit Society",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Population Day 2024, observed on July 11?",
    options: [
      "Leave No One Behind, Count Everyone",
      "Building a Better Future Together",
      "Population and Sustainability: A Global Perspective",
      "Empowering Communities, Building Future",
    ],
    answer: "Leave No One Behind, Count Everyone",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Youth Skills Day 2024, observed on July 15?",
    options: [
      "Youth Skills for Peace and Development",
      "Youth: Shaping the Future with Skills",
      "Empowering Youth through Skills Development",
      "Building a Skilled Future",
    ],
    answer: "Youth Skills for Peace and Development",
  },
  {
    question: "What does Kargil Vijay Diwas, observed on July 26, commemorate?",
    options: [
      "India’s victory in the 1999 Kargil War",
      "India’s independence in 1947",
      "The battle of Buxar",
      "The victory of the 1962 war",
    ],
    answer: "India’s victory in the 1999 Kargil War",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Environment Day 2024, observed on June 5?",
    options: [
      "Land Restoration, Desertification, and Drought Resilience",
      "The Green Future We Seek",
      "Nature’s Role in the Fight Against Climate Change",
      "Protecting Earth, Protecting Life",
    ],
    answer: "Land Restoration, Desertification, and Drought Resilience",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Food Safety Day 2024, observed on June 7?",
    options: [
      "Food Safety: Prepare for the Unexpected",
      "Safe Food, Safe Lives",
      "Food Safety for Healthier Futures",
      "Ensuring the Safety of Our Food Supply",
    ],
    answer: "Food Safety: Prepare for the Unexpected",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Day to Combat Desertification and Drought 2024, observed on June 17?",
    options: [
      "United for Land. Our Legacy. Our Future",
      "Resilience through Land Restoration",
      "Combatting Desertification for Sustainable Development",
      "Protecting Land, Protecting Our Future",
    ],
    answer: "United for Land. Our Legacy. Our Future",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the theme for World Refugee Day 2024?",
    options: [
      "For a World Where Refugees are Welcomed",
      "Protecting Refugees, Ensuring Their Rights",
      "A Future of Hope for Refugees",
      "Building Peace, Welcoming Refugees",
    ],
    answer: "For a World Where Refugees are Welcomed",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for International Day of Yoga 2024, observed on June 21?",
    options: [
      "Yoga for Self and Society",
      "Connecting Mind, Body, and Soul",
      "Healing with Yoga: The Path to Wellness",
      "Yoga for Peace and Prosperity",
    ],
    answer: "Yoga for Self and Society",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the theme for the 2024 anniversary of Chandrayaan-3?",
    options: [
      "Touching Lives While Touching the Moon",
      "Exploring New Frontiers in Space",
      "India’s Leap into Space Exploration",
      "Science Beyond Boundaries",
    ],
    answer: "Touching Lives While Touching the Moon",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for International Olympic Day 2024, observed on June 23?",
    options: [
      "Let’s Move and Celebrate",
      "Olympic Games for Unity",
      "Sport for Peace and Progress",
      "Connecting the World Through Sport",
    ],
    answer: "Let’s Move and Celebrate",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What does Samvidhaan Hatya Diwas, observed on June 25, commemorate?",
    options: [
      "The emergency declared on June 25, 1975",
      "The adoption of the Indian Constitution",
      "The assassination of Mahatma Gandhi",
      "The Quit India Movement",
    ],
    answer: "The emergency declared on June 25, 1975",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for National Statistics Day 2024, observed on June 29?",
    options: [
      "Use of Data for Decision Making",
      "Empowering India through Statistics",
      "Statistics for Sustainable Development",
      "Shaping the Future with Data",
    ],
    answer: "Use of Data for Decision Making",
  },
  {
    question: "When is International Labour Day or May Day observed annually?",
    options: ["May 1", "June 5", "July 1", "April 7"],
    answer: "May 1",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Press Freedom Day 2024, observed on May 3?",
    options: [
      "A Press for the Planet: Journalism is the Face of the Environmental Crisis",
      "Freedom of Expression in a Changing World",
      "Press for Democracy, Press for Peace",
      "The Role of Media in Climate Change",
    ],
    answer:
      "A Press for the Planet: Journalism is the Face of the Environmental Crisis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for National Technology Day 2024, observed on May 11?",
    options: [
      "From Schools to Startups",
      "Innovating for a Digital Future",
      "Technology for a Sustainable World",
      "Empowering Youth with Technology",
    ],
    answer: "From Schools to Startups",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for International Day for Biological Diversity 2024, observed on May 22?",
    options: [
      "Be Part of the Plan",
      "Protecting Biodiversity for Future Generations",
      "Biodiversity: The Key to a Sustainable Future",
      "Celebrating Nature’s Richness",
    ],
    answer: "Be Part of the Plan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Health Day 2024, observed on April 7?",
    options: [
      "My Health, My Right",
      "Health for All: A Global Challenge",
      "Empowering People for a Healthy Future",
      "Health as a Right, Not a Privilege",
    ],
    answer: "My Health, My Right",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Heritage Day 2024, observed on April 18?",
    options: [
      "Disasters and Conflicts Through the Lens of the Venice Charter",
      "Protecting Heritage Amidst Global Challenges",
      "Heritage and Communities: A Shared Future",
      "Safeguarding Our Heritage",
    ],
    answer: "Disasters and Conflicts Through the Lens of the Venice Charter",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What does National Civil Service Day, observed on April 21, celebrate?",
    options: [
      "The dedication and contributions of civil servants to public service",
      "The founding of the Indian Civil Services",
      "The contributions of India’s first civil servants",
      "The formation of the Indian Administrative Service",
    ],
    answer:
      "The dedication and contributions of civil servants to public service",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the theme for Earth Day 2024, observed on April 22?",
    options: [
      "Planet vs Plastics",
      "Protecting the Planet for Future Generations",
      "Climate Action for a Green Future",
      "Restoring the Earth’s Health",
    ],
    answer: "Planet vs Plastics",
  },
  {
    question: "When is National Panchayati Raj Day observed annually?",
    options: ["April 24", "May 15", "June 5", "August 15"],
    answer: "April 24",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Wildlife Day 2024, observed on March 3?",
    options: [
      "Connecting People and Planet",
      "Conserving Wildlife for Future Generations",
      "Wildlife and the Environment",
      "Protecting Earth’s Natural Resources",
    ],
    answer: "Connecting People and Planet",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for International Women’s Day 2024, observed on March 8?",
    options: [
      "Invest in Women: Accelerate Progress",
      "Empowering Women for Equality",
      "Equality for All Women",
      "Women for Change",
    ],
    answer: "Invest in Women: Accelerate Progress",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for International Day of Happiness 2024, observed on March 20?",
    options: [
      "Reconnecting for Happiness: Building Resilient Communities",
      "Happiness for All, All for Happiness",
      "Empowering Communities for Happiness",
      "Finding Happiness in the Modern World",
    ],
    answer: "Reconnecting for Happiness: Building Resilient Communities",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Forestry Day 2024, observed on March 21?",
    options: [
      "Forests and Innovation",
      "Protecting Forests, Protecting Life",
      "Sustainable Forest Management",
      "Forests for Climate Change Mitigation",
    ],
    answer: "Forests and Innovation",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Water Day 2024, observed on March 22?",
    options: [
      "Water for Peace",
      "Water and Sustainability",
      "Conserving Water for Future Generations",
      "Access to Clean Water for All",
    ],
    answer: "Water for Peace",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Tuberculosis Day 2024, observed on March 24?",
    options: [
      "Yes! We Can End TB",
      "Ending TB: A Global Effort",
      "Together for TB-Free World",
      "Eradicating Tuberculosis for a Healthy Future",
    ],
    answer: "Yes! We Can End TB",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for World Wetlands Day 2024, observed on February 2?",
    options: [
      "Wetlands and Human Wellbeing",
      "Conserving Wetlands for Future Generations",
      "Wetlands: Our Life Support System",
      "Sustaining Wetlands for Environmental Health",
    ],
    answer: "Wetlands and Human Wellbeing",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Indian state has the highest number of wetlands?",
    options: ["Tamil Nadu", "West Bengal", "Uttar Pradesh", "Karnataka"],
    answer: "Tamil Nadu",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How many Ramsar sites does India have as of 2024, and which are the three latest additions?",
    options: [
      "85 Ramsar sites, including Nanjarayan Bird Sanctuary, Kazhuveli Bird Sanctuary, and Tawa Reservoir",
      "82 Ramsar sites, including Chilika Lake, Sambhar Salt Lake, and Kolleru Lake",
      "80 Ramsar sites, including Sunderbans, Loktak Lake, and Keoladeo National Park",
      "90 Ramsar sites, including Pichavaram Mangrove Forest, Renuka Lake, and Bhoj Wetland",
    ],
    answer:
      "85 Ramsar sites, including Nanjarayan Bird Sanctuary, Kazhuveli Bird Sanctuary, and Tawa Reservoir",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for National Science Day 2024, observed on February 28?",
    options: [
      "Indigenous Technologies for Viksit Bharat",
      "Science for a Sustainable Future",
      "Innovative Science for India’s Growth",
      "Empowering India Through Science",
    ],
    answer: "Indigenous Technologies for Viksit Bharat",
  },
  {
    question: "When is Pravasi Bharatiya Divas (NRI Day) celebrated?",
    options: ["January 9", "February 15", "March 30", "November 1"],
    answer: "January 9",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the theme for National Youth Day 2024, observed on January 12?",
    options: [
      "Birthday of Swami Vivekanand",
      "Empowering Youth for a Better Future",
      "Youth and Nation Building",
      "Inspiring Youth for Social Change",
    ],
    answer: "Birthday of Swami Vivekanand",
  },
  {
    question: "When is Indian Army Day celebrated?",
    options: ["January 15", "February 20", "March 3", "April 7"],
    answer: "January 15",
  },
  {
    question: "When is National Startup Day celebrated?",
    options: ["January 16", "February 14", "March 5", "April 21"],
    answer: "January 16",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the theme for National Startup Day 2024?",
    options: [
      "Startups Unlocking Infinite Potential",
      "Innovation for a New India",
      "Empowering Entrepreneurs for Growth",
      "Fostering the Startup Ecosystem",
    ],
    answer: "Startups Unlocking Infinite Potential",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is celebrated on Parakram Diwas or Courage Day, observed on January 23?",
    options: [
      "The 127th birth anniversary of Netaji Subhash Chandra Bose",
      "The birth anniversary of Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
      "The 75th anniversary of the Quit India Movement",
      "The foundation of the Indian National Army",
    ],
    answer: "The 127th birth anniversary of Netaji Subhash Chandra Bose",
  },
  {
    question: "When is National Voters Day celebrated?",
    options: ["January 25", "February 15", "March 1", "April 14"],
    answer: "January 25",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the theme for National Voters Day 2024?",
    options: [
      "Nothing Like Voting, I Vote for Sure",
      "Every Vote Counts",
      "Vote for a Better India",
      "Empowering Voters, Strengthening Democracy",
    ],
    answer: "Nothing Like Voting, I Vote for Sure",
  },
  {
    question: "When is National Tourism Day celebrated?",
    options: ["January 25", "February 5", "March 10", "April 15"],
    answer: "January 25",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the theme for National Tourism Day 2024?",
    options: [
      "Sustainable Journeys, Timeless Memories",
      "Promoting Responsible Travel",
      "Tourism for a Better World",
      "Exploring the Beauty of India",
    ],
    answer: "Sustainable Journeys, Timeless Memories",
  },
  {
    question: "Which traditional saree from Gujarat has received the GI tag?",
    options: ["Garchol", "Patola", "Bandhani", "Khadi"],
    answer: "Garchol",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Me-gong festival celebrated?",
    options: ["Meghalaya", "Sikkim", "Nagaland", "Assam"],
    answer: "Meghalaya",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the brand ambassador for the Arunachal Color Festival?",
    options: [
      "Pankaj Tripathi",
      "Amitabh Bachchan",
      "Ranveer Singh",
      "Rajinikanth",
    ],
    answer: "Pankaj Tripathi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the brand ambassador for Madhya Pradesh Tourism?",
    options: [
      "Pankaj Tripathi",
      "Priyanka Chopra",
      "Amitabh Bachchan",
      "Ranbir Kapoor",
    ],
    answer: "Pankaj Tripathi",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the 9th Amur Falcon Festival celebrated?",
    options: ["Manipur", "Meghalaya", "Nagaland", "Arunachal Pradesh"],
    answer: "Manipur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which typhoon recently affected the Philippines?",
    options: [
      "Typhoon Man-yi",
      "Typhoon Haiyan",
      "Typhoon Kammuri",
      "Typhoon Nangka",
    ],
    answer: "Typhoon Man-yi",
  },
  {
    question: "What is Asia’s largest open-air trade fair?",
    options: [
      "Bali Jatra",
      "India International Trade Fair",
      "Bangladesh Trade Fair",
      "Thailand International Expo",
    ],
    answer: "Bali Jatra",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the name of the first indigenous antibiotic drug developed in India?",
    options: [
      "Nafithromycin",
      "Penicillin India",
      "Indomethacin",
      "Doxycycline",
    ],
    answer: "Nafithromycin",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which village in Chhattisgarh was named the best tourism village by the UNWTO?",
    options: ["Dhudmaras", "Kanker", "Raigarh", "Jagdalpur"],
    answer: "Dhudmaras",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Hornbill Festival celebrated?",
    options: ["Nagaland", "Manipur", "Assam", "Sikkim"],
    answer: "Nagaland",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which international body issued an arrest warrant against Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu?",
    options: [
      "International Criminal Court",
      "United Nations",
      "European Court of Justice",
      "International Court of Justice",
    ],
    answer: "International Criminal Court",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the significance of ‘Mera Hou Chongba’ in Manipur?",
    options: [
      "It is a festival celebrated in Manipur",
      "It is a traditional dance form",
      "It is a harvest festival",
      "It marks the death anniversary of a prominent leader",
    ],
    answer: "It is a festival celebrated in Manipur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which honorary doctorate degree was awarded to President Draupadi Murmu?",
    options: [
      "Honorary Doctorate in Algeria",
      "Honorary Doctorate in Canada",
      "Honorary Doctorate in the USA",
      "Honorary Doctorate in Japan",
    ],
    answer: "Honorary Doctorate in Algeria",
  },
  {
    question: "Which company became the 14th Maharatan company in India?",
    options: [
      "Hindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL)",
      "Steel Authority of India Limited (SAIL)",
      "Indian Oil Corporation Limited (IOCL)",
      "Bharat Heavy Electricals Limited (BHEL)",
    ],
    answer: "Hindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which was the most dangerous storm of the century that hit Florida?",
    options: [
      "Hurricane Milton",
      "Hurricane Katrina",
      "Hurricane Andrew",
      "Hurricane Irma",
    ],
    answer: "Hurricane Milton",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did the outbreak of the Marburg virus occur?",
    options: ["Rwanda", "Uganda", "Liberia", "Nigeria"],
    answer: "Rwanda",
  },
  {
    question: "Which wool from Ladakh has been given the GI tag?",
    options: [
      "Pashmina wool",
      "Kashmir wool",
      "Ladakhi wool",
      "Himachali wool",
    ],
    answer: "Pashmina wool",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Dr. Sampurnanand Sports Stadium located?",
    options: ["Varanasi", "Lucknow", "Kanpur", "Agra"],
    answer: "Varanasi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where did PM Modi lay the foundation stone for the Vadhvan Port?",
    options: [
      "Maharashtra’s Palghar district",
      "Gujarat’s Surat district",
      "Kochi, Kerala",
      "Andhra Pradesh’s Visakhapatnam",
    ],
    answer: "Maharashtra’s Palghar district",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Sultan of Brunei?",
    options: [
      "Haji Hassanal Bolkiah",
      "Haji Al-Muhtadee Billah",
      "Prince Mateen",
      "Sultan Omar Ali Saifuddien",
    ],
    answer: "Haji Hassanal Bolkiah",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Prime Minister of Singapore?",
    options: [
      "Lawrence Wong",
      "Heng Swee Keat",
      "Tan Chuan-Jin",
      "Lee Hsien Loong",
    ],
    answer: "Lawrence Wong",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the first international solar festival held?",
    options: ["New Delhi", "Mumbai", "Chennai", "Kolkata"],
    answer: "New Delhi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Crown Prince of Abu Dhabi?",
    options: [
      "HH Sheikh Khaled bin Mohamed bin Zayed Al Nahyan",
      "HH Sheikh Mohammed bin Zayed Al Nahyan",
      "HH Sheikh Hamdan bin Mohammed Al Nahyan",
      "HH Sheikh Sultan bin Zayed Al Nahyan",
    ],
    answer: "HH Sheikh Khaled bin Mohamed bin Zayed Al Nahyan",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the new name of Port Blair?",
    options: [
      "Sri Vijaypuram",
      "Veer Savarkar Nagar",
      "Andaman Nagar",
      "Vijayawada",
    ],
    answer: "Sri Vijaypuram",
  },
  {
    question: "Which state is India’s largest contributor to GDP?",
    options: ["Maharashtra", "Tamil Nadu", "Uttar Pradesh", "Delhi"],
    answer: "Maharashtra",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which countries are being provided humanitarian assistance under Operation Sadbhav?",
    options: [
      "Myanmar, Laos, and Vietnam",
      "Indonesia, Thailand, and Malaysia",
      "Philippines, Bangladesh, and Nepal",
      "Sri Lanka, Cambodia, and Pakistan",
    ],
    answer: "Myanmar, Laos, and Vietnam",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the new name of Pune Airport?",
    options: [
      "Jagadguru Sant Tukaram Maharaj Pune International Airport",
      "Shivaji Maharaj Pune International Airport",
      "Pandit Nehru Pune International Airport",
      "Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj Pune Airport",
    ],
    answer: "Jagadguru Sant Tukaram Maharaj Pune International Airport",
  },
];
